<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of Ioseph a poem / written by Daniel Cudmore, Gent.</title>
            <author>Cudmore, Daniel, 17th cent.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1652</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 178 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A35338</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing C7462</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R20251</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12259071</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12259071</idno>
            <idno type="VID">57741</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A35338)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 57741)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 178:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of Ioseph a poem / written by Daniel Cudmore, Gent.</title>
                  <author>Cudmore, Daniel, 17th cent.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[5], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T. Warren for the use of the author,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1652.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-11</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:57741:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57741:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF IOSEPH. A POEM</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Written by</hi> DANIEL CUDMORE, <hi>Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <l>Say not, my hand this work to end hath brought,</l>
               <l>Nor this my vertue hath attained to:</l>
               <l>Say rather thus, this God by me hath wrought;</l>
               <l>God's th' Authour of the little good I do.</l>
               <bibl>Du Bart. <hi>in Quadrians of Pabr.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON, Printed by <hi>T. Warren</hi> for the uſe of the Author, 1652.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:57741:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:57741:2"/>
            <head>To his much reſpected Vncle Mr. ZACHARY CUDMORE all health and happineſs.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">P</seg>Romiſes are due debt; you were pleaſed not long ſince, ſo far to encourage my en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>devours as to claim this Poem; which I (having nothing which I might truly ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogate to my ſelf, but you might juſtly challenge yours, as purchas'd by your fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vours) thankfully promiſed; and now at length, like <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Butler, on the conſideration of your manifold Curteſies, being check'd to a remembrance of my promiſe, humbly tender, and with it (like the poor <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niard,</hi> who when a Father of the Inquiſition deſired but the Fruit, preſented him the Tree) preſent my ſelf; ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept this with the like candour of mind, as I devote it with it really, and I ſhall eſteem my hopes anchor'd in a happy Bay. If any upbraid me, being a Poet, with the fatall name of a begger, I anſwer with the ſweet Singer of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el <hi>Adhuc &amp; vilior fiam,</hi> ſo I may but herein do God the leaſt ſervice, and ſo render my ſelf gracious to your ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance; nor doubt I but time may ſo midwife it, that here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after I may tender ſome thing which may (if not redeem ſome of my engagements) yet induce your courteſie to forbear the debts wherein ſtands obliged</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your obſervant Nephew, DAN. CUD.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:57741:3"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Courteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Here preſent thee with the Hiſtory of <hi>Joſeph,</hi> which as I could ſeldome paſs over without tears, ſo I could not but digeſt them into matter through the Lymbeck of my Quill, though into ſuch a form as my moſe eaſie <hi>Genius</hi> lead me; 'tis a ſubject, I confeſs, which ſeems to claim both a more elaborate Brain, and a more accu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate Pen than mine, yet ſhall I neither eſteem my labour loſt, nor my time ill-beſtow'd, if I may herein prove but the <hi>Foyl</hi> of thoſe who have writ more gravely on the ſame matter, that in my weakneſs may the more clearly appear their worth. If thou object, that in the p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſſage between <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his wanton Miſtris, I have rendred my ſelf. <hi>Pathick</hi> than <hi>Pathetick,</hi> I may anſwer firſt, that I have deſcribed her Paſſion in as grave a Wantonneſt as the tenour of her <hi>broad expreſſions</hi> would permit; Secondly, for the frequency of it, the Text tells me that it was her daily practice; Thirdly, I have an example from <hi>Solomon</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, who, (doubtleſs guided by Gods Spirit) ſets forth a Harlot thus in her courteous vanities; In the laſt place, I hope <hi>His</hi> modeſt anſwers which ſtruck, for the preſent, the impatient opponent dumb, will take off a judicious cenſure from reply. What I here preſent thee, is mine own, what thou haſt here is no <hi>Crambes bis cocta,</hi> no Page, <hi>furtivis ornata colori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> nor can my fancy upbraid my Pen, as 'tis to be fear'd, God will one day our new compounded faſhions, <hi>Hoc non eſt opus meum, imago mea.</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Farewell.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="poem">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:57741:3"/>
            <head>The hiſtory of <hi>Joſeph,</hi>
            </head>
            <lg>
               <head>The <hi>Proem.</hi>
               </head>
               <l>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Sing of <hi>Joſeph's</hi> fate, our <hi>Saviour's type,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then <hi>heaven</hi> bee <hi>auſpicious</hi> to my <hi>pipe;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>What though my <hi>fancie's dull,</hi> my <hi>ſtile's unfil'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My <hi>Pia-mater</hi> be an infant-child,</l>
               <l>This be a task for <hi>Angells,</hi> each whoſe page</l>
               <l>(If fully peraphras'd,) would crave an age?</l>
               <l>Each <hi>Angel</hi> is my <hi>muſe, Sion</hi> the <hi>hill</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>ſacred raptures</hi> ſhall <hi>intrance</hi> my <hi>quill;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And if divine <hi>Apollo</hi> tune my <hi>harp,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Let <hi>Zoilus</hi> cenſure, and let <hi>Momus</hi> carp.</l>
               <l>Then, where the <hi>Dove-like Spirit</hi> daignes us matter,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Owles</hi> forbear to <hi>ſcreech,</hi> and <hi>Pies</hi> to <hi>chatter.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here is a <hi>ſtory,</hi> each whoſe circumſtance</l>
               <l>Is to b'aſcrib'd to <hi>providence</hi> not <hi>chance,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Compar'd to this all <hi>humane eloquence</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth ſcarce deſerve the <hi>bounteous name of ſenſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here is a ſtory, whoſe <hi>ſublime invention</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So farr tranſcends mans <hi>reach,</hi> and weak <hi>dimenſion,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A ſtory here, whoſe <hi>fancie's towring hight</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doth ſoar ſo high beyond our <hi>dull conceit</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All wits ſhould here their <hi>conquer'd lawrels</hi> bring,</l>
               <l>Their <hi>Helicons</hi> are <hi>puddles</hi> to this <hi>ſpring.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then <hi>ſacred Three in One,</hi> who in this ſtory</l>
               <l>Didſt from mans wickedneſs procure thee glory,</l>
               <l>O let my <hi>weakneſſe tun'd in ſlender layes</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Advance</hi> thy honour, and <hi>promote</hi> thy praiſe;</l>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:57741:4"/>
               <l>Then I'll invoke no <hi>Heliconian dame,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If thou but <hi>rarifie the ſmoakie flame</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That actuates my fancy,</hi> and but drain</l>
               <l>From 'its polluted dreggs my youthfull brain.</l>
               <l>My pen thus dipt in the true <hi>Theſpian stream,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus do I proſecute my ſacred theam.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>THE heav'nly regiſter of ſacred truth</l>
               <l>Records old <hi>Jacobs</hi> age, bleſt with a youth</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> by name; whoſe vertue from the reſt</l>
               <l>Had won the chiefeſt room in <hi>Jacobs</hi> breſt.</l>
               <l>Th' equall proportion of both face, and limb</l>
               <l>(Requir'd in outward beauty) was in him,</l>
               <l>So here, was that more noble <hi>Symnetry</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A heav'nly heart, the rarer <hi>harmony:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For though no <hi>Architect</hi> will ever chooſe</l>
               <l>The <hi>ſtately marble</hi> but to <hi>noble</hi> uſe,</l>
               <l>And in a palace what a ſtately, gueſt</l>
               <l>Is entertain'd, may by the pomp be <hi>gheſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Beautie's oft Bawd to vice,</hi> a heav'nly fiend,</l>
               <l>Sin oft abounds where beauty doth tranſcend;</l>
               <l>Whoſe <hi>Angells image,</hi> as it oft appears,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſuperſcription of the Devill</hi> bears.</l>
               <l>Our <hi>Joſeph's</hi> lovely viſage ſome that viewd</l>
               <l>Thought <hi>Adams</hi> native beauty here renewd;</l>
               <l>His ſpotleſſe innocence by others was</l>
               <l>Compar'd to <hi>Adam</hi> in his ſtate of grace;</l>
               <l>For he muſt moſt be void of all offence</l>
               <l>Who was the perfect'ſt <hi>type</hi> of <hi>innocence.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>God who in mercy did to <hi>Abraham</hi> ſwear</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That he ſhould vie a child with ev'ry ſtar,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Here of his promiſe as the <hi>Intereſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Fixt <hi>Joſeph</hi> as a ſtar to guide the reſt.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fixt ſtar?</hi> nay rather <hi>planet,</hi> ſince his fate</l>
               <l>Was to be exil'd by his Brethrens hate.</l>
               <l>Time now had writ old age on <hi>Jacobs</hi> skull,</l>
               <l>And long ſince chang'd his down to rougher wooll,</l>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:57741:4"/>
               <l>When faint diſeaſe did on his members creep</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hee</hi> to his ſons reſign'd his charge of ſheep;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> was always at his fathers beck,</l>
               <l>Each frown, a wound did ſeem, a death each check,</l>
               <l>And who but wondring ſaw that he ſhould bring</l>
               <l>So full an harveſt in his youthfull ſpring?</l>
               <l>Which much in <hi>Jacobs</hi> thoughts did him promote,</l>
               <l>Who clad him in a <hi>parti-colour'd coat;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Brethren ſee'ng their <hi>Father</hi> ſo inclin'd</l>
               <l>At his indulgence proudly thus repin'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>He's <hi>Jacobs ſeed elixard,</hi> we the dreggs,</l>
               <l>Baſe chicken we, born of unhappy eggs,</l>
               <l>Quoth one, we to no other end are born</l>
               <l>But t'wear out wooll or to conſume the corn,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> the white hens chick, <hi>he, Fortunes minion;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His childiſh face hath purchas'd this opinion,</l>
               <l>Yet is no more like to my lad (God knows)</l>
               <l>Than is you <hi>cowſlip</hi> to a <hi>verdant roſe,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>A <hi>Kid</hi> t'a <hi>Lamb,</hi> my <hi>Ewe</hi> to yonder Goat,</l>
               <l>Yet he's inveſted in a gawdy coat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſince diſeaſe, which ſtill attends on age,</l>
               <l>Confin'd had <hi>Jacob</hi> to an Hermitage,</l>
               <l>And <hi>he</hi> whoſe diſcipline was wont to awe</l>
               <l>His ſons, and give unto their deeds a law,</l>
               <l>The <hi>Sunſhine</hi> of whoſe preſence would diſperſe</l>
               <l>Such vapours, vice could here have no commerce,</l>
               <l>Declining was, no wonder there appears</l>
               <l>If pitchie vapours now did blot the ſphears,</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Joſeph</hi> knew, when he in humble ſort</l>
               <l>Vnto his father brought their ill report,</l>
               <l>Yet not in baſe revenge, and ranc'rous ſpleen,</l>
               <l>As is in ſome maligning Brethren ſeen,</l>
               <l>Who ſtrive to raiſe the <hi>Trophies</hi> of their name,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Triumph,</hi> on the <hi>Tombes</hi> of others ſhame,</l>
               <l>Or ſome, as if their envie were ſo nice</l>
               <l>To wound the Perſon, and to ſpare the Vice:</l>
               <l>But <hi>Joſeph's</hi> heart with Zealous ſorrow bleeds</l>
               <l>While to his father he rehea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſt their deeds.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay, further thus, he did exaſperate</l>
               <l>His Brethrens ſpleen, and mov'd their ſweiling hate;</l>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:57741:5"/>
               <l>Quoth he <hi>Dear Brethren, not a foggy ſtream</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From a diſtemper'd liver, no vain theam,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ingroſt my fancie, when thus (by your leaves)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I dreampt, you and my ſelf were binding ſheaves,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>My ſheaf (me thought) roſe up; all your's, in ſigne</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of duty, did obeyſance unto mine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His Brethren ſtart and check him, how ſo plain?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And muſt thou thus become our King, and raign?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>True; in your robes your <hi>Majeſtie's</hi> impall'd,</l>
               <l>Oh how we long to ſee your <hi>grace</hi> inſtall'd?</l>
               <l>A ſcepter for him, no, thou ſawcy ſwain,</l>
               <l>A <hi>Rod</hi> to whip thee to thy wits again.</l>
               <l>Nay further, harmleſſe <hi>Joſeph</hi> did incur</l>
               <l>Their hate, which needed not a ſecond ſpur;</l>
               <l>Brethren quoth he, No aim to diſinherit</l>
               <l>You of your Birth-right; 'tis no private Spirit;</l>
               <l>My head like th' higheſt region of the air</l>
               <l>From all ſuch Meteors is pure and fair,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I dream'd the Sun and Mo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> did with a troop</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of'leven ſtarrs, unto mee humbly ſtoop.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No ſooner ſpoke, but all his <hi>Brethren</hi> rouz,</l>
               <l>One ſtamps and fumes, another frownes and vowes,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Muſt Father, Mother, and we all eleven</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Submit to thee!</hi> how long ſince cam'ſt from heaven?</l>
               <l>When is your <hi>Majeſtie's inauguration,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>King</hi> of your <hi>country, Father of your nation?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Theſe <hi>Temples</hi> are too ſtately to be bound</l>
               <l>With roſie <hi>Chaplets,</hi> no, they muſt be crown'd;</l>
               <l>Theſe armes of late too maſſie grown to weigh</l>
               <l>The worthleſſe ſheephook, muſt a ſcepter ſway.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> takes all with an unfurrow'd brow,</l>
               <l>And mildly crowcheth with a lowly bow,</l>
               <l>Anon unto his Father tells again</l>
               <l>The heav'nly dreams of his inſpired brain;</l>
               <l>Who though his ſon was yet in years but green,</l>
               <l>It fills him more with wonder than with ſpleen;</l>
               <l>Quoth he <hi>Thine</hi> and thy Brothers purity</l>
               <l>Spark like a conſtellation in my skie;</l>
               <l>In whom Vice ne'r could get a patronage,</l>
               <l>Free from the ſins that do ingroſs this age,</l>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:57741:5"/>
               <l>But that I with the reſt ſhall proſtitute</l>
               <l>Submiſſively to thee I yet diſpute;</l>
               <l>This in the Brethren had ill blood begotten,</l>
               <l>Which by hot rage was ſoon to rancour rotten,</l>
               <l>And yet no opportunity had been,</l>
               <l>That they might vomit their impoſtum'd ſpleen.</l>
               <l>Time was when youthfull <hi>Joſeph</hi>'s Brethren fed</l>
               <l>Their fleecy charge on <hi>Shechems</hi> flow'ry bed,</l>
               <l>Anon-their wanton Lambkins further rov'd,</l>
               <l>And they with them to <hi>Dothan</hi> next remov'd,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Jacob</hi> calling <hi>Joſeph</hi> to his tent</l>
               <l>With ſuch like words <hi>him</hi> to his Brethren ſent;</l>
               <l>Run, and make haſt again, my darling ſon,</l>
               <l>On whoſe lifes thread, <hi>that,</hi> of my life is ſpun;</l>
               <l>I through whoſe Organs breath my life, and whoſe</l>
               <l>Eys if long abſent, <hi>mine</hi> would quickly cloſe;</l>
               <l>Theſe apples in thy cheek, my pretty page,</l>
               <l>Are th' onely food that do ſuſtain my age;</l>
               <l>Thou knowſt in <hi>Shechem</hi> now thy Brethren are,</l>
               <l>Run, and bring how they and their flocks do fare.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Obedience, wing'd with loyalty now poſts</l>
               <l>With nimble ſpeed to <hi>Shechems</hi> paſt'rall coaſts,</l>
               <l>And finding not his Brethren there, he wanders</l>
               <l>In crooked by-paths, mazes and Meanders,</l>
               <l>Thus roved he perplex'd, till found by one,</l>
               <l>Who told him they to <hi>Dothan</hi> late were gone;</l>
               <l>Thither he bends, and might anon behold</l>
               <l>His Brethren, and their flocks, as late was told.</l>
               <l>One of his Brethren ſeeing him, in haſt</l>
               <l>Cryes yonder commeth our <hi>Enthuſiaſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>All with conſent giv'd way to headſtrong fury,</l>
               <l>Sans the convention of the ſacred Jury</l>
               <l>Of reaſon love and faith, <hi>Joſeph</hi> muſt die,</l>
               <l>Grim death ſhall caſt him in a <hi>Lethargy.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then when he wakes let him with dreams out-brave</l>
               <l>Our thoughts, thus ſlain let's caſt him in ſome Cave.</l>
               <l>This ſaid thus ſtarts up <hi>Reuben,</hi> Heav'n forbid</l>
               <l>We ſhould be guilty all of fratricide,</l>
               <l>Forbear, the milder Citizens of th' wood</l>
               <l>Upon each tree will carve this theam of blood,</l>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:57741:6"/>
               <l>Forbear, the Fiſh will loſe their being mute,</l>
               <l>Each Bird 'gainſt murther quaintly will diſpute;</l>
               <l>Forbear, our Lambs with bleating Oratory</l>
               <l>When they come home will tell of <hi>Joſephs</hi> ſtory,</l>
               <l>Our Heards miſcarry, and each pregnant Ew</l>
               <l>Enix abortive Lamb-kins at the view;</l>
               <l>Forbear, the raging winds will burſt their lungs</l>
               <l>And in articulate tones pronounce his wrongs.</l>
               <l>O be not taught by ſelf-experience,</l>
               <l>Conſider <hi>Cains</hi> juſt curſe for this offence;</l>
               <l>And ſince God is the ſame, can we expect</l>
               <l>But like proceedings ſhould have like effect?</l>
               <l>Yet if your charity cannot forgive,</l>
               <l>Then let humanity grant that he live;</l>
               <l>Into the pit let's caſt the ſilly Swain,</l>
               <l>So ſpoke, that he might ſet him free again.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, our nimble youth with active pace</l>
               <l>Where they conſulted had attaind the place;</l>
               <l>All ruſh on him God ſave our Soveraign ſheaf,</l>
               <l>Nay prethee ſpeak not, reſolution's deaf;</l>
               <l>Do'ſt bluſh? wee'l empty all theſe veins of blood</l>
               <l>As clean as is thy ſoul from grace and good;</l>
               <l>This is the coat, this that Majeſtick ſute,</l>
               <l>To which we all muſt humbly proſtitute,</l>
               <l>A coat of Sack-cloth for to expiate</l>
               <l>Thy ſin, and to appeaſe deſerved hate,</l>
               <l>Far better would become thee, thou ſhalt die,</l>
               <l>Pale death ſhall cloath thee in her livery;</l>
               <l>What, not a word unleſs you wear a Crown?</l>
               <l>Pray knit your brows, wee'l tremble at your frown;</l>
               <l>I prethee weep; I prethee ſigh, my Boy,</l>
               <l>That we may dance, that we may ſing for joy;</l>
               <l>Let's place him on yon-hillock, for a throne,</l>
               <l>Then to his Majeſtie wee'll all fall proue;</l>
               <l>Come, come, ſtrip off this coat, and next prepare</l>
               <l>For to uncloath thy ſoul; why doſt thou ſtare?</l>
               <l>Rapt in ſome ſtrange <hi>Enthuſiaſm</hi> we know;</l>
               <l>Death, quoth another, ſhall intrance him now.</l>
               <l>At this our youth grew pale, his blood retreats,</l>
               <l>And to his heart a fierce alarum beats,</l>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:57741:6"/>
               <l>Knees bended, hands expans'd, erected eye,</l>
               <l>All ſilent Rhet'rick of humility,</l>
               <l>Got nought but this, We will without remorſe,</l>
               <l>Of ſoul and body make a quick divorce,</l>
               <l>Like poor <hi>Abſyrtus</hi> by his Siſter ſlain,</l>
               <l>Or wretched <hi>Itis</hi> ſo he beg'd in vain;</l>
               <l>Quoth he, I doe not uſe this bootleſs ſtrife,</l>
               <l>For to obtain that worthleſs name of life,</l>
               <l>I fear not death; yet Brethren, pittie take</l>
               <l>If not for mine, yet for my Fathers ſake;</l>
               <l>Since ther's a God, to Heaven I appeal,</l>
               <l>If I you hate, may not the ſtones conceal</l>
               <l>But give me ſtrait the lie, my ſoul is white,</l>
               <l>Black guilt on her ne'r could ſuch treſpaſs write;</l>
               <l>If that it could then I would never grudge,</l>
               <l>Nay ſhould my ſelf-condemn were I my Judge;</l>
               <l>Had I deſerv'd death I'd yeeld to dye,</l>
               <l>Juſtice ſhould ſwill untill my veins were dry.</l>
               <l>Oh how his pittie-pleading eyes would view</l>
               <l>Now ſadly one, then to another ſue!</l>
               <l>Then to their unrelenting Breſts would fly,</l>
               <l>Claſping their necks, Sweet Brethren pitty me.</l>
               <l>The true imagination of his pains</l>
               <l>Doth make my blood carcer within my veins;</l>
               <l>When I think on't my paſſion is ſo wild,</l>
               <l>I ſtart, and cry as preſent, Save the child.</l>
               <l>My fingers fayl and in perplex'd demurs</l>
               <l>Inſtead of words my pen indenteth blurs;</l>
               <l>My heart doth quake my joints are all benum'd,</l>
               <l>My trembling tongue unto my jaws is gum'd:</l>
               <l>Yet not for him alone, but for my Saviour</l>
               <l>Of whom <hi>he</hi> was the type, with worſe behaviour</l>
               <l>They uſed him of old, let every age</l>
               <l>At once preſent their Scenes upon one Stage,</l>
               <l>And all the miſeries in Hiſtory</l>
               <l>Coucht in moſt tragick prodigality,</l>
               <l>And in moſt gorgeous rhetorick expreſt,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>his</hi> but in their naked colours dreſt</l>
               <l>Would ſhew moſt gaudy, ſuch as would inforce</l>
               <l>Ev'n Pagans unto mourning and remorſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:57741:7"/>
               <l>Anon our Brethren did deliberate,</l>
               <l>Not to extenuate but defer their hate,</l>
               <l>Till all the horrour of their wittieſt rage</l>
               <l>Might wait on death in horrid equipage.</l>
               <l>Mean while of <hi>Reubens</hi> counſell they admit,</l>
               <l>And (void of mercy) caſt him in the pit;</l>
               <l>Where if they meant him meat for Wolves or Bears,</l>
               <l>Or in the empty pit to drown in tears,</l>
               <l>Or left him there a prey to greedy famine,</l>
               <l>The text is ſilent, nor may I examine.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mild <hi>Reuben</hi> joyfull that by this perſwaſion</l>
               <l>He ſtopt their fury, thought by this evaſion</l>
               <l>When the dark night might, with his care conſpire,</l>
               <l>To free young <hi>Joſeph</hi> from his Brethrensire,</l>
               <l>Wherefore he cri'd I'm void from this offence.</l>
               <l>Bear witneſſe heaven of my Innocence,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now when they had left <hi>Joſeph,</hi> and were dining,</l>
               <l>And in a bloody <hi>ſynod</hi> were combining,</l>
               <l>They lifted up their eies, and might diſcern</l>
               <l>A company, which they anon might learn</l>
               <l>Were <hi>Midianites,</hi> whoſe trade was merchandice,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Gilead</hi> Balm, gum, mirrh, and fragrant ſpice,</l>
               <l>For <hi>Egypt</hi> on their bunch-back'd Camels bound,</l>
               <l>Which ſeen, thus <hi>Judah</hi> riſeth from the ground;</l>
               <l>Brethren, quoth he, the blood in <hi>Joſephs</hi> veines</l>
               <l>The ſelf ſame tincture with our own retaines,</l>
               <l>And from the ſelf-ſame chanell it derives</l>
               <l>As we do <hi>that</hi> which actuates our lives,</l>
               <l>He is our fleſh, let not his blood be ſpilt</l>
               <l>(Since murther cann't be hid) leſt that the guilt</l>
               <l>On us and our poſterity intail</l>
               <l>A curſe, from death let forefight be his bayl;</l>
               <l>Come then, let's ſell him to yon merchant-crew,</l>
               <l>And then ſee what will of his dreams enſue;</l>
               <l>The Brethren all aſſent to this advice,</l>
               <l>And one is ſent to barter for the price.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quoth he, Good ſirs we have in yonder cave</l>
               <l>A ſmooth-fac'd lad, whom you may buy your ſlave,</l>
               <l>Whom we would ſell at reaſonable price</l>
               <l>Of gold, or ſilver, mirth, ſweet balm, or ſpice:</l>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:57741:7"/>
               <l>Mean while our youth (bleſſing their cruelty</l>
               <l>That yet where God ſate thron'd he ſaw the skie)</l>
               <l>Thus prayd, Great God of Angels, and of Man,</l>
               <l>Who meteſt out yon heavens with the ſpan,</l>
               <l>Who ſtretch'ſt them like a curtain, and canſt roll</l>
               <l>Them up together like a Parchment ſcroll,</l>
               <l>I've not deſerv'd this at my Brethrens hands,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>greater,</hi> by tranſgreſſing thy commands,</l>
               <l>And ſince thou by the hate, doſt me reprove,</l>
               <l>Of thoſe, of whom I moſt did hope for love,</l>
               <l>'Tis juſt, 'gainſt thee I oft commit offence,</l>
               <l>Who moſt of me expectedſt reverence:</l>
               <l>Yet if I by my Brethren yeeld my breath,</l>
               <l>O pardon me, and pardon them my death.</l>
               <l>No ſooner had he voyc'd this prayer, when</l>
               <l>His furious Brethren had approacht the den,</l>
               <l>Whence having took him up by tackled cords,</l>
               <l>Who look'd for nought but death, they uſe theſe words,</l>
               <l>Look you, quoth one, look yonder are thy maſters,</l>
               <l>Wee'll give thee time to weep at thy diſaſters;</l>
               <l>Forſake thy native for a forreign land,</l>
               <l>Where this fair skin ſhall be Sun-parch'd and tand;</l>
               <l>Prepare theſe dainty limbs t'endure the gripes</l>
               <l>Of hardeſt labour, and theſe ſides for ſtripes;</l>
               <l>Prepare this dainty palate to be parch'd</l>
               <l>With thirſt, this ſtomach to be hunger-ſearch'd.</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Joſeph,</hi> if you will not pitty take</l>
               <l>For mine, nor <hi>Jacobs,</hi> then for heavens ſake</l>
               <l>Here let me ſtarve, here let me dig my grave</l>
               <l>Within this pit, O ſell me not a ſlave.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>I'd weep ſuch characters, my tears ſhould trace</l>
               <l>Such <hi>Water-works</hi> upon my blubberd face,</l>
               <l>Whoſe intricate <hi>Meanders</hi> ſhould out-vie</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Trajans</hi> or <hi>Buſhells</hi> in <hi>Hydrography.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>His mones no more appeaſe their raging minds</l>
               <l>Than can a Sea-mans whiſtle ſtill the winds;</l>
               <l>But <hi>him for twenty ſilver pieces ſell,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And with a ſcornfull look they bid farewell.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As <hi>Arethuſa</hi> through the mazes led</l>
               <l>Of the dark earth, through her incloſed bed,</l>
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:57741:8"/>
               <l>At length makes paſſage, ſo my ſorrow ſwels,</l>
               <l>O'r flows my Brain, and drowns my brinie cels;</l>
               <l>Their names, and natures ſeem to ſuit each other,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Judas</hi> ſold <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Judah</hi> ſold his Brother,</l>
               <l>And when I ſin how can't be underſtood</l>
               <l>But that I'm guilty of my Saviours blood!</l>
               <l>I ſold him, and he bought me, yet in vain,</l>
               <l>For I each day doe barter him again;</l>
               <l>Sins are too pregnant, that they ſhould appear</l>
               <l>So far remov'd, only in <hi>Plato's</hi> year:</l>
               <l>Their Brother by the <hi>Patriarks</hi> of old,</l>
               <l>After our Saviour was by <hi>Iudas</hi> ſold,</l>
               <l>Men are liv'd o'r again; O could our times</l>
               <l>Non guilty plead from ſuch unnat'rall crimes!</l>
               <l>For ſpurious vices are hereditary,</l>
               <l>Though th' ages vaniſh, and the ſeaſons vary.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now nights dark mantle had the world behung,</l>
               <l>Nights Quiriſter her ev'ning notes had ſung,</l>
               <l>And carefull <hi>Reuben</hi> thinking all ſecure,</l>
               <l>Darkneſs at hand that might his care mature,</l>
               <l>Unto his Brother hies, and comming near</l>
               <l>He cries aloud dear Brother <hi>Ioſeph</hi> hear;</l>
               <l>No anſwer made, unto a higher ſtrain</l>
               <l>He tunes his voice aloud to rouze the Swain,</l>
               <l>None but an <hi>echo</hi> anſwers, with his fiſt</l>
               <l>Then thumps his Breaſt, leſt death and ſleep had kiſt,</l>
               <l>Then carefull fear makes nearer ſcrutiny,</l>
               <l>Believing not his ear, he truſts his ey,</l>
               <l>And finding <hi>him</hi> not there ſadly returns</l>
               <l>Unto his Brethren, rents his cloaths, and mourns.</l>
               <l>The child is not, then I, I will not home,</l>
               <l>But like ſavage Satvr hence will come,</l>
               <l>Like a wood-Cit'zen, on the ſame accounts</l>
               <l>With Bears and Wolves I'd dine and ſup by ounce.</l>
               <l>You never ſuckt the Breaſts of Wolves or Bears,</l>
               <l>That you ſhould be obdurate to his tears;</l>
               <l>Since he is ſlain, where have you him inhears'd?</l>
               <l>Which of you hath his guiltleſſe boſome piec'd?</l>
               <l>Fear you not <hi>Rachel</hi> will appear anon.</l>
               <l>And to our Father mone her murtherd ſon,</l>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:57741:8"/>
               <l>And with ſtrong dreams at night intrance his ſpirit?</l>
               <l>You for a bleſſing may a curſe inherit.</l>
               <l>Had rage no other countermine in ſtore</l>
               <l>Againſt contempt but death? what could it more?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At this they all ſtood mute, none was ſo bold</l>
               <l>For to reply that <hi>Joſoph's</hi> bought and ſold,</l>
               <l>Untill that one more boldly for the reſt</l>
               <l>To mourning <hi>Reuben</hi> all the truth confeſt.</l>
               <l>That done, the coat which they from <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſtript</l>
               <l>I'th' blood of a young tender Goat they dipt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Chriſts</hi> cloaths were parted, <hi>Joſephs</hi> dipt in blood,</l>
               <l>May ne'r by them our Church be underſtood,</l>
               <l>May ne'r our Church lie tinctur'd in her gore,</l>
               <l>Not rent by Shiſmaticks, I heav'n implore,</l>
               <l>Nor hereſies, may not that lovely Spouſe</l>
               <l>Be forc'd, nor Goats upon that Vineyard brouze;</l>
               <l>May ne'r the Boars on it commit their rapes,</l>
               <l>Nor in their mud lie drunken with her grapes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>Dan</hi>'s inſtructed with a feigned prize</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Joſephs</hi> coat to pierce his Fathers eyes.</l>
               <l>Quoth he, Sir walking partly for to muſe,</l>
               <l>Partly to gather hurdles for our Ewes,</l>
               <l>I ſaw my Curr ſtrangely to breath the wind,</l>
               <l>Anon this bloody garment for to find,</l>
               <l>I doubt 'tis <hi>Joſephs,</hi> and I could not reſt</l>
               <l>Till you reſolv'd what yet my fears ſuggeſt;</l>
               <l>Then <hi>Jacob</hi> rent his cloathes, puts ſackcloth on,</l>
               <l>Doubtleſſe, quoth he, ſome beaſt hath torn my ſon,</l>
               <l>Come grief unſluce the floodgates of my brain,</l>
               <l>Break ope the ſprings, let forth the ſilver rain:</l>
               <l>Hath age or paſſion drain'd my humours drie?</l>
               <l>What means within my brain this <hi>ſtrangury?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>My brain's a barren cloud, though it have felt</l>
               <l>The heat of grief 'twill not diſſolve nor melt;</l>
               <l>Me thinks now ſhould my dropſi'd skin deplore</l>
               <l>My <hi>Ioſephs</hi> death with tears through ev'ry pore,</l>
               <l>I've heard great ſorrow's dumb and wanteth words,</l>
               <l>But now griefs barren, and no tears affords;</l>
               <l>My brain and fancy both alike are drie,</l>
               <l>I can nor weep, nor ſpeak my miſerie;</l>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:57741:9"/>
               <l>Would from the <hi>North</hi> I ſtormy ſighs could borrow,</l>
               <l>Tears from the fleeting <hi>South</hi> to weep my ſorrow,</l>
               <l>My heavy heart as moated round with led,</l>
               <l>Doth lie within my boſome buried?</l>
               <l>I've heard ſome have been nouriſhed by Beaſts,</l>
               <l>Some children have been foſtred at their Breaſts,</l>
               <l>Then, then, could not my <hi>Joſeph's</hi> inn'cent ey</l>
               <l>E'n charm all Beaſts from their <hi>Antipathy?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Dans</hi> words did grate the griſles of my ears,</l>
               <l>Crackt not my eye-ſtrings when I ſaw through tears</l>
               <l>The Coat? O would it had been a diſguiſe,</l>
               <l>But tears were not falſe glaſſes to mine eyes;</l>
               <l>I'd weep the dreggs of tears, theſe ſeem the froth</l>
               <l>Of triviall grief, ſince tears cauſe childrens growth.</l>
               <l>Come <hi>Benjamin,</hi> Now thou mayſt juſtly borrow</l>
               <l>Thy Mothers name <hi>Benoni,</hi> ſon of ſorrow;</l>
               <l>Th'art not ſo young in years, but canſt conceive</l>
               <l>Of this our loſſe, how canſt thou chooſe but grieve?</l>
               <l>Father, quoth he (then were his eyes afloat</l>
               <l>When as as he viewd the parti-coloured coat)</l>
               <l>Do not all ſorrow to your ſelf ingroſſe,</l>
               <l>You weep a Sons, and I, as Brothers loſs;</l>
               <l>O would my tears were of that pretious rate</l>
               <l>That they ſlain <hi>Joſeph</hi> could redeem from fate;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph's</hi> not loſt, I've heard you oft rehearſe</l>
               <l>That <hi>Enoch</hi> had with God ſo neer commerce</l>
               <l>That God did take him, might not providence</l>
               <l>Have like reſpect to <hi>Joſeph's</hi> innocence?</l>
               <l>If ſo, I've likewiſe often heard you name</l>
               <l>How that my faithfull Grandſire <hi>Abraham</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Would in obedience unto Gods command</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His only Son,</hi> with an impartiall hand,</l>
               <l>Offer to God, you've many, he no more,</l>
               <l>Grudge not to ſpare God one of all your ſtore.</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Jacob,</hi> Oh theſe hopes are counterfeit,</l>
               <l>I'd gladly cheat my grief with ſuch deceit,</l>
               <l>My fear's too reall, then his tears he ſhowr'd,</l>
               <l>Doubtleſs, quoth he, ſome beaſt hath him devour'd.</l>
               <l>Come, come, my children, weep with me awhile,</l>
               <l>While that I lie like to a floating Ile</l>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:57741:9"/>
               <l>Soaking in tears, come, and in Sympathie</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Joſephs</hi> fortunes lend a bleeding eie.</l>
               <l>Talk not of cloaths, this is griefs ornament,</l>
               <l>Sorrow my food, and <hi>Machpalah</hi> my tent.</l>
               <l>Would I had never ſeen theſe diſmall years,</l>
               <l>Then ne'r had I thus dy'd imbalm'd in tears.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grief be my <hi>Sexton,</hi> Sorrow toll my Bell.</l>
               <l>Death my <hi>Veſpillo</hi> bee, Fates ring my knell,</l>
               <l>My Nun-like ſoul is weary of her cloyſter,</l>
               <l>So ſorrow ſucks my marrow, dries my moyſture.</l>
               <l>In pitty of his tears, what tyrant keeps</l>
               <l>His eyes from raining when an old man weeps?</l>
               <l>With the <hi>Venetian</hi> ſorrow hath a Sea</l>
               <l>Eſpouſed to my brain, <hi>tears are griefs plea,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Whoſe headſtrong torrent who can but affront?</l>
               <l>What <hi>Xerxes</hi> can but guive my <hi>Holieſpont?</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>The <hi>Midianties</hi> as doubting a reprieve</l>
               <l>Of their lov'd purchaſe ſtrait to <hi>Memphis</hi> drive,</l>
               <l>Whoſe burniſh'd turrets as they did approach,</l>
               <l>Shewd like ſome Saphyrs dropt from <hi>Phoebus</hi> Coach;</l>
               <l>Whoſe lofty Pinacles tranſparent light</l>
               <l>Did ſeem to mock the twinckling ſtarrs by night:</l>
               <l>The Merchants willing to obtain regard</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Putiphar</hi> Captain of <hi>Pharoahs</hi> guard,</l>
               <l>And good opinion of their trading truth,</l>
               <l>With humble Court'ſie thus preſent our youth.</l>
               <l>Great Sir, quoth they, as we paſto'r the plains,</l>
               <l>It was our chance to meet with <hi>Hebrew</hi> ſwains;</l>
               <l>At whoſe much importunity we bought</l>
               <l>This youth, whom we have to your Lordſhip brought;</l>
               <l>Aſſuring thus our ſelves, that if the grace</l>
               <l>Of mind be anſwerable to his face,</l>
               <l>So ſweet a face, ſo bleſt a <hi>Genius,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Is fitter for your Lordſhip, than for us.</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Putiphar</hi> it argues not your thrift,</l>
               <l>To tender gratis ſuch a worthy gift,</l>
               <l>Let not your courteſie thus ſeem ſo nice,</l>
               <l>Nor circumſtantiall, but tell the price.</l>
               <l>Quoth one, the <hi>Hebrews</hi> askt Spice Balm, or gum,</l>
               <l>But twenty ſilver pieces was the ſum;</l>
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:57741:10"/>
               <l>At this the Captain ſtarteth How ſo cheap?</l>
               <l>So rare a purchaſe for ſo ſmall a heap?</l>
               <l>Were I a King, and ſuch a ſon had loſt,</l>
               <l>I would redeem him at my kingdom's coſt,</l>
               <l>Nay though twice <hi>Egypt,</hi> and though <hi>Nile</hi> did ſtream</l>
               <l>In golden Cataracts, ſurpaſt a dream,</l>
               <l>Though each ſand were a Saphyr on his banks;</l>
               <l>Take gold for ſilver, for your love take thanks;</l>
               <l>Theſe homely weeds do not beſeem my lad,</l>
               <l>Thou ſhalt in ſcarlet, and in ſilks be clad,</l>
               <l>Nor by extorting trialls will I prove,</l>
               <l>How thou hereafter wilt deſerve my love,</l>
               <l>Though I am not like thoſe that doe rejoyce</l>
               <l>When that they buy, in nature, more than choice;</l>
               <l>This ſaid, the multitude about him crowds,</l>
               <l>Hee like a ſtar bemantled round with cloudes,</l>
               <l>Or like a Diamond if richly ſet</l>
               <l>In the circumference of a ring of jet.</l>
               <l>You in his face might read whom he ador'd,</l>
               <l>And in their viſage, whom they oft implor'd.</l>
               <l>Now to his home the Captain brought his page,</l>
               <l>Dreſt with the reſt in ſcarlet equipage,</l>
               <l>Whoſe bluſhing cheeks natures freſh livery,</l>
               <l>Did ſhame the ſcarlet with a nobler die;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> ne'r was ſerv'd by ſuch a <hi>Ganymede,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>No falſe <hi>Ixion</hi> to his maſters bed;</l>
               <l>What e'r he did ſome <hi>Angel</hi> did attend,</l>
               <l>And brought his actions to a proſperous end,</l>
               <l>And for his ſake, his Maſters care and pain</l>
               <l>Was ever recompence'd with double gain.</l>
               <l>This ſeen, there's granted to his providence</l>
               <l>The office of a ſteward to diſpenſe:</l>
               <l>Where God's the ſuperviſor who will fear?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>T'a faithfull ſteward God's a treaſurer;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Succeſſe the midwife was, and gain the heir</l>
               <l>And happy iſſue ſtill of each affair.</l>
               <l>Envy at this repines, and madly ſhakes</l>
               <l>About her horrid head her ratling ſnakes;</l>
               <l>Her looks more meager grew, her limbs more thin,</l>
               <l>And with her ruſty teeth begins to grin</l>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:57741:10"/>
               <l>At <hi>Joſephs</hi> Fortunes, <hi>he</hi> muſt drink a ſup</l>
               <l>Of hers, as well as Fortunes pleaſant cup;</l>
               <l>Among the reſt that homage did of duty,</l>
               <l>And vow'd adorates were to <hi>Joſephs</hi> beauty,</l>
               <l>His miſtris (fair <hi>Iempſar</hi>) tore the veil</l>
               <l>Of modeſty, no counſell could be bail</l>
               <l>For captive reaſon <hi>J ſeph</hi> gave the wound,</l>
               <l>And who to cure't but <hi>Joſeph</hi> may be found?</l>
               <l>Firſt reaſon to her fancy read this lecture,</l>
               <l>Should this be known what would the Court conjecture?</l>
               <l>Reaſon exiled judgment thus deprav'd,</l>
               <l>Thou to thy ſervile vaſſall thus inſlav'd.</l>
               <l>I grant ſweet <hi>Joſeph</hi> hath a peerleſs beauty,</l>
               <l>But can his loyally diſpenſe with duty,</l>
               <l>He owes his maſter <hi>Potiphar</hi> her Lord?</l>
               <l>And fear'ſt thou not his luſt-revenging ſword?</l>
               <l>But what quoth ſhe? let fore-ſight wait one age,</l>
               <l>Youth ne'r to counſell ſues for Patronage;</l>
               <l>Let fab'lous fears preſent their bug bear faces,</l>
               <l>And marſhall all their horrours yet the baſis</l>
               <l>On which my reſolution grounds my love</l>
               <l>What terrour can but ſhake what fear remove?</l>
               <l>Now this reſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>lv'd upon what flight evaſion</l>
               <l>Hath critick reaſon, and what vain perſwaſion?</l>
               <l>Wer't not for gifts this face perſwades alone</l>
               <l>Since he hath eyes and ears, he may be won.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Pregnant with hopes impariently ſhe tends</l>
               <l>Till time might provent Pander for her ends,</l>
               <l>And long had ſweating loſt conſpir'd with fraud,</l>
               <l>Untill fa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Opportunity the <hi>Baud</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch deſigns, appointed time and place,</l>
               <l>When ſhe uninterrupted pleads her caſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dear <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſeph,</hi> long with hopes my breſt hath teem'd,</l>
               <l>Time long unfleg'd and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>llow wing'd hath ſeem'd,</l>
               <l>Til they deliver'd by the Midwifry</l>
               <l>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of this happy Opportunity,</l>
               <l>Which ſince it ſmiles on us, I hope my love</l>
               <l>Shall not by coy neglect abortive prove.</l>
               <l>Why ſtarts thou at love nam'd? why doſt thou ſcorn?</l>
               <l>'Tis to and for love that we all were born.</l>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:57741:11"/>
               <l>Frown not but ſpeak yet ſpeak not while you frown,</l>
               <l>I will not hear, nay pray, you ſhall not down.</l>
               <l>What is it that thou feareſt? no ſpie waits</l>
               <l>To fright our dalliance to diſtracted ſtraits.</l>
               <l>Pray leave theſe niceties, and give a kiſſe</l>
               <l>As happy <hi>Prologue</hi> to enſuing bliſs.</l>
               <l>Come youth, I'll ſet thee in a ſhowr of gold.</l>
               <l>And rain down Pearls upon thee; nay be bold:</l>
               <l>Pray ſmooth this brow, theſe clowdy looks inform</l>
               <l>That ſome diſlike is raiſing of a ſtorm.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Madam, quoth he, excuſe if I explode</l>
               <l>This your requeſt, 'tis ſin againſt my God.</l>
               <l>How can I then do this? this maſſie roof</l>
               <l>That thus contains us is not thunder proof:</l>
               <l>How can my loyalty break down the verge</l>
               <l>Of reaſon, love, and duty? ſince the charge</l>
               <l>Of all to me is granted, you except</l>
               <l>What hath my Lord from me detain'd or kept?</l>
               <l>Which would much aggravate this groſs abuſe,</l>
               <l>So farre beyond remiſſion, as excuſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now here was beauty, if he had been fond</l>
               <l>Beauty with beauty here might correſpond.</l>
               <l>Here were large promiſes, that might inchant</l>
               <l>A ſtern refuſall to a ſilent grant.</l>
               <l>Since heaven was his love, it is no wonder</l>
               <l>If leſs he fear'd her frown than heavens thunder.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Not willing to deſiſt at this repulſe,</l>
               <l>Our Amoriſt with ſecond thoughts conſults;</l>
               <l>Firſt fearing leſt her faces nice peruſall</l>
               <l>Might in the lad occaſion this refuſall,</l>
               <l>Her glaſſe ſhe curſes, grief her heart doth gnaw;</l>
               <l>I thought quoth ſhe, theſe beaming eyes could thaw</l>
               <l>E'n froſt-congealed veins, and might ſuffice</l>
               <l>To melt a heart though moated round with yee;</l>
               <l>But I'm deceiv'd, by <hi>Chemoſh</hi> and you light</l>
               <l>My nayles could damn you to eternall night,</l>
               <l>And on this face could act a Martyrdome,</l>
               <l>Bite off this fruitleſs tongue, and hence live dumb.</l>
               <l>Alas poor ornaments, deſpiſed treſſes,</l>
               <l>Contemned promiſes, deceiving dreſſes,</l>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:57741:11"/>
               <l>Love took me pris'ner, yet I could take arms,</l>
               <l>And now what wit, what counſell-countercharms</l>
               <l>Can exerciſe my love? love's ſpirit lies</l>
               <l>Beyond the reach of all our ſorceries.</l>
               <l>What patience can conceal't, What reaſon ſmother?</l>
               <l>Falſe expectation is a curſt Stepmother.</l>
               <l>With what an Uſury doth ſhe extort</l>
               <l>An ages longing for a minutes ſport?</l>
               <l>But joy with grief, Fate on one Bottome ſpins,</l>
               <l>And pain and pleaſure often-times are twins.</l>
               <l>Though Pain's the elder, yet to the forlorn</l>
               <l>Anon Joy th'younger Siſter will be born;</l>
               <l>On this our Lover Deifies Perſwaſion,</l>
               <l>And with a Godhead ſhe inveſts Occaſion;</l>
               <l>Shee'll try once more, though ſhame do countermand,</l>
               <l>Though life with death in equall ballance ſtand.</l>
               <l>Deſpair and Hope long in her Breſt conteſted,</l>
               <l>Untill her mem'ry time and place ſuggeſted;</l>
               <l>And now how ſlowly <hi>Phoebus</hi> ſnailes his courſe,</l>
               <l>And draws his fiery Coach with founderd horſe;</l>
               <l>The wings of flagging Time are clipt, he feels</l>
               <l>The keyes of ſleep and death weigh'd at his heels.</l>
               <l>Occaſion ſerving her you may conceive</l>
               <l>Our wanton Amoriſt thus playes the <hi>Eve.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dear <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Fate and Fortune have conſpir'd</l>
               <l>For to mature the ſute I late deſir'd,</l>
               <l>Then let's no longer this our bliſs prorogue,</l>
               <l>But now cloſe up our loving Epilogue;</l>
               <l>Why looks diſdain aſquint? this forehead furld</l>
               <l>In angry folds? Survey this little world,</l>
               <l>What beautie's in the world (my type) ſurmiz'd</l>
               <l>That's not in me more gloriouſly compriz'd?</l>
               <l>My Eyes dim <hi>Phoebus</hi> light, my Cheeks the ſphears,</l>
               <l>And what deformed clouds on them appears?</l>
               <l>Each beauty here's a ſtar, only from hence</l>
               <l>My <hi>J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>eph</hi> doth diſdain their influence;</l>
               <l>The Sun's all eye, the walls can do no wrong,</l>
               <l>By palate, throat, two lips, four teeth and tongue.</l>
               <l>Then fear no ſpies, theſe frowns ſhall never daunt,</l>
               <l>They'r but an <hi>Introduction</hi> to a grant.</l>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:57741:12"/>
               <l>What, fear'ſt the light? the windows ſhall be ſeeld;</l>
               <l>Since love is blind, Come do not frown, but yeeld.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quoth hee, What means this chat, this bootleſs flattr'y?</l>
               <l>Remove your Siege, my Fort diſdains the Batt'ry;</l>
               <l>O let your face and deeds be Relatiſts,</l>
               <l>Where heaven, grace, and beauty in one twiſts,</l>
               <l>'Tis a rare mixture, elſe for what's this face?</l>
               <l>Your world doth want his Sun if void of Grace.</l>
               <l>Is luſtfull <hi>Sodoms</hi> fiery doom forgot?</l>
               <l>Or was't not heard? me thinks the room's too hot.</l>
               <l>This Curtain's woven in too thin a loom</l>
               <l>To bear out forked lightning and this room</l>
               <l>Not built of ſuch unmalleable ſtuff,</l>
               <l>But the ſame God can thunderbolt it through.</l>
               <l>What Mimick figures doth this Face aſſume</l>
               <l>To ſet forth Paſſion? uſe this fruitleſs rheum</l>
               <l>Diſtilling from your Eyes to purge your guilt,</l>
               <l>For to this purpoſe all in vain are ſpilt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>On this <hi>Iemſar</hi> madly ruminates,</l>
               <l>Fortune's a Strumpet, who, but Bawds the Fates?</l>
               <l>Occaſion is a Traitreſs, 'tis no ſlander</l>
               <l>If <hi>Venus</hi> be call'd Where, <hi>Cupid</hi> a Pander.</l>
               <l>Anon ſhe frets and fumes, vext with the pride</l>
               <l>That ſhe ſhould be neglected, and deni'd.</l>
               <l>Then rails on Nature 'cauſe her beauties vigour</l>
               <l>Could not prevail, then threats her with this rigour.</l>
               <l>Poor face, quoth ſhe, my nails could quote in ſcarrs,</l>
               <l>And trace thy ſhame in bloudy characters.</l>
               <l>Theſe Eyes, theſe Eyes, are Baſilisks, elſe ſure</l>
               <l>Where they are thus avoided, might allure;</l>
               <l>Then ſince that nought avails this idle breath,</l>
               <l>I'll to my glaſs, and look my ſelf to death.</l>
               <l>Weak Hair! How often have I thought in vain</l>
               <l>That you in amorous guives could <hi>Hero's</hi> chain?</l>
               <l>Are you thus ſlighted? can a ſervile groom</l>
               <l>Break through your treſſes like a Spiders loom?</l>
               <l>I'd gladly Reaſon re-admit my tutor,</l>
               <l>And friendly counſell, as her Coadjutor;</l>
               <l>But where ſome beauties cloy the appetite,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>His</hi> ſets a ſharper edge upon delight.</l>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:57741:12"/>
               <l>Let reaſon chat, ſo with attentive griſle</l>
               <l>Rough <hi>Boreas</hi> hearkens to the Sea-mens whiſtle;</l>
               <l>For what! who but a leaden-ſpirited clown</l>
               <l>Will fearfully ſtand bent at ev'ry frown?</l>
               <l>True Reſolution hath my temper ſteel'd,</l>
               <l>Which back will ſpring, till broke will never yeeld.</l>
               <l>Long Summers crown the long expected primes,</l>
               <l>And who will gain his ends muſt wait on times,</l>
               <l>Where pleaſure's principall, pain paies the uſe.</l>
               <l>Of Fate and Fortune now ſhe begs excuſe;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Love</hi> with whom ſhe madly late conteſted</l>
               <l>Is in his Deity now re-inveſted;</l>
               <l>Who'll not endure Love's pecking Doves ſhall ſmart</l>
               <l>For his impatience with his angry dart;</l>
               <l>To thoſe that yeeld Love is a gracious Queen,</l>
               <l>A tyrant to a refractory ſpleen;</l>
               <l>Somtimes ſhe fears ſuſpition might diſcover</l>
               <l>To <hi>Putiphar,</hi> ſhe was her Vaſſals lover,</l>
               <l>And then what ſlight, or what inſinuation</l>
               <l>Can free her from his juſt repudiation?</l>
               <l>But Fear's a <hi>Pigmie</hi> dreſt in <hi>Gorgons</hi> cloaths;</l>
               <l>To gain her ends ſhee'll break all nuptiall oaths:</l>
               <l>On Lovers perjuries they ſay <hi>Joves</hi> ſmiles,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Love</hi> is ſtill auſpicious to ſuch Wiles.</l>
               <l>As did <hi>Semiramis</hi> once woo her <hi>Nine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So likewiſe our <hi>Egyptian Meſſaline.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Occaſion ſerving her, you may ſurmize,</l>
               <l>Thus makes her third aſſault upon her prize.</l>
               <l>Look dear, how Time hath granted what I claim'd,</l>
               <l>And Chance preſents the ſcope to which I aim'd,</l>
               <l>Let's not delay, of my requeſt accept,</l>
               <l>And in my graunt let Nature have her debt;</l>
               <l>Thou to a Father wert a Child, I gather</l>
               <l>That to a Child thou mightſt become a Father;</l>
               <l>Pray do not thus diſcourteouſly impeach</l>
               <l>Me as before, hear, till I end my Speech;</l>
               <l>Yet in my ſuing looks if I were mute,</l>
               <l>Thou mightſt moſt plainly read my loving ſute;</l>
               <l>Regard theſe Tears, Pearls of ſo rare eſteem</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Pharoh,</hi> if a Captive, might redeem.</l>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:57741:13"/>
               <l>What's here, ſhouldſt thou of envie take advice?</l>
               <l>What's here deformed that thou ſhouldſt be nice?</l>
               <l>Here's ſymmetry no ill-proportion'd frame,</l>
               <l>Nature and Art herein deſerve no blame;</l>
               <l>My ſinewes active are my ſpirits quick</l>
               <l>Are as thine own, they'r neither gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſs nor thick;</l>
               <l>Which granted, ſpeak, who (but a ſenſleſs ſtone)</l>
               <l>To ſuch requeſts as theſe would not be prone?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Madam, quoth he my reſolution's fixt,</l>
               <l>Nor with ambiguous doubts at all is mixt;</l>
               <l>Were you an Angell come from heav'n, and mov'd</l>
               <l>Me to this ſute, I never would have lov'd;</l>
               <l>Which yer I grant, conceive that Heav'n and Hell,</l>
               <l>Things inconſiſtent, incompatible</l>
               <l>Shall in harmonious unity combine,</l>
               <l>Yer I one thought to your requeſt incline;</l>
               <l>Though nature you with choyſeſt parts endows,</l>
               <l>My ey ſhall never countermand my vows.</l>
               <l>I hate not love, but that intemp'rate flame</l>
               <l>Of burning luſt that thus uſurps his name;</l>
               <l>Love at a heav'nly beam doth light his torch,</l>
               <l>While helliſh flames the luſt-allured ſcorch.</l>
               <l>Much more than <hi>this,</hi> for ſacred love I'd ſpeak;</l>
               <l>The text is old, the oratory weak.</l>
               <l>Pray ſpeak no more, my ears do burn for ſhame</l>
               <l>To hear your talk, my cheeks are all aflame.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thus daily did our pathick Amoriſt,</l>
               <l>The fair <hi>Iempſar,</hi> in her ſute perſiſt;</l>
               <l>And <hi>Joſeph's</hi> truth, as bold was as her luſt</l>
               <l>Denies to violate his faith and truſt.</l>
               <l>Oft did his ears pump her invention dry,</l>
               <l>And then her ſighes her meaning would ſupply;</l>
               <l>And as ſome doe obſerve, the viſage keeps</l>
               <l>The ſelf-ſame figures when it laughs and weeps,</l>
               <l>So various were her paſſions, none could read</l>
               <l>In <hi>hers</hi> where that ſhe ſmil'd, or wept indeed.</l>
               <l>Had but the <hi>Syrens</hi> to <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> ſung</l>
               <l>So ſweetly, as here woo'd <hi>Iemſars</hi> tongue,</l>
               <l>'Tis thought <hi>Ulyſſes</hi> had, though ne'r ſo chaſt,</l>
               <l>Broke through the yeelding Cable, burſt the Maſt,</l>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:57741:13"/>
               <l>His mens unſealed ears charm'd by her notes,</l>
               <l>Had left their empty ſhip to <hi>Neptunes</hi> floats.</l>
               <l>Now would ſhe ſtrike her Breſts, then otherwhiles</l>
               <l>Weep tears would cheat even the Crocodiles.</l>
               <l>Ne'r was a <hi>Roe</hi> more weary of her chaſe,</l>
               <l>Ne'r timerous Hare to ſhun the Hunters trace,</l>
               <l>Doubled more folds, or made more neer eſcapes,</l>
               <l>Than to avoid her, he did vary ſhapes;</l>
               <l>And when he ever would himſelf unmew,</l>
               <l>Shee like diſdained <hi>Echo</hi> ſtill would ſue;</l>
               <l>Or like his ſhadow, only had not fled,</l>
               <l>Had he returned to her luſtfull Bed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iempſar</hi> at young <hi>Joſephs</hi> chaſt regrets,</l>
               <l>Is madly malecontent, and thus ſhe frets.</l>
               <l>Shall expectation longer dull my ſenſe?</l>
               <l>Or I turn'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> o'r to racking patience?</l>
               <l>Stoop I ſo low, and in my ſute ſo ſerious?</l>
               <l>And is this Lad ſo ſullen and imperious?</l>
               <l>Shall I, ſhall I, who was ſo nobly born</l>
               <l>Thus prove a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rop<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> to my vaſſals ſcorn?</l>
               <l>Shall I, whoſe words can either ſave or doom,</l>
               <l>Thus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ive, as ſentenc'd by my ſervile groom?</l>
               <l>Shall I, whoſe powrfull face was wont to bow</l>
               <l>The ſtouteſt Monarchs to an amorous vow,</l>
               <l>Be thus deſpis'd contemn'd condemn'd, rejected,</l>
               <l>My promiſe ſlighted and my faith ſuſpected?</l>
               <l>I'll make him know by dear experience,</l>
               <l>What 'tis a womans fury to incenſe.</l>
               <l>Women are <hi>Angels,</hi> grant to what they mov'd,</l>
               <l>Deni'd are <hi>Furies,</hi> hate what e'r they lov'd.</l>
               <l>But yet there are ſome hopes; perhaps this Boy</l>
               <l>Is out of inexperience thus ſo coy:</l>
               <l>A bold aſſault, perchance, may win the crown,</l>
               <l>Then will I thunder if he dare to frown;</l>
               <l>The ſweeteſt Wine hath ſtill the ſharpeſt lees;</l>
               <l>And water heat, once coold will hardeſt freeze:</l>
               <l>Seeing thus my reſolution hath decreed,</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Ven<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> or <hi>Alecto</hi> be my ſpeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ne'r could our haunted youth have the enjoyment</l>
               <l>Of eaſe or quiet, labour or employment,</l>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:57741:14"/>
               <l>But him ſhe haunts, at length he unaware,</l>
               <l>Thus boldly ſhe anticipates his ear.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Look dear, my care thy utmoſt hath outvi'd;</l>
               <l>Why fly'ſt me ſo? ſweet give me leave to chide;</l>
               <l>Was it not grief enough thou ſhould'ſt deny mee?</l>
               <l>But thus likewiſe diſcourteouſly to fly mee?</l>
               <l>Denyalls wound but where love cannot plead</l>
               <l>His ſute through abſence, ſorrow ſtrikes him dead:</l>
               <l>Dear, Why art thou and I grown day and night,</l>
               <l>When I am moſt then thou art leaſt in ſight:</l>
               <l>Look Time o'rſhades us with a proſp'rous wing,</l>
               <l>And but thy love could I wiſh any thing?</l>
               <l>Frown not, ſince Fortune ſmiles, make uſe of ſeaſon,</l>
               <l>Here is no blab to prate, then fear no treaſon.</l>
               <l>Art thou religious? What is zeal but love?</l>
               <l>And ſuch proficients muſt ſuch means improve;</l>
               <l>Leave, leave this coyneſs, let not love be baniſh'd,</l>
               <l>Make uſe of love, before this Youth be vaniſh'd.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, our haſty lover is grown mute,</l>
               <l>As was invention prompting a recruit.</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Madam, leave theſe <hi>Syrens</hi> ſongs,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>This pair of ears can dry a thouſand tongues,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>They ne'r ſhall force a paſſage to my heart;</l>
               <l>My reſolution goes beyond your art.</l>
               <l>Then be reſolv'd, I wiſh you underſtood</l>
               <l>Luſt ſtains the tincture of your noble blood.</l>
               <l>Love is all valour, damned luſt a craven;</l>
               <l>Love's <hi>Embleme</hi> is a <hi>Dove,</hi> but Luſt's a <hi>Raven.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>More I could ſpeak.—and more he would have ſpoke</l>
               <l>Had ſhe not luſtfully caught at his Cloak,</l>
               <l>Who, of his Cloak, not chaſtity, bereft,</l>
               <l>Fled, and his garment with his Miſtris left.</l>
               <l>He gon, her blood through choler grew aduſt</l>
               <l>Within her veins, black, as her burning luſt;</l>
               <l>Where Luſt's the Mother, Hate is ſtill the Child,</l>
               <l>Thus Love and Luſt are never reconcil'd.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iempſar</hi> raves, no other pains ſhe felt</l>
               <l>Than did ſome Witch her waxen ſtatue melt,</l>
               <l>Her heart knockt at her ribs e'n ſuch a pain</l>
               <l>Did <hi>Meleager</hi> (Poets ſay) ſuſtain,</l>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:57741:14"/>
               <l>When that his Mother with her angry hand</l>
               <l>Into the flames had caſt the fatall brand;</l>
               <l>Officious envy ſoon a lie ſuggeſted,</l>
               <l>And ſhe as by ſome horrid gheſt infeſted</l>
               <l>Exclaim'd aloud, her ſervants at the noyſe</l>
               <l>Approach'd, whom ſtrait ſhe greeteth with this voice.</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe, The ſlave on which <hi>He</hi> ſo conſides,</l>
               <l>Forſooth the Steward who our buſineſs guides,</l>
               <l>Would raviſh me; but by my outcrie chac't,</l>
               <l>Fled, and his garment with me left through haſt,</l>
               <l>Glad ſhe had dreſt her lie in ſuch a ſhape,</l>
               <l>That he on her attempted had a rape,</l>
               <l>She knew the Youth ſhould from her Husband win</l>
               <l>No expiation for ſo foul a ſin,</l>
               <l>On which triumphing our incenſed Dame</l>
               <l>Layes up the Garment till her Husband came.</l>
               <l>He come, her mind our Lady thus diſcuſt,</l>
               <l>As <hi>Phaedra</hi> once accus'd her ſon of luſt.</l>
               <l>With mournfull looks, moyſt eies, and hands expans'd,</l>
               <l>Quoth ſhe, The Youth whom you have ſo advanc'd,</l>
               <l>Had raviſh'd me, had not my ſhreeking tongue</l>
               <l>More powerfull been, than my defence was ſtrong.</l>
               <l>And as a witneſs of what he deſign'd</l>
               <l>For haſt he left with me his Cloak behind.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, the blood boyld in the Captains veins,</l>
               <l>Rough Jealouſie ſtrait gave his rage the reins;</l>
               <l>Quoth He to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> is this lovely look</l>
               <l>So fair an Index to ſo falſe a Book?</l>
               <l>Nay ſure old Nature doted, when ſhe ſhrind</l>
               <l>Within ſo fair a Caſe ſo foul a Mind.</l>
               <l>Hence, I'll ne'r truſt to beauty, ſince I know</l>
               <l>Worſt thoughts lurk mask'd under the faireſt ſhow.</l>
               <l>How I'm deceived who would ever fear</l>
               <l>A Devill mov'd within this ſplendid ſphear?</l>
               <l>I know the reaſon now, and will aſſent</l>
               <l>Why faireſt flowers have ſtill the fouleſt ſent.</l>
               <l>Is thy Religion but a feign'd diſguiſe?</l>
               <l>Is luſt the zeal that thus thy temper fries?</l>
               <l>Wert thou for this prefer'd, ſo highly fed,</l>
               <l>That thou ſhouldſt thus attempt to ſtain my Bed?</l>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:57741:15"/>
               <l>Could none, could none, ambitious luſt, ſuffice</l>
               <l>But ſuch a purchaſe of ſo rare a prize?</l>
               <l>Hardſhip ſhall check this temper day and night,</l>
               <l>Hunger ſhall quell this luſtfull Appetite;</l>
               <l>Yet though thou herein wer't ſo malapert,</l>
               <l>And this offence might cancell all deſert,</l>
               <l>My rage ſhall not glut on thy fleſh for food,</l>
               <l>Nor ſhall my furyes revell on thy blood;</l>
               <l>Yet leave theſe robes that I may be reveng'd,</l>
               <l>Theſe golden Chains for Guives muſt be exchang'd,</l>
               <l>Theſe Rings for Manacles, for Tapeſtry</l>
               <l>Darkneſs ſhall ſerve thee for a Canopy;</l>
               <l>To priſon hence, whence hope for no reprivall:</l>
               <l>Think'ſt thou my thoughts can brook my ſlave, my rivall?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Oft <hi>Joſeph</hi> thus began, yet when he ſpoke</l>
               <l>The Captain on the Jaylour would invoke.</l>
               <l>My grief the rigour of your doom exceeds,</l>
               <l>That Fate hath interwoven ſo my deeds</l>
               <l>With ſecrecy that what my Miſtris ſaith</l>
               <l>Beyond my truth, of all ſhould purchaſe faith:</l>
               <l>Yet innocence is bold and I avouch</l>
               <l>If e'r I ſo attempted her to touch,</l>
               <l>May heav'n and earth againſt me both conſpire,</l>
               <l>And may I ſtand the object of their ire,</l>
               <l>If I were falſe, then as my juſt deſert,</l>
               <l>May this right hand prove traytour to my heart.</l>
               <l>To God who is as innocent, ſo juſt</l>
               <l>I do appeal, I never ment this luſt;</l>
               <l>To him, that will both quit me for this blame,</l>
               <l>And in the end make envy bluſh for ſhame.</l>
               <l>Theſe notwithſtanding <hi>Joſephs</hi> vows and tears,</l>
               <l>So Jealouſie ſtood in the Captains ears</l>
               <l>As Centinell, that no complaint or mone</l>
               <l>Could force a paſſage unto reaſons throne;</l>
               <l>And thus no further brought unto the teſt</l>
               <l>The Jaylour entertains his wofull gueſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Although a Pearl through glaſs more dully ſhines,</l>
               <l>'Tis not the priſon Wall but guilt confines;</l>
               <l>Where conſcience in the boſome runs atilt</l>
               <l>Againſt the heart, the Jaylour <hi>there</hi> is guilt.</l>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:57741:15"/>
               <l>And if the body, not the mind be free,</l>
               <l>What is that but a captiv'd liberty?</l>
               <l>The greater world to ſuch, no leſs doth ſeem,</l>
               <l>Than is the leſſer in the ſouls eſteem.</l>
               <l>But innocence though in a narrow gyre</l>
               <l>Is free as ever fancy can deſire;</l>
               <l>Angels ſpread not more free their aery wings;</l>
               <l>The charter'd Libertine of the Woods, not ſings</l>
               <l>More free; the ſhip cuts not the ſilver fome,</l>
               <l>Nor Fiſh more freely in the Ocean come;</l>
               <l>Nay Winds are limited, and Sea's reſtrain'd,</l>
               <l>But Innocence is free, though bound and chain'd.</l>
               <l>Oft our impris'ned Youth his God implor'd,</l>
               <l>And with theſe mournfull ſighes the heavens board,</l>
               <l>Thou that art cloath'd with light; as with a cloak,</l>
               <l>Before whom heaven vaniſheth like ſmoak,</l>
               <l>Diſpell, O Lord, that wilfull ignorance</l>
               <l>That would miſcall this Providence, a Chance;</l>
               <l>Lord, I have ſinned, and this heavy ſcourge</l>
               <l>Thou plagu'ſt me with, was formed in my forge;</l>
               <l>'Tis ſin, my conſcience, Lord, doth ſo atteſt,</l>
               <l>Betraies my freedome unto this arreſt;</l>
               <l>So that I cannot ſatisfie my mind</l>
               <l>Which of the <hi>two</hi> more ſtraightly is confin'd,</l>
               <l>Either my <hi>Soul</hi> within this fleſh immur'd,</l>
               <l>Or elſe my <hi>Body</hi> that is thus ſecur'd;</l>
               <l>Thou, that for former ſins doſt <hi>thine</hi> correct</l>
               <l>(Although <hi>then</hi> innocent) with falſe ſuſpect;</l>
               <l>Thou who mak'ſt greateſt men, like ſtouteſt trees</l>
               <l>At thy rebuke to bow their knotty knees;</l>
               <l>Since ſin upon my Soul writes not this guilt;</l>
               <l>Let mercy bayl, let not my life be ſpilt:</l>
               <l>This of thee, Lord, I humbly do importune,</l>
               <l>Who art far much above Men, Fate, or Fortune.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our Youth in Priſon had not long been kept,</l>
               <l>But that his winning manners ſoftly crept</l>
               <l>Into the Jaylours breſt, and won ſuch grace,</l>
               <l>The Jaylour captive to his Pris'ner was;</l>
               <l>So ever did this holy Witch inchaunt him,</l>
               <l>So ever <hi>Joſeph's</hi> good conceit did haunt him;</l>
               <pb n="26" facs="tcp:57741:16"/>
               <l>That he anon commiſerates the youth,</l>
               <l>And makes ſtrange deſcants on <hi>Iemſars</hi> truth;</l>
               <l>Anon his care by conſtancy matur'd,</l>
               <l>Had ſo the Jaylour of the truth aſſur'd,</l>
               <l>That to his providence, he grants at large</l>
               <l>His keyes, his care, his cuſtody and charge;</l>
               <l>Anon great <hi>Pharaoh</hi> highly was incens'd,</l>
               <l>For thus ſuſpition had her plaint commenc'd</l>
               <l>His Butler and his Baker had compli'd</l>
               <l>On him to act a poys'nous <hi>Regicide;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The King defer'd not, but on his attaint</l>
               <l>Both were confined to a cloſe reſtraint;</l>
               <l>Both to the ſelf-ſame priſon were conveigh'd</l>
               <l>To which ſweet <hi>Joſeph</hi> lately was betray'd,</l>
               <l>Whom ſo the Captain of the guard inlarg'd</l>
               <l>That with the new-come Pris'ners he was charg'd,</l>
               <l>Who for a time were both in priſon kept,</l>
               <l>Till in a night when ſleep payd Natures debt;</l>
               <l>Their brains had etertained ſuch conceits,</l>
               <l>Whoſe reſolution drove them to ſuch ſtraits;</l>
               <l>What ſhould theſe dreams import, whoſe ridling fancy</l>
               <l>They fear'd ſurpaſt the rack of <hi>Necromancy;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With ſtrange imaginations thus perplext</l>
               <l>They ſate revolving on the fancies text:</l>
               <l>Till <hi>Ioſeph</hi> came, who ſtrait in humble ſort</l>
               <l>Thus asks what theſe demeanours did import,</l>
               <l>Quoth he, what means this eye, late, quick, and full</l>
               <l>So ſuddenly grow hollow, ſunk and dull.</l>
               <l>Theſe fixed looks, what do theſe ſighs imply?</l>
               <l>This viſage dreſt in ſorrows livery?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Grief vented much is eas'd,</hi> then tell the cauſe</l>
               <l>On what you thus demur, and ſadly pauſe;</l>
               <l>This night, quoth they, our troubled <hi>Genii</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Have fixt ſo ſtrangely on our memory</l>
               <l>Strange Dreams, beyond our powers to untwiſt,</l>
               <l>And (worſe) we fear, of Charm or <hi>Chemoſh</hi> Prieſt,</l>
               <l>This ſayd, quoth <hi>Joſeph</hi> heaven oft in Dreams</l>
               <l>Preſents imagination with Theams</l>
               <l>Of high import, inſpired fantaſie</l>
               <l>Oft ſpeaks more true then weak Aſtrology;</l>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:57741:16"/>
               <l>And as 'tis Gods t'inſpire, I dare be bold</l>
               <l>To ſay 'tis likewiſe <hi>his</hi> for to unfold;</l>
               <l>Weak ſorcery may feed you with deluſion,</l>
               <l>Ne'r ſatisfie you with a true concluſion;</l>
               <l>Then here unload your thoughts to me, and I</l>
               <l>I'th'end may prove your faithfull <hi>Mercury.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>At this the Butler ſpeaks then hear, Ipray</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me thought one Vine three branches did diſplay,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which firſt, me thought, did bud, then bloom'd abroad,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then bore ripe cluſters of a pleaſant load;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I having</hi> Pharaohs <hi>Cup, before him ſtood,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And in it to him cruſht their ſparkling blood;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quoth</hi> Joſeph <hi>then, three branches are three days,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which time expired,</hi> Pharaoh <hi>ſhall thee raiſe</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>From up this Dungeon, unto former grace,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſhalt officiate in thy wonted place.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But then, quoth he, as this ſhall thus prove true,</l>
               <l>So to the King for my releaſment ſue,</l>
               <l>That I no longer thus, may ly inplung'd,</l>
               <l>My ſpotleſs name by infamy expung'd;</l>
               <l>For I long ſince was raviſhed by theft,</l>
               <l>Both of my Country, and my friends bereft;</l>
               <l>Then when you are to dignity reſtor'd,</l>
               <l>Pray think on what I humbly here implor'd;</l>
               <l>Remember <hi>Joſeph,</hi> quit me from this blame,</l>
               <l>Leſt I prove, ſhortly, nothing but the name.</l>
               <l>From that ſin of Luſt, heav'n knows I'm cleer,</l>
               <l>As is you light that Chariots in his Sphear.</l>
               <l>The Baker ſeeing the Butlers Dreams import,</l>
               <l>Was of his re-advancement in the Court,</l>
               <l>Quoth he, <hi>I likwiſe ſtrangely dream'd, me thought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As to the Court I three white Baskets brought</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With bak'd-meats, and with other plenty ſtor'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Wherewith I might repleriſh</hi> Pharaohs <hi>board,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Birds allured by the dainties fled,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And pickd them as I bore them on my head.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Quoth</hi> Joſeph <hi>theſe three Baskets do preſage,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>When thrice the Sun hath paſt the azurd ſtage.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The King ſhall from this Priſon thee conveigh,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And hang thee on a tree for Birds a prey;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:57741:17"/>
               <l>The third day <hi>Memphis</hi> with triumphall mirth</l>
               <l>Held in remembrance of their <hi>Pharohs</hi> birth,</l>
               <l>When that the Butlers innocent deſert</l>
               <l>Was re-advanc'd the Baker to the Cart</l>
               <l>From Priſon was conveigh'd, and in this ſeaſon</l>
               <l>Was hang'd in expiation of his treaſon;</l>
               <l>Whoſe trunk allured many an aery gueſt,</l>
               <l>Who ſeem'd in honour of the time to feaſt;</l>
               <l>The Butler notwithſtanding <hi>this,</hi> forgot</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Joſeph</hi> that foretold his future lot,</l>
               <l>As fatteſt fields yeeld weeds of fouleſt ſavours,</l>
               <l>Ingratitude repayes the greateſt favours;</l>
               <l>Since Pride, is Fortunes daughters 'tis leſs ſtrange</l>
               <l>To ſee how ſoon <hi>us</hi> can Preferment change:</l>
               <l>For they whoſe Fortunes flie another ſphear</l>
               <l>Unto their Mates, ſtern Planets oft appear;</l>
               <l>At leaſt deſpiſe them, or their Vows forget;</l>
               <l>So Bells at firſt ſpeak thick, but rais'd are ſet.</l>
               <l>So ſmall Brooks roar, but gaining depth of land,</l>
               <l>Their ſwelling ſtreams are at a ſullen ſtand.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Twice ſwelling <hi>Nile</hi> his barren banks had drown'd,</l>
               <l>And with his fertile ſlime inricht the ground,</l>
               <l>Twice twelve times had the Miſtris of the night,</l>
               <l>Lookt black, through abſence of her lovers ſight,</l>
               <l>When that great <hi>Pharaoh</hi> on his couch lay ſtretcht,</l>
               <l>And leaden <hi>Morpheus</hi> on his ſenſes watcht,</l>
               <l>His roving <hi>Genius</hi> was entertain'd</l>
               <l>By ſuch conceits, which, though his fancy feign'd,</l>
               <l>Yet under them, he fear'd, was coucht a ſenſe</l>
               <l>Of high Import, and mighty Conſequence;</l>
               <l>When, ſtraight, he tryes the Charmers and their Spells,</l>
               <l>Who all implor'd their wonted Oracles;</l>
               <l>One woo'd the Stars, another pli'd the Tomb,</l>
               <l>A third his Spirit charm'd, but all were dumb;</l>
               <l>As when ſome did the <hi>Delphian</hi> Shrine implore,</l>
               <l>When th'Oracle grew dumb, and ſpake no more.</l>
               <l>On which the Butler being ſeen awoke</l>
               <l>By racking memory, thus humbly ſpoke,</l>
               <l>Great Sir, I cannot give my thoughts a truce,</l>
               <l>Till I my ſelf thus to your Grace accuſe,</l>
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:57741:17"/>
               <l>I with the Baker were accus'd long ſince</l>
               <l>To have conſpir'd the death of thee, our Prince,</l>
               <l>On which, as Traitours to the ſolemn Oath</l>
               <l>Of our Aleageance, you confin'd us both;</l>
               <l>When in one night, our fancies had impreſt</l>
               <l>Such Dreams on memory, which to the teſt</l>
               <l>Of Reaſon brought, drove us t'amazed ſtraights</l>
               <l>Who might unfold their intricate conceits;</l>
               <l>When to a fellow-pris'ners much requeſts</l>
               <l>The Captains ſervant, We unlockt our Breaſts,</l>
               <l>Who, the reſults both of my innocence</l>
               <l>Foretold, and of the Bakers juſt events.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharaoh</hi> not asking why he was attach'd,</l>
               <l>A haſty Meſſage to the Guard diſpatch'd</l>
               <l>To ſet their Pris'ner free; who we may gheſſe,</l>
               <l>Was brought to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> in a ſeemly dreſſe;</l>
               <l>Who, now rejecting all the Magick ſect,</l>
               <l>Thus ſpeaks to <hi>Joſeph</hi> with a mild aſpect;</l>
               <l>Strange Dreams, this night, my Spirits have ingroſt,</l>
               <l>Remembrance haunts me like an angry Ghoſt,</l>
               <l>And I have heard thy Spirit is accute,</l>
               <l>And canſt unravell Dreams beyond diſpute;</l>
               <l>Now, couldſt thou lead me through this Maze, and Miſt</l>
               <l>Of doubts, could'ſt thou my ridling Dreams untwiſt?</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Joſeph,</hi> Then let <hi>Pharaoh</hi> hear me ſpeak,</l>
               <l>Yet 'tis not I, but God, for I am weak;</l>
               <l>Let fears all vaniſh, let debarement ceaſe;</l>
               <l>My God ſhall to great <hi>Pharaoh</hi> anſwer peace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> as I ſlept, this was my Dream.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Me thought I ſtood cloſe by a pleaſant ſtream,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I look'd, and from the banks I ſaw there climb'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seven Kine, fat-fleſh'd, and well proportion limb'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which in a Medow neer the River plac'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fed pleaſantly, and made a full repaſt:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Next, from the ſtream aſcending, I obſerv'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seven Kine, ſmall limb'd, ſunk-ey'd, and hunger-ſtarv'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Who ſtraight devour'd the reſt that came before,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet ſtill remain'd ill-favoured, lean, and poor,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Then I awoke, and while I ſadly mus'd,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where this were naturall, or elſe infus'd,</l>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:57741:18"/>
               <l>I know not yet, what vapours did condenſe</l>
               <l>Within my brain, ſleep once more lockt my ſenſe,</l>
               <l>When lo, I dream'd again, <hi>One ſtalk ſustaind</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sev'n eares of Corn, rank, good, and heavy-graind;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Next them, ſev'n eares thin, blaſted, and deflowr'd</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Aroſe, which ſtrait, the former crop devour'd:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>I told the Charmers this yet ne'r could learn</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Of them, what theſe my dreamings did concern.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Sir, quoth <hi>Joſeph</hi> thus, <hi>theſe ſev'n full ears,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>And ſev'n good kine, are ſeven plenteous years,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>In which the earth ſhall in increasfull crops.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rejoyce the Husbandmen beyond their hopes;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The ſev'n thin eares, and ſeven ill-favoured kine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Are ſeven years of Famine, I divine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which ſhall enſue the firſt,</hi> the Springs recruit</l>
               <l>Be void, the Earth fail of her wonted fruit;</l>
               <l>The Vine ſhall not her wonted Vintage bleed,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Nile</hi> in nothing fruitfull but in weed.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Dream was twice preſented, for to ſhew</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That this establiſh'd is, and ſhall enſue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Through Gods decree, now</hi> (by your Graces leave)</l>
               <l>If I might counſell what I fit conceive,</l>
               <l>Though I am ſhallow, and my thoughts I ſtill</l>
               <l>Confeſſe, flag much below your Counſels skill.</l>
               <l>Yet I might ſay, that oft (your Grace doth know)</l>
               <l>To loweſt means we greateſt matters owe.</l>
               <l>And though that no one can anticipate</l>
               <l>The Heavens decree, and croſs the doom of Fate,</l>
               <l>Your Grace may know there's by this warning meant,</l>
               <l>That you this judgement may through care prevent;</l>
               <l>Let <hi>Pharaoh</hi> make one of his wiſeſt Peers</l>
               <l>Chief Maſter of the Corn the plenteous years.</l>
               <l>Who may diſperſe his ſervants through each County.</l>
               <l>To gather up <hi>Ceres</hi> ſuperfluous bounty</l>
               <l>To a fifth part, while plenty ſo ſhall laſt,</l>
               <l>Through riot that there be no ſpoil nor waſt,</l>
               <l>Who where there are no Barns may give a charge;</l>
               <l>To build where they are ſmall for to inlarge;</l>
               <l>For great ſhall be the plenty and extream</l>
               <l>Shall be the famine, as your Grace did Dream;</l>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:57741:18"/>
               <l>So ſhall you wiſely deal, like carefull Ants,</l>
               <l>Whom Natures teacheth to prevent their wants;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Famine's Death's younger Siſter,</hi> 'tis an Elf</l>
               <l>More terrible than War or Death it ſelf.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This liking <hi>Pharaoh</hi> well he anſwers thus;</l>
               <l>Where can we find ſo fit a <hi>Genius?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So dext'rous as thy ſelf ſo full of merit,</l>
               <l>In whom there is inſhrin'd ſo rare a Spirit?</l>
               <l>So worthy of our confidence, ſo prompt?</l>
               <l>Of my affairs here take the full accompt,</l>
               <l>Who dares againſt my choice for to repine?</l>
               <l>Or turn a Rebell to thy Diſcipline?</l>
               <l>My <hi>Genius,</hi> my triple ey I ſwear</l>
               <l>Thou than my other two art far more dear;</l>
               <l>How joy refines my temper! oh 'tis ſtrange,</l>
               <l>They erre that think Complexions cannot change.</l>
               <l>Embraces diſtant are O would that Fate</l>
               <l>Would grant we might more neer incorporate.</l>
               <l>My wit wants words to ſet my Paſſion forth,</l>
               <l>Or <hi>Hieroglyphycks</hi> to deſcribe thy worth;</l>
               <l>Who dares with thee confeſt? there's greater none</l>
               <l>Than thee but I that ſit upon the Throne.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e late under an Imperious guard,</l>
               <l>Was now advanced unto high reward;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſate at the Helm, but <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſteer'd,</l>
               <l>And in the ſecond Chariot was preferr'd</l>
               <l>And ſome, according to the Kings Decree</l>
               <l>Would run before him, crying, <hi>Bow the knee.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So he, who ſeem'd in miſerie forlorn'd</l>
               <l>His neck hath with a golden Chain adorn'd;</l>
               <l>His finger decked with a precious Ring</l>
               <l>Which <hi>Pharaoh</hi> wore as <hi>Embleme</hi> of a King.</l>
               <l>Who in deſpiſed rags did lie of late.</l>
               <l>Now in rich Robes walk'd in Majeſtick ſtate:</l>
               <l>The <hi>Bias</hi> of all <hi>Egypt</hi> he, that drew</l>
               <l>Their Inquiſition t'an admiring view:</l>
               <l>The Court was but the Ring, and he the Gem,</l>
               <l>As to a branch of <hi>Egypts</hi> Royall Stem.</l>
               <l>All did ſubmit themſelves, and to the Court</l>
               <l>As to a late deſcended God reſort.</l>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:57741:19"/>
               <l>Firſt, one would call him Father, and ſalute</l>
               <l>Him with a preſent of his early fruit;</l>
               <l>In things of weight, one by his <hi>Genius</hi> ſwore,</l>
               <l>A third in pain would <hi>Joſephs</hi> God implore,</l>
               <l>The old (late weary of their lives) deſir'd</l>
               <l>To bleſs their Eyes with him yet they expir'd;</l>
               <l>The middle ag'd would bleſs him, and the young</l>
               <l>Unto him iſſue, in a num'rous throng;</l>
               <l>Rich, poor, ſtrong weak, the humble, and the haughty,</l>
               <l>All ran to ſee the Author of their ſafety;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So he,</hi> on whom the heavens ſeem'd to frown,</l>
               <l>Is now advanced unto high renown.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So he,</hi> who late in Priſon did obey,</l>
               <l>Now o'r all <hi>Egypt</hi> bears a mighty ſway;</l>
               <l>Our Saviours trueſt Type; ſo Chriſt aroſe</l>
               <l>To ſave thoſe whom God of his mercy choſe;</l>
               <l>As <hi>Pharaohs</hi> love to <hi>Joſeph</hi> was inclin'd,</l>
               <l>Hath God the Father to his <hi>Son</hi> reſign'd</l>
               <l>All Power, hath <hi>Him</hi> from bonds of fleſh releas'd,</l>
               <l>So is the Father in the Son well pleas'd;</l>
               <l>Hath at his right hand plac'd him, wills that wee</l>
               <l>At <hi>Jeſus</hi> name ſhould bow an humble knee.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Thrice ten times <hi>Joſeph</hi> had ſeen <hi>I aniveer</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With double face to uſher in the year,</l>
               <l>When thus he ſtood before great <hi>Pharaohs</hi> face,</l>
               <l>And gain'd this meaſure of his Princely grace,</l>
               <l>Which age, now for a boſome help matur'd,</l>
               <l>Such was kind <hi>Pharoahs</hi> love, that he procur'd</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Potipherah,</hi> the princely Prieſt of <hi>Un,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>To take his Countries Father for his Son,</l>
               <l>His firſt-born was <hi>Manaſſeth,</hi> for I have</l>
               <l>Quoth he, forgot how I was ſold a ſlave.</l>
               <l>My preſent happineſs where e'r I come,</l>
               <l>Makes me forget my Friends and native home;</l>
               <l>His <hi>ſecond Ephraim,</hi> for I, a ſtranger,</l>
               <l>Quoth he, am fruitfull in a Land of danger;</l>
               <l>About which age our bleſſed Sacrifice</l>
               <l>Having redeem'd us not with common price,</l>
               <l>But with his blood, aſcended hence from <hi>this,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> a far more glorious world of bliſs;</l>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:57741:19"/>
               <l>And for his ſweet belov'd, though he the groom</l>
               <l>Prorogue the Mariage till the day of doom;</l>
               <l>He ne'r is abſent from the Church, his Spouſe,</l>
               <l>Both by the Spirit dart their mutuall vowes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now 'gan the plenteous years, <hi>Nile</hi> at no time</l>
               <l>Did ever leave ſuch fruitfull beds of ſlime;</l>
               <l>The Husbands pain though great, though fat the ſoyl,</l>
               <l>Yet ſtill the fruit ſurpaſt their hopes and toyl;</l>
               <l>As if God through a gracious remorſe</l>
               <l>Of mans great toyl, had here repeal'd that curſe</l>
               <l>Of tedious barrenneſs, for here their ground</l>
               <l>Did like a fertile Paradiſe abound;</l>
               <l>Fields that this Marſhes weep, that Fens did mourn,</l>
               <l>With fruit now laught, and ſung with cheerfull corn;</l>
               <l>The weather ſeaſonable, no fierce rain</l>
               <l>Egg'd on by Tempeſts, waſh'd away their grain;</l>
               <l>The heat was temperate, <hi>Sols</hi> gawdy torch</l>
               <l>Did ſmile to ripen, never kiſs to ſcorch.</l>
               <l>And now did <hi>Joſeph,</hi> like a carefull Father,</l>
               <l>Againſt the time of Dearth begin to gather,</l>
               <l>Conceiv'd how many ſands are on the ſhore,</l>
               <l>So vaſt, ſo numberleſs was <hi>Joſeph's</hi> ſtore;</l>
               <l>Who, from the Kings Exchequer ſtor'd with Coin,</l>
               <l>Fill'd up both Field and City, then would join</l>
               <l>Barn unto barn, which large repoſitories</l>
               <l>Stood long as Monuments of <hi>Joſeph's</hi> glories.</l>
               <l>Now to prevent all riots he began,</l>
               <l>Which ſtill deſtroyes more than a Famine can,</l>
               <l>Corrupting plenty often is the Nurſe</l>
               <l>Of foul diſeaſe, no bleſſing but curſe,</l>
               <l>Time oft can witneſs, when abuſe begat</l>
               <l>Upon ſo fair a piece ſo foul a Brat.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sev'n times had <hi>Sol</hi> cheer'd the <hi>Cymmerian</hi> coaſt,</l>
               <l>Twelve times ſo oft exchang'd his monthly Hoſt,</l>
               <l>Since Nature like an ill-drawn Picture grew,</l>
               <l>When it is pencill'd with a partiall view;</l>
               <l>Or an unconſtant Parent, whoſe love's blind,</l>
               <l>And ſo imparts his ſtore by <hi>Gavell kind,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since ſhe thus <hi>Egypt</hi> with ſuch plenty bleſt,</l>
               <l>But prov'd almoſt a Stepdame to the reſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:57741:20"/>
               <l>Anon (all things being hurried on the hinge</l>
               <l>Of change, and ſubject to the fatall ſwinge</l>
               <l>Of miſery) here Famine rays'd her ſtage,</l>
               <l>And 'gan, as <hi>Joſeph</hi> did foretell, to rage.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Nile</hi> that was wont to drench their parched earth,</l>
               <l>Now only flow'd in tears to weep their dearth;</l>
               <l>As if ſome pore, or dry-exhauſting vein</l>
               <l>Had drain'd that ſlime that ſhould refreſh their grain;</l>
               <l>The Husband-man lamented, that his ſeed</l>
               <l>Di'd not to live again, the noyſome weed</l>
               <l>Did revell in his labour whoſe exceſs</l>
               <l>Did riot in a fruitfull barrenneſs;</l>
               <l>Thus pin'd he, 'cauſe he liv'd a bootleſs ſlave:</l>
               <l>Now might he with his Plough ſhare dig his grave;</l>
               <l>His Prune-hook uſeleſs was, unleſs the Fate</l>
               <l>Of Dearth therewith he would anticipate.</l>
               <l>Now Famine had preſented her firſt ſcene,</l>
               <l>Which made the frighted Country-man to glean</l>
               <l>His late neglected fields, and that is priz'd</l>
               <l>As a rich Harveſt which was late deſpis'd;</l>
               <l>Another greedily would ſcrape the dough</l>
               <l>That lay neglected in her kneading trough;</l>
               <l>That face, which had Natures freſh liv'ry worn,</l>
               <l>And ſhew'd as verdant as the roſie morn,</l>
               <l>Now full-fac'd plenty had the Land forſook</l>
               <l>Famine diſplay'd pale colours in each look,</l>
               <l>All walking like to naked <hi>Skeletons</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unto their Fellows made their heavy mones;</l>
               <l>Some in the ſtreet did reel, how could they tread</l>
               <l>A ſteady pace, that lack'd the ſtaff of bread?</l>
               <l>Now all neer famiſh'd, and their gleanings done,</l>
               <l>With trembling ſteps they all to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> run,</l>
               <l>As to their Father, making their complaint,</l>
               <l>While ſome through weakneſs in his preſence faint.</l>
               <l>Great Sir quoth one, look how our beautie's blaſted,</l>
               <l>Our ſtrength is ſpent, our ſpirits are exhauſted,</l>
               <l>Our young ones ſtarve, our abler ſtomacks feed,</l>
               <l>(Unleſs thou food ſupply,) on graſs and weed;</l>
               <l>Obſerve how Dearth mocks Death, our nether jawes</l>
               <l>Hang down through weakneſs, while we plead our cauſe;</l>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:57741:20"/>
               <l>Look, look, how ſome would ſpeak, but their faint lungs</l>
               <l>Stop the intendments of their clammy tongues;</l>
               <l>Grant, and diſmiſs us, for we here reſort</l>
               <l>Not for to make a Charnell-houſe thy Court.</l>
               <l>The King prick'd with remorſe of <hi>Egypts</hi> want,</l>
               <l>Thus mildly condeſcends his Princely grant,</l>
               <l>Quoth he, go, and what <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhall injoyn</l>
               <l>Obey, doubt not, his ſpirit is divine.</l>
               <l>That ſaid, they croucht their thanks, have you obſerv'd</l>
               <l>How that a Falcon through neglect neer ſtarv'd,</l>
               <l>Soon as her Keeper comes within her ſight,</l>
               <l>Both makes an eager, though a ſlug-like flight,</l>
               <l>Unto her prey, and though her limbs be weak,</l>
               <l>Shee fiercely tugs it with her ragged beak;</l>
               <l>So the <hi>Egyptians</hi> in a numerous preſs</l>
               <l>To <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Palace, make their full addreſs,</l>
               <l>Some dumbly paſſionating begg'd, ſome kiſt</l>
               <l>His feet, who op'ning all his ſtore diſmiſt</l>
               <l>Them all without a rigorous diſpute,</l>
               <l>With a glad burthen of their purchas'd ſute.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now <hi>Egypt</hi> in this fatall time of dearth</l>
               <l>Remain'd the onely Store-houſe of the Earth,</l>
               <l>The worlds chief Granary, of grain the ſole</l>
               <l>Exchequer of each Land from Pole to Pole;</l>
               <l>Ev'n <hi>Canaan</hi> on whoſe rich abounding ſtore</l>
               <l>Once lived thirtie Kings, muſt now implore</l>
               <l>Her neighbours help, glad if ſhe might in peace</l>
               <l>Be made partaker of her bleſt increaſe;</l>
               <l>Among whom (ſo did Providence deſign)</l>
               <l>Old <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Sons began to pine</l>
               <l>Through dearth; the palat late ſo liquoriſh,</l>
               <l>Would gladly banquet on a common-diſh;</l>
               <l>Oft <hi>Jacob</hi> ruminates and weighs the cauſe</l>
               <l>Why were all Kingdomes offer'd to the jawes</l>
               <l>Of Famine, then concludes they'r juſtly curſt,</l>
               <l>Since they ſuch monſtrous ſinners long had nurſt;</l>
               <l>Then would he doubt leſt that his Childrens ſin</l>
               <l>Had brought this Curſe on fertile <hi>Paleſtine.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then ſeeks with Sacrifice for to appeaſe</l>
               <l>The heavens wrath, ſo might their fields increaſe;</l>
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:57741:21"/>
               <l>Diſtruſt he would not, for he did believe</l>
               <l>God would redeem him with a ſafe reprieve,</l>
               <l>Who promis'd that his ſeed (though death did rage)</l>
               <l>Should have their Country for their Heritage;</l>
               <l>While thus imagination had ingroſt</l>
               <l>His ſenſe, and fancy thus divinely gloſt;</l>
               <l>He calls his ſons, to whom, you may ſuppoſe,</l>
               <l>His ſmother'd thoughts old <hi>Jacob</hi> did diſcloſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>My Sons, quoth he you know our Corn is ſpent,</l>
               <l>And little's left either in Field or Tent,</l>
               <l>Our plenty-pregnant ſins have now at laſt</l>
               <l>Brought forth a Dearth, the mighty <hi>Protoplaſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Mov'd by our monſtrous ſins hath ſtrongly ſeel'd</l>
               <l>The heav'ns with braſs, and th'earth beneath hath ſteel'd:</l>
               <l>And Death and Famine two remorſleſs Mates,</l>
               <l>Triumphing ride, and knock at all our gates;</l>
               <l>Thoſe dainties fail that fed our glutt'nous luſt,</l>
               <l>Our chalkie teeth have loſt their unctuous ruſt,</l>
               <l>Why do you whiſper thus, why do you gaze</l>
               <l>One on another? let your Lambkins graze.</l>
               <l>There's Corn in <hi>Egypt,</hi> goe and buy, my ſons,</l>
               <l>That we may live, we and our little ones.</l>
               <l>You know our fruitfull fields forbear to teem,</l>
               <l>We ſtarve, unleſs your ſpeedy care redeem;</l>
               <l>Go, and make haſte my ſons, your Brothers pain</l>
               <l>Shall be redoubled till you come again;</l>
               <l>Your Sheep ſhall feed upon their pleaſant grounds,</l>
               <l>No Goat ſhall rove beyond his wonted bounds,</l>
               <l>No Dog ſhall fright, no rav'nous Beaſt purſue</l>
               <l>With fearfull flight a Kid or tender Ewe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>No dull delay could their intents adjourn,</l>
               <l>But when ſtout <hi>Chaunticleer</hi> had wak'd the morn,</l>
               <l>The carefull Brethren with a ruſtick port</l>
               <l>Knockt to fair <hi>Memphis,</hi> then to <hi>Joſephs</hi> Court;</l>
               <l>For he it was who did diſpenſe the Corn</l>
               <l>To thoſe whom meager Death had made forelorn.</l>
               <l>Anon to <hi>Joſeph</hi> they themſelves addreſt</l>
               <l>With great ſubmiſſion, and with lowly creſt</l>
               <l>The proſtrate <hi>Ten</hi> unto his Lordſhip croucht,</l>
               <l>In every look humility was coucht,</l>
               <pb n="37" facs="tcp:57741:21"/>
               <l>Whom <hi>Joſeph</hi> knew, yet he his paſſion checkt,</l>
               <l>And ſtrangely views them with a ſtern aſpect;</l>
               <l>And thus began What are you, and from whence?</l>
               <l>Under what clime have you your reſidence?</l>
               <l>Quoth they Great Maſter, <hi>Canan</hi> is our home,</l>
               <l>Hither to buy food are thy ſervants come.</l>
               <l>Their lowlineſs remembring him the truth</l>
               <l>Of his preſaging Dreams while yet a Youth.</l>
               <l>Now might pale rancour ſwell, revenge inſult,</l>
               <l>And malice might demand no common mulct,</l>
               <l>And envy by that ſeeming Juſtice backt</l>
               <l>Of like for like, might proudly now exact</l>
               <l>Great recompence, a Dungeon well might ſit</l>
               <l>Their cruelty that doom'd him to the Pit;</l>
               <l>The law of Nature now might ſeem to crave</l>
               <l>As they had him, ſo he ſhould them inſlave;</l>
               <l>And in remembrance of their ſlouts, in ſcorn</l>
               <l>Diſmiſs them hopeleſs, and deny them Corn.</l>
               <l>Where envy is the memories Recorder,</l>
               <l>Expect proceedings in remo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſlleſs order;</l>
               <l>But he ne'r entertain'd <hi>Her</hi> as a gueſt,</l>
               <l>Much leſs a Tenant, in his peacefull Breſt;</l>
               <l>Their ſight his pitty, not revenge begate,</l>
               <l>His blood did daunce for joy, not boyl with hate;</l>
               <l>Yet though his bowels did through paſſion yern,</l>
               <l>As were his looks, thus his reproofs were ſtern.</l>
               <l>Quoth he, what made you hither to repair</l>
               <l>To leave your own, to breath a forreign air?</l>
               <l>How careleſs is our guard? how have they watch'd?</l>
               <l>That ſuch ſuſpitious Spies paſs unattach'd?</l>
               <l>Y'are Spies, our tortures ſhall the truth extort,</l>
               <l>Why you thus ſaucily approach our Court;</l>
               <l>You come to ſpie our weakneſs, you ſhall feel</l>
               <l>What ſtrength our Country hath, perhaps our Steel.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Our ſins makes God ſeem ſtrange, as clouds we ſee</l>
               <l>Shrowd th'ey of heav'en, ſo ſin Gods heav'nly ey;</l>
               <l>Or if but ſeen his cheeks with an anger glow,</l>
               <l>Wrath's on his ey thron'd, ruin on his brow,</l>
               <l>And while they ſin, as Traitors he attaints</l>
               <l>Unto his Covenant, his deareſt Saints.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="38" facs="tcp:57741:22"/>
               <l>The Brethren ſtarted at theſe thundring words,</l>
               <l>The active blood within each body curds,</l>
               <l>Quoth they, let not your Lordſhip this Impute,</l>
               <l>Nor miſ-interpret our unfeigned ſute,</l>
               <l>We all the tincture have of one mans blood,</l>
               <l>Who hither hath us ſent to buy ſome food,</l>
               <l>And ſo let heaven with thy ſervants deal,</l>
               <l>As we intend unto your Common-weal.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wee'll have the truth of this upon the racks,</l>
               <l>Quoth he, your ſute, your Aſſes and your Sacks</l>
               <l>Are meer pretences, you are all but Spies,</l>
               <l>Theſe ſpecious colours cannot blind our eyes.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>We're twelve, quoth they, and by one man begot,</l>
               <l>The youngeſt is at home, and one is not,</l>
               <l>We are no ſuch, that to ſuch ends do rome,</l>
               <l>Hither to buy food are thy ſervants come;</l>
               <l>Let not your Lordſhip trample miſerie;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pitty a ſtrangers privilege ſhould be;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>O do not cenſure, w'are ſo innocent</l>
               <l>We ſcarce conceive what by your words is meant;</l>
               <l>If want be treaſon, and to come to buy</l>
               <l>Food be invaſion, then we come to ſpy.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Y'are Spies, quoth he, vain words no longer urge,</l>
               <l>They are too empty this your guilt to purge,</l>
               <l>Since you no other voucher can produce</l>
               <l>To prove your truth, but only this excuſe,</l>
               <l>My Sentence, like my words, none may revoke,</l>
               <l>Send for that youngeſt Son of whom you ſpoke;</l>
               <l>Unleſs that Brother prove your evidence,</l>
               <l>By <hi>Pharaohs</hi> life yee ſhall not part from hence,</l>
               <l>Send one, mean while ye ſhall be all reſtraind</l>
               <l>To prove if that your words be true or feign'd,</l>
               <l>But if th'event convince you of a lie,</l>
               <l>Why then by <hi>Pharaohs</hi> life ye come to ſpie.</l>
               <l>Now were the Brethren all impriſoned.</l>
               <l>Till thrice the Sun had left <hi>Aurora's</hi> bed;</l>
               <l>When thus his Lordſhip ſpake. Sirs if y'are true,</l>
               <l>Doe this, I fear a God as well as you,</l>
               <l>If your cauſe ſpring from an unfeigned ſource,</l>
               <l>No falſe injuſtice ſhall divert its courſe;</l>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:57741:22"/>
               <l>If true, you blunt, if falſe, you whet the edge</l>
               <l>Of our proceedings, leave one as a Pledge</l>
               <l>Of our return, yet ſee you doe not fail,</l>
               <l>None but that Brother proves your pledges bayl.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now conſcience like a wound by time o'r-skin'd,</l>
               <l>(Launc'd by the memory of what they'd ſinn'd)</l>
               <l>Grew to an Ulcer, which ſeem'd ſound before,</l>
               <l>And guilt, like <hi>Titius</hi> Vultur gripes the ſore;</l>
               <l>Croſſes the Midwives to the conſcience be,</l>
               <l>From the groſs womb of dull ſecurity;</l>
               <l>As <hi>Sols</hi> fierce heat diſſolves the ycic plain,</l>
               <l>That drowns the murmur of the roaring main;</l>
               <l>So croſſes ſoon the frozen heart-ſtrings thaw,</l>
               <l>As if a flaming Hell were in the Maw,</l>
               <l>Heart-gnawing Vultures gripes are not ſo fierce</l>
               <l>As thoſe, that do a frighted conſcience pierce;</l>
               <l>Like a fierce lightning which doth frie at once</l>
               <l>The marrow, and incinerates the bones.</l>
               <l>No Tyrants cruelty, nor are the phangs</l>
               <l>Of rav'nous Beaſts more horrid than thoſe pangs,</l>
               <l>Which now the Brethren knew, when that they felt</l>
               <l>Their wounded hearts even in their Breſts to melt;</l>
               <l>Brethren, quoth one would we could <hi>that</hi> forget</l>
               <l>Which doth our conſcience-ſeared heart-ſtrings fret,</l>
               <l>When we (O horrid piacle inroll'd</l>
               <l>In heavens notaries) our Brother ſold,</l>
               <l>Tyrants had wept, but we would not condole</l>
               <l>The bitter anguiſh of his troubled ſoul;</l>
               <l>This Curſe our Brother did to us bequeath,</l>
               <l>Whom we undoubtedly betrayd to death;</l>
               <l>The fact was haynous, and the ſin moſt groſs,</l>
               <l>So here is rage for rage, and croſs for croſs;</l>
               <l>Me thinks, as yet, his mones do pierce my ears,</l>
               <l>My heart drops blood, faſt as his ey wept tears;</l>
               <l>Our ſcourging conſcience more doth tyrannize,</l>
               <l>Than did our rage upon ſo weak a prize.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ſaid, quoth <hi>Reuben,</hi> Brethren, ſpake, not I</l>
               <l>(Soon as I heard your Plot your Tragedy)</l>
               <l>Although I fortun'd not to intervene,</l>
               <l>When you were acting of that rigid Scene.</l>
               <pb n="40" facs="tcp:57741:23"/>
               <l>O ſpare the Child, but you prov'd to my plea</l>
               <l>As deaf and unrelenting as the Sea;</l>
               <l>Bondage is <hi>Bawd</hi> to death, I fear whoſe kniſe</l>
               <l>Made quick abridgement of his tender life;</l>
               <l>We juſtly bondage fear, and which is worſe,</l>
               <l>His blood may challenge blood, a greater curſe,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Little the Brethren thought that their remorſe</l>
               <l>Of Conſcience, their language and diſcourſe</l>
               <l>His Lordſhip underſtood, whoſe meanings were</l>
               <l>Deliver'd them by an Interpreter;</l>
               <l>Who now no longer could his paſſion ſmother,</l>
               <l>But as in Tydes one wave purſues another,</l>
               <l>Oft ceaſing not, till in their rolling ranks</l>
               <l>They drown all Barriers and fencing Banks;</l>
               <l>So at each circumſtance his paſſion higher</l>
               <l>And higher ſwell'd, then did ſo high aſpire,</l>
               <l>That he retiring could not tears refrain,</l>
               <l>But through his eyes diſcharg'd his troubled brain;</l>
               <l>Who though the rain was paſt, would yet allow</l>
               <l>Some frowning clouds to triumph on his Brow.</l>
               <l>Anon quoth he returning to the room,</l>
               <l>Your reaſon's woven in too thin a Loom,</l>
               <l>To take our faith, my will by oath is ſeal'd,</l>
               <l>By vow my ſentence not to be repeal'd;</l>
               <l>Since you no other evidence a lege</l>
               <l>To prove your truth, thus will I chooſe my pledge;</l>
               <l>Before them all then <hi>Simeon</hi> was bound;</l>
               <l>Ev'n thus, quoth he, the truth I'll juſtly ſound</l>
               <l>Of your intents, you gain no further grace,</l>
               <l>Unleſs that younger Brother ſee my face;</l>
               <l>That youngeſt Brother only ſhall redeem</l>
               <l>This Brother bound then traffick with eſteem.</l>
               <l>Why do you whiſper thus? ſpeak, if your cauſe</l>
               <l>Be juſt demur not thus, <hi>Truth needs no pauſe.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now had he charg'd the Steward of his Treaſure</l>
               <l>To fill their Sacks with Corn in bounteous meaſure,</l>
               <l>To ſtore them for the journey, and to pack</l>
               <l>Their Money in the mouth of each mans Sack.</l>
               <l>Their Aſſes loaden, now you may conceive</l>
               <l>With humble promiſes they take their leave,</l>
               <pb n="41" facs="tcp:57741:23"/>
               <l>And leſt old <hi>Jacob</hi> might through <hi>their</hi> delay</l>
               <l>Do not leſt <hi>they</hi> might prove an untimely prey</l>
               <l>Unto ſome danger, leſt his hopes might bleed</l>
               <l>T'a lingring death they make the greater ſpeed.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now at his Inne as each his Aſſe did bait,</l>
               <l>Opening their Sacks, their Money in full weight</l>
               <l>Was in their Sacks mouth, much they did reſent</l>
               <l>With ſad amazement that ſtrange accident;</l>
               <l>One doubted <hi>Egypts</hi> ſpells, another fear'd</l>
               <l>Th'abuſed <hi>Medium,</hi> which another clear'd;</l>
               <l>A third non-payment, and a fourth purſute,</l>
               <l>But all concluded in confus'd diſpute;</l>
               <l>But all grant 'twas an act that God had wrought,</l>
               <l>Which ſhould b'unravel'd far beyond their thought.</l>
               <l>Conceive them now at home, where, you may gheſs,</l>
               <l>They tell their Father of their ſad ſucceſs;</l>
               <l>Dear Sir, quoth one, the Maſter of the Land</l>
               <l>Dealt roughly with us, and began to brand</l>
               <l>Us with the name of Spies, as ſome that aim'd</l>
               <l>To ſearch their weakneſs, which we all diſclaim'd,</l>
               <l>We humbly all our ſute for Corn inferr'd</l>
               <l>As witneſs of our truth, and more averr'd,</l>
               <l>We're twelve, quoth we, and by one man begot,</l>
               <l>The youngeſt is at home, and one is not;</l>
               <l>Excuſe, nor plea, could not maintain our cauſe,</l>
               <l>But <hi>He</hi> th'advantage taking of that clauſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The youngeſt is at home,</hi> thus aim'd to prove.</l>
               <l>Where we were ſuch that to ſuch ends did rove;</l>
               <l>Quoth he, where either you ſpeak truth, or feign,</l>
               <l>I'll doe no more than Juſtice ſhall maintain;</l>
               <l>Take for to nurſe your houſes and be gon,</l>
               <l>And come not here without that youngeſt Son.</l>
               <l>If y'have at home a Brother, as you ſpoke,</l>
               <l>That labours with you under the ſame yoke</l>
               <l>Of filiall duty, if you here approach</l>
               <l>Sans him, as Spies, no doubt, you now encroach;</l>
               <l>And that you may conceive, how far your wit</l>
               <l>Shall fail of our ſuſpect you to acquit,</l>
               <l>Let one of you, here, as your Pledge reſide</l>
               <l>Till your return, ſo ſhall your truth be tri'd.</l>
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:57741:24"/>
               <l>You me, quoth mourning <hi>Jacob,</hi> have beguil'd</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Simeon</hi> now, and <hi>Joſeph</hi> whilſt a Child;</l>
               <l>And think you with this ſlight me to ſupplant?</l>
               <l>To take his Brother? This I cannot grant.</l>
               <l>At this, quoth <hi>R<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uben,</hi> let my Sons be ſlain,</l>
               <l>If I return thy ſon not ſafe again;</l>
               <l>Both <hi>mine</hi> I'll ſacrifice unto thy rigour,</l>
               <l>If that he come not home, in perfect vigour.</l>
               <l>My Son, quoth <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſhall not hence go down</l>
               <l>To be a prey to thoſe of <hi>Memphis</hi> town,</l>
               <l>The journey's dangerous, and at each pace</l>
               <l>Death may arreſt him with his Ebon Mace;</l>
               <l>Oh be advis'd, my ſons, when <hi>Joſeph</hi> di'd,</l>
               <l>My Soul neer ſayl'd forth with his purple tide;</l>
               <l>And ſhould his Brother fail, the ſelf ſame dart</l>
               <l>Would cut the Cables of my an'chring heart,</l>
               <l>Or weigh it from my boſomes anchorage;</l>
               <l>Deliberate, take pitty on my age.</l>
               <l>Now <hi>Jacobs</hi> Corn was ſpent, and yet this year</l>
               <l>Small ſhew of future harveſt did appear,</l>
               <l>Who calling for his Children, thus began;</l>
               <l>My Sons, quoth he, life, which ſome tearm a ſpan</l>
               <l>Dearth will t'an inch reduce, and we ſhall wax</l>
               <l>(Being Famine-ſuck'd) as empty as our Sacks.</l>
               <l>Again go buy ſome food, there's yet ſmall hope</l>
               <l>That th'heavens will their wonted fatneſs drop;</l>
               <l>Your Brother ſhall take care, that while you want,</l>
               <l>No rav'nous Beaſt neer to your folds ſhall haunt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At this, quoth <hi>Judah, Egypts</hi> Maſter ſwore</l>
               <l>He neither would our Brother bound reſtore,</l>
               <l>Nor yet ſupply our wants, untill thy Son</l>
               <l>Appeard before his face as we have done;</l>
               <l>If he be ſent we'll go; ſince here are graves,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould we hence to dy <hi>Egyptian</hi> ſlaves?</l>
               <l>Quoth <hi>Iacob,</hi> why ſpoke you of <hi>Benjamin?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now ill betide ſuch an unnat'rall ſin,</l>
               <l>You might the matter with more judgement wave,</l>
               <l>Unleſs you meant to hiſs me to my grave.</l>
               <l>Dear Sir, quoth they, with us <hi>He</hi> ſubtly dealt,</l>
               <l>And roughly asked of us where we dwelt,</l>
               <pb n="43" facs="tcp:57741:24"/>
               <l>Then of our Kindred, and our Fathers life,</l>
               <l>Then of the youngeſt ſon began the ſtrife,</l>
               <l>Who thought ſuch ſtrife would from theſe words ariſe,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The youngeſt is at home,</hi> through his deviſe?</l>
               <l>Dear Sir quoth <hi>Iudah,</hi> if we thus divide,</l>
               <l>We ſhall be guilty <hi>all</hi> of <hi>ſuicide,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since, though w'are brought unto thoſe exigents,</l>
               <l>God to prevent our Dearth the means preſents;</l>
               <l>Of me require him, may my hopes be rackt</l>
               <l>On all extremities, thy rage compact</l>
               <l>With danger to o'rthrow me, may my name</l>
               <l>Be henceforth branded with eternall ſhame</l>
               <l>T'have ſlain my Fathers joyes, if that the Swain</l>
               <l>Be not ſafe to thy Boſome brought again:</l>
               <l>If thou hadſt ſent him, which thou wouldſt not grant.</l>
               <l>We now had laught with ſtore, who weep through wan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>Our Sacks that now exhauſted are, and empty,</l>
               <l>Repleniſh'd with our care had ſwell'd with plenty.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Well then, quoth <hi>Jacob,</hi> ſince it muſt be ſo,</l>
               <l>And that I muſt thus needs embrace my woe,</l>
               <l>Goe take a Preſent for the man, <hi>the ſavour</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Oft of a little brings the greateſt favour.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He may your Brother from his Bonds releaſe,</l>
               <l>Send you repleniſh'd home, my Son in peace;</l>
               <l>Take Nuts and Almonds, Myrrhe, ſweet Balm, and Ho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </l>
               <l>And leſt there were miſtakes, take double Money.</l>
               <l>Dear Image of thy ſweet deceaſed Mother,</l>
               <l>Sweet relique of thy too too ſoon ſlain Brother,</l>
               <l>By Natures ſecret and unknown inſtinct,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Thine</hi> to my cords of life, are ſtrongly linckt</l>
               <l>In a firm Union, ſoon again return,</l>
               <l>Leſt ſoon thy abſence hiſs me to my urn.</l>
               <l>Ev'n as a friend who till his cy-ſtrings fail.</l>
               <l>Stands viewing of his Friend late under ſayl,</l>
               <l>As if his feet unto the ſhore did grow,</l>
               <l>Firſt points him out as ſmall as is a crow,</l>
               <l>The maſt to th' diminution of a hair,</l>
               <l>Till all diſſolv'd are quite from that to air.</l>
               <l>So <hi>Iacob</hi> though his Suns began to ſet,</l>
               <l>And that through age almoſt his ey-lids met,</l>
               <pb n="44" facs="tcp:57741:25"/>
               <l>Long correſpondence with their motion kept,</l>
               <l>Then out of ſight he turn'd his head and wept.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Omit their weary journeys <hi>tedium,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Cold fear already did their ſenſe benumn,</l>
               <l>For now they ſaw (ſo may your fancy prompt)</l>
               <l>Fair <hi>Memphis,</hi> Arts chief pride, and Natures pomp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </l>
               <l>Who now with Country gates, and ruſtick greets</l>
               <l>To the nice Citizens, knockt through their ſtreets:</l>
               <l>Then did they all to <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Palace plod,</l>
               <l>Each one approaching with a ſubmiſſive nod;</l>
               <l>Soon <hi>Joſeph</hi> at firſt-ſight his Brother knew,</l>
               <l>Soon joy and fear their tears began to brew;</l>
               <l>Then charg'd the Steward of the houſe to haſt,</l>
               <l>For they at night with him ſhould take repaſt;</l>
               <l>Long had they not attended, till a Groom</l>
               <l>Conducted them into an inner room;</l>
               <l>When Conſcience to its former rigour grew,</l>
               <l>And Fear of danger pierc'd the wound anew,</l>
               <l>Fear made ſtrange deſcants, and few could conclude</l>
               <l>Why they, in manners rough, in habit rude,</l>
               <l>Were uſed kindly thus, unleſs to cloak</l>
               <l>Their cloſe intents to ſeiz them, and to yoak</l>
               <l>Them as their ſlaves, or how God had diſpos'd</l>
               <l>About the Money in their Sacks inclos'd.</l>
               <l>Whereof they fearing now a rough inqueſt,</l>
               <l>Themſelves to <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Steward thus addreſt;</l>
               <l>Sir, long it is not, ſince with full-ſtufft Sacks</l>
               <l>We left the noiſe of <hi>Nilus</hi> Cataracts,</l>
               <l>Since we t'your Maſter ow'd, we are not brought</l>
               <l>(Being Dearth exhauſted) to our former nought,</l>
               <l>But fears have mixt ſweet joy with ſow'r conceit,</l>
               <l>We in our Sacks our Coin found in full weight;</l>
               <l>Of this event we often have revolv'd,</l>
               <l>Which yet ſtands undetermind, unreſolv'd;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pitty with caſuall errors oft diſpenſeth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>While cruelty miſtakes, as fauls commenceth;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Unleſs we much miſtook, our money weigh'd</l>
               <l>In equall ballances we truly pay'd,</l>
               <l>Yet that we payd it, we will not aver,</l>
               <l>For memory is frail, and we may erre,</l>
               <pb n="45" facs="tcp:57741:25"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>But faults are loſt i'th' name of Innocence,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Since what e'r hap'ned'twas not meant offence;</l>
               <l>Deceit could not advantage, ſince we knew</l>
               <l>We ſhortly muſt our former ſute renew,</l>
               <l>Great Sir 'twas no impoſture, for, <hi>What ſtranger</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Is ſo fool-hardy as to play with danger?</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Then here accept your due, and grant our ſute</l>
               <l>On like Conditions for a new recruit.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sirs, quoth the Steward, to remove your terrour,</l>
               <l>There was no falſe deceit, nor caſuall errour,</l>
               <l>I had your coin, nor will deſerve the curſe</l>
               <l>To take th'advantage on a ſtrangers purſe;</l>
               <l>I had good weight, as you had bounteous meaſure,</l>
               <l>Then traffique with eſteem, and trade at pleaſure;</l>
               <l>Your God, your Fathers God, whom you adore</l>
               <l>Did each mans Money in his Sack reſtore;</l>
               <l>None ſhall your perſons hurt, your ſtate impair,</l>
               <l>Our actions, like your faces, ſhall be fair;</l>
               <l>And you (his Lordſhip ſeldome grants this boon)</l>
               <l>Muſt at my Maſters table dine at noon;</l>
               <l>Half all mens hearts are <hi>His,</hi> mil'd courteſie,</l>
               <l>That wins each heart, ſits ſmiling in his eye.</l>
               <l>As token that his Lordſhip thus was pleas'd,</l>
               <l>Their Brother <hi>Simeon</hi> was ſtraight releas'd,</l>
               <l>Who, unattended with a ridgid Mace,</l>
               <l>Was now ſaluted with a glad embrace;</l>
               <l>Now were a little of their fears ſuſpended,</l>
               <l>And they to <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Houſe were all attended;</l>
               <l>One brought in water with a courteous greet,</l>
               <l>To waſh their journey-dirt-bedaubed feet,</l>
               <l>One dreſt their Aſſes, in officious duty,</l>
               <l>Another ſhew'd the Palace and its beauty;</l>
               <l>All which, thus ſhew'd ſo far beyond their merits</l>
               <l>They rather thought dreams of their troubled ſpirits</l>
               <l>Than reall objects, now they 'gan to ſhape</l>
               <l>Them in their beſt attire, anew to ape</l>
               <l>The ſeemlieſt poſtures, how they might preſent</l>
               <l>The Token with a grace their Father ſent,</l>
               <l>Then all of Table courteſie combine,</l>
               <l>Becauſe they heard they with the Lord ſhould dine.</l>
               <pb n="46" facs="tcp:57741:26"/>
               <l>Gladly did <hi>Joſeph</hi> his affairs prorogue,</l>
               <l>Now were deferr'd the needy <hi>Catalogue,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Imagine him returned to his houſe,</l>
               <l>Where they with humble thanks, with hearty vowes,</l>
               <l>In great ſubmiſſion proſtrate on their face,</l>
               <l>Tender their Fathers Preſent to his Grace.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sirs, quoth his Lordſhip, if I erre not much</l>
               <l>You are the ſame, or very like to ſuch</l>
               <l>Whom I as Spies ſuſpected, if y'are ttue,</l>
               <l>Preſent that youngeſt Brother to my view;</l>
               <l>Oft-times hath <hi>Phoebus</hi> wheel'd about his teem,</l>
               <l>Yet you ne'r came to gain your loſt eſteem,</l>
               <l>And yet, I fear, the day is yet to dawn.</l>
               <l>Wherein you will redeem again your Pawn.</l>
               <l>Sir (quoth they, crouching) we at length have won</l>
               <l>Our wary Father for to ſend his Son,</l>
               <l>Our former callow hopes again are fledge.</l>
               <l>That you to freedome will reſtore our pledge.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As yet quoth <hi>Joſeph,</hi> doth that old man breath?</l>
               <l>Hath Fate not yet betray'd him unto death?</l>
               <l>Is death yet retrograde? hath yet your God</l>
               <l>Unto your Famine ſet a period?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Sir, quoth they, our Father yet doth breath</l>
               <l>Through heav'n and you, but no triumphant wreath</l>
               <l>Of full-ear'd Harveſt crowns the Husbands brows,</l>
               <l>Nor one ſmali Sheaf doth anſwer all our vowes;</l>
               <l>Our Father lives, though not with wonted heat</l>
               <l>His heart with healthy vigour yet doth beat;</l>
               <l>As yet he lives, unleſs his life be ſpun</l>
               <l>To th'utmoſt thread, through abſence of his Son;</l>
               <l>By us he beggs you, Sir, (though we are rude,</l>
               <l>And though of language indigeſt and crude)</l>
               <l>This preſent as the Intereſt t'accept</l>
               <l>Of a more vaſt, and far immenſe a debt;</l>
               <l>Is this, quoth <hi>Joſeph,</hi> he of whom I ſware,</l>
               <l>That being owes, and life to the ſame care,</l>
               <l>Of the ſame Sire with you? they, on their knee</l>
               <l>Falling ſubmiſſively, ſay this is he.</l>
               <l>Let God, quoth <hi>Joſeph</hi> from his bounteous treaſure</l>
               <l>Showr on thee bleſſings in a gracious meaſure;</l>
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:57741:26"/>
               <l>I now my Cenſure willingly revoke,</l>
               <l>Gladly releaſe your brother from this yoak,</l>
               <l>Untill your miſerie be retrograde,</l>
               <l>You ſhall b'admitted here in peace to trade.</l>
               <l>Y'are proof enough, y'are of an honeſt tribe,</l>
               <l>What doth this Preſent mean? <hi>I ruth needs no bribe.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Scarce could he Paſſion check, which would eruct</l>
               <l>What he would have concealed, ſcarce obſtruct</l>
               <l>His tears, which now like billowes rais'd by wind,</l>
               <l>Diſdain'd within their cells to be confind;</l>
               <l>Which leſt too ſoon they might excell his power</l>
               <l>He ſtept aſide, and wept a plenteous ſhower;</l>
               <l>Thrice had he waſh'd his face, but tears did riſe</l>
               <l>Too great a chanell for his conduit-eyes,</l>
               <l>And he muſt ſtay their weeping, the extent</l>
               <l>Of his large cells had too too ſmall a vent:</l>
               <l>Thrice, had he lockt his door, but all in vain;</l>
               <l>For through the flood-gates broke the ſilver rain;</l>
               <l>Thrice, he in Paſſion, as he paſt the ſtair,</l>
               <l>Did for his Brother hug the empty air:</l>
               <l>Then muſt return, for tears again did trace</l>
               <l>Their rivulets upon his blubber'd face:</l>
               <l>Scarce could he with his Paſſion take a truce,</l>
               <l>Scarce could he ſtop his tear-betraying ſluce;</l>
               <l>His reeking cheeks, like Roſes rain-bedaſht,</l>
               <l>Imagin from their ſtains at length were waſht;</l>
               <l>When Paſſions cloſe recluſe at length came down,</l>
               <l>With looks importing, nor a ſmile nor frown,</l>
               <l>None there deſpaired, through a ſtern reflect,</l>
               <l>None by his pleaſant looks might him ſuſpect;</l>
               <l>At his command the Table ſtrait was ſpread;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>The Dainties uſher'd by a grim death head;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Where <hi>Joſeph</hi> by himſelf was ſerv'd in ſtate;</l>
               <l>His honour had no rivall, knew no mate:</l>
               <l>And <hi>Egypt</hi> 'mongſt all of the Univerſe,</l>
               <l>With th' <hi>Hebrews</hi> might not eat, and ſcarce commerſe.</l>
               <l>Now as each Brothers age excell'd in date</l>
               <l>Of years, each one above another ſate;</l>
               <l>The eldeſt was not Lord, nor th' young'ſt his Page,</l>
               <l>But each took place according to his age;</l>
               <pb n="48" facs="tcp:57741:27"/>
               <l>To whom his Lordſhip ſent to each a diſh,</l>
               <l>And ſo ſurpaſt at once, deſert and wiſh;</l>
               <l>And as, though clouds ſhrowd <hi>Titans</hi> golden ray,</l>
               <l>Through them, unſeen, he doth diſpenſe the day;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Joſeph,</hi> though thus ſtrange, yet did diſpenſe</l>
               <l>Kind welcome through his favours influence;</l>
               <l>As oft the Sun doth through thoſe vapours pierce</l>
               <l>That ſhrowd his beauty from the Univerſe</l>
               <l>So through his auſtere ſtrangeneſs, oft there ſhin'd</l>
               <l>Beams of unwonted favour, while they din'd,</l>
               <l>On <hi>Benjamin,</hi> though few the cauſe could gheſſe,</l>
               <l>Why he was ſerved with a five fold meſſe.</l>
               <l>And though his Lordſhip by no means could brook</l>
               <l>Exceſs his Butler, Luxurie his Cook,</l>
               <l>No <hi>Kickſhawe</hi> wanting was, nor Courtly cate,</l>
               <l>Which they enjoy'd in peace and jolly chat.</l>
               <l>Now heav'n through grief of loſing <hi>Phoebus</hi> light</l>
               <l>In mourning darkneſs entertain'd the night;</l>
               <l>And ſtars like to obſequious Tapors ſhin'd,</l>
               <l>As if lamenting that <hi>their Lord</hi> declin'd;</l>
               <l>When <hi>Joſeph</hi> charg'd the Steward of his Corn</l>
               <l>With early care t'anticipate the morn;</l>
               <l>Yer ſleep the Howlets watchfull ſenſe benum'd.</l>
               <l>Birds chirp their morning peals, or Beetle hum'd;</l>
               <l>In plenteous ſort to fill each Brothers Sack,</l>
               <l>Till ev'n they did with ſwelling plenty crack;</l>
               <l>To give them for their journey and reſtore</l>
               <l>In each ones Sack his Money as before;</l>
               <l>And in the youngeſt Brothers Sack to knit</l>
               <l>His ſilver Cup, <hi>Love's waited on by wit.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Soon as <hi>Aurora</hi> wept her dewy drops,</l>
               <l>And jocund day peer'd on the mountain tops,</l>
               <l>The carefull Brethren kindly were diſmiſt,</l>
               <l>And when departing <hi>Sol</hi> the morn had kiſt,</l>
               <l>His Lordſhip ſent his Steward on purſute</l>
               <l>Of the late ſtrangers to their charge t'impute</l>
               <l>T'have ſtoln his Lordſhips Cup, and thus to gloſs</l>
               <l>With harſh expreſſions on a fault ſo groſs;</l>
               <l>That if his Lordſhips late unwonted care</l>
               <l>Wrought no impreſſion, yet how they did dare</l>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:57741:27"/>
               <l>T'abuſe him thus, whoſe power like the Kings</l>
               <l>Could reach far off like wide-ſtretcht Dragons wings?</l>
               <l>That not deliberation could of time</l>
               <l>Nor cloſe evaſions excuſe this crime;</l>
               <l>That 'twas the Cup by which his Lord divin'd,</l>
               <l>No weak conjecture of a doubtfull mind.</l>
               <l>This ſpoke, that by this means he might reduce</l>
               <l>Them, on pretence to anſwer this abuſe,</l>
               <l>The carefull Steward this command diſcharg'd,</l>
               <l>And wiſely on the premiſes enlarg'd;</l>
               <l>Soon like a biting froſt this fierce arreſt,</l>
               <l>Nipt all the hopes that budded on their creſt;</l>
               <l>Great Sir, quoth they why ſpeaks my Lord theſe words?</l>
               <l>They of our hearts diſſect the tender cords;</l>
               <l>God, who Heaven rules, and Hells infernall vault,</l>
               <l>Knows we are innocent, free from this fault,</l>
               <l>Fearing miſtakes, we brought again our Coin,</l>
               <l>Why ſhould we Gold or Silver then purloin?</l>
               <l>Wee'll this offence not with pretences gild,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Truth needs no colour,</hi> let his blood be ſwill'd</l>
               <l>By the ſevereſt Juſtice at a ſup,</l>
               <l>With whomſoe'r is found his Lordſhips Cup.</l>
               <l>Well, quoth the Steward, as you ſay, I'll deal,</l>
               <l>Your words are juſt, and I to them appeal,</l>
               <l>With whomſoe'r his Lordſhips Cup is found.</l>
               <l>Ev'n as you ſpoke, he ſhall my ſlave be bound;</l>
               <l>But yee ſhall all be free through innocence,</l>
               <l>Since each muſt anſwer for his own offence;</l>
               <l>At this each willingly his Sack unknit,</l>
               <l>While each one ſought himſelf for to acquit,</l>
               <l>The Cup was found knit in the young'ſt his Sack,</l>
               <l>At which ev'n all their ey-ſtrings ſeem'd to crack,</l>
               <l>So ſtars as ſham'd of day I've ſeen to wink,</l>
               <l>So have I ſeen the Snail being hit, to ſhrink</l>
               <l>Within his ſhelly penthouſe, and now fail'd</l>
               <l>Their eyes, as ſudden grief their ey-balls veil'd.</l>
               <l>What ſhould they ſay? for to deny the deed</l>
               <l>Did ſeem a ſhift weak as a <hi>Nilus</hi> reed</l>
               <l>Which would both fail and hurt them, ſhould they lie,</l>
               <l>What ſhould they do? who like a late-ſpawn'd frie</l>
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:57741:28"/>
               <l>In the wild Sea, were ſubject to the prey</l>
               <l>Of every greater fiſh, ev'n ſo ſeem'd they.</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Beniamin</hi> ſpar'd neither vowes nor oaths</l>
               <l>To back his innocence, each rent his cloathes</l>
               <l>And back in grief returned to the City</l>
               <l>Submiſſively to crave his Lordſhips pitie.</l>
               <l>Gueſs them return'd, to them the Lord begun,</l>
               <l>What deed is this, quoth he, that you have done?</l>
               <l>I gave you Wine, for which my Cup you ſtole,</l>
               <l>Thought you I had not a divining Soul?</l>
               <l>The fact is evident, then ceaſe to quilt</l>
               <l>A web of ſpecious lies upon your guilt,</l>
               <l>This aggravates what I of late ſuſpected;</l>
               <l>Heav'n will not you ſhould thus paſſe undetected.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Great Sir, quoth they, you juſtly may upbraid</l>
               <l>Us with your love, we juſtly are betrayd,</l>
               <l>The fact is clear, what ſhall we then allege</l>
               <l>To clear our ſelves? and who ſhall be our pledge?</l>
               <l>Wee ſcarce have blood in all our veins, great Lord,</l>
               <l>Enough to ſtain your Vice-revenging ſword;</l>
               <l>Creat Sir, we beg if bondage expiates,</l>
               <l>Our Crime, then mercy rules among the Fates?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nay, quoth the Lord, my heart's not Adamant,</l>
               <l>No rocky Iſle where ſuch like <hi>Furies</hi> haunt,</l>
               <l>Nor hath my Soul ſo liquoriſh a guſt</l>
               <l>That nought but blood can ſatiate her luſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Mercy,</hi> and <hi>Juſtice,</hi> here, are neer a kin,</l>
               <l>Our mercy here's ſtill greater than the ſin;</l>
               <l>Think, I have pitty on your Fathers age,</l>
               <l>Nor will enſlave you all in vaſſalage,</l>
               <l>I'll onely recompence upon that Youth</l>
               <l>That had my Cup, bonds, for his breach of truth.</l>
               <l>No ſore-tormenting <hi>Probe</hi> unto the quick</l>
               <l>More deeply ſearcht a wound, nor of the ſick</l>
               <l>No launcet hit more ſure the maſter-vein,</l>
               <l>Than did his Lordſhips words pierce through each ſwain,</l>
               <l>Who ever thus, in tearms accutely coucht</l>
               <l>Rub'd on the matter they would have untoucht;</l>
               <l>Some beg'd, ſome wept, and ſome confus'dly mutter'd,</l>
               <l>Some indigeſted reſolutions utter'd,</l>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:57741:28"/>
               <l>At laſt, quoth <hi>Judah,</hi> humbly on his knee,</l>
               <l>Great Sir, yet what you ſpake your vow decree,</l>
               <l>Let not your anger flame, that I, ſo rude</l>
               <l>In language, and in habit, thus intrude;</l>
               <l>You ask'd when firſt wee hither did repair,</l>
               <l>Doth yet your Father breath the common air?</l>
               <l>Have you alive a Brother more at home?</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Our ſpeech in devious falſhoods did not come,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>But kept truths rode,</hi> quoth we, Our Father's old,</l>
               <l>Half wearied Fate doth yet her diſtaff hold,</l>
               <l>We have a Brother more, a youthfull page,</l>
               <l>Whom <hi>He</hi> eſteems the comfort of his age,</l>
               <l>His Fathers joy, ſince his deceaſed Brother,</l>
               <l>The onely Son of his expired mother;</l>
               <l>And ſince our Father's old, and lame, and dim,</l>
               <l>He only walks, and breaths, and ſees in him;</l>
               <l>Then ſaidſt thou, as a witneſs of your truth,</l>
               <l>Bring down your Brother, let me ſee the youth;</l>
               <l>Great Sir, quoth we, our Brother ſtands between</l>
               <l>Death and our Fathers lamp as th'only ſcreen;</l>
               <l>And <hi>He</hi> remov'd our Sires declining ſnuff</l>
               <l>Would ſoon b'extinguiſht by ſome envious puff;</l>
               <l>Yet ſaidſt thou to thy ſervants, bring the Child,</l>
               <l>If that you will we ſhall be reconcil'd;</l>
               <l>All this we to our Father did rehearſe,</l>
               <l>With the proceedings of our laſt commerce;</l>
               <l>Our Corn exhauſted there was long diſpute</l>
               <l>'T wixt Want and Nature, we renew'd our ſute</l>
               <l>To him to ſend our brother, and at large</l>
               <l>Importunately urg'd your Lordſhips charge;</l>
               <l>So, quoth our father, were I moſt forlorn;</l>
               <l>By <hi>Rachaell</hi> I had two children born,</l>
               <l>Whereof one parting hence, became a feaſt</l>
               <l>(Ay me!) I fear unto ſome rav'nou, Beaſt,</l>
               <l>With whom fled half my life, then leave his Brother,</l>
               <l>'Twere Paricide to take away the other;</l>
               <l>O think, my ſons, ſhould you remove the prop</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That ſtayes my age, I in my grave ſhould drop;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Were there a Chryſtall window in each Breſt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>We know no more than what we have confeſt;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="52" facs="tcp:57741:29"/>
               <l>Now ſhould we home, and leave his ſon behind,</l>
               <l>As with Prophetick doubts his fear divin'd,</l>
               <l>Both hope and life would fail him, ſhould I know</l>
               <l>That I my ſelf were the unhappy Bow,</l>
               <l>Through whom falſe death aim'd her remorſleſs dart</l>
               <l>To the true manſion of my Fathers heart,</l>
               <l>What ſhould I do? that ſhall both guilty ſeem,</l>
               <l>Both of my Brothers loſs, and death of him;</l>
               <l>I to my Sire was ſurety for the youth,</l>
               <l>Have pitty on his age, and on my truth.</l>
               <l>When death, quoth I, my lamp of life ſhall quench,</l>
               <l>May my good name dy in a noyſome ſtench;</l>
               <l>And with like vows I heaven did implore,</l>
               <l>If I his ſon not ſafely did reſtore;</l>
               <l>Then if my Lord pleaſe to reverſe his doom,</l>
               <l>I'd gladly ſerve bound in my Brothers room;</l>
               <l>Great Sir, be pleas'd t'admit me in exchange,</l>
               <l>I'd weary cruelty, and mock revenge,</l>
               <l>I'd count deaths ſentence but an idle breath,</l>
               <l>Yer I'd ſeem guilty of my Fathers death.</l>
               <l>Good Sir, have pitty, I would dare to meet</l>
               <l>A Thunderbolt wrapt in a lightning ſheet,</l>
               <l>Yet I'd provoke a Fathers angry gall,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Parents curſes are Propheticall.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>As a new tun'd Cask of unpurged Wine;</l>
               <l>Wind pris'ned in the earth, or like a <hi>Mine,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The one, if clos'd, will make a furious vent;</l>
               <l>The other break forth in a thundring rent;</l>
               <l>Such were his Lordſhips tears, ſuch was his joy,</l>
               <l>Which Paſſion though it long ſeem'd ſtrange and coy,</l>
               <l>And fickle in the wooing, th'end did prove</l>
               <l>In it was coucht a Brothers tender love,</l>
               <l>Which he no more was able to reſiſt,</l>
               <l>Than the quick pulſe that thumpt within his wriſt;</l>
               <l>And joy, like wind impris'ned in the earth,</l>
               <l>Will ſhake th'hearts center but 'twill have a birth.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now ſince he could no longer thus conteſt,</l>
               <l>H'intended ſecretly t'unlock his breaſt,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shame, that's ſins daughter, wer't not for this care</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Might here have prov'd the mother of deſpair;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:57741:29"/>
               <l>
                  <hi>Open reproofs, like an impetuous rain,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Do waſh away, but not refreſh the grain.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now would he think to ſpeak, and then retreat,</l>
               <l>Then on the prize his heart a charge would beat,</l>
               <l>And though the cauſe, as yet, obſcurely ſlept,</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſervants heard him while he wept;</l>
               <l>At laſt he thus began, I <hi>Joſeph</hi> am;</l>
               <l>Is th' Oyl yet ſpent that fed my Fathers flame?</l>
               <l>This on the porches of their ears he beat,</l>
               <l>But all in vain, that ſenſe had left her ſeat.</l>
               <l>And with the eyes, by horrour ſcattered,</l>
               <l>Had to the brain as an <hi>Aſylum</hi> fled;</l>
               <l>Yet being the kingly hearts chief centinells,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He</hi> by degrees diſmiſt them from their cells:</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For ſenſe-bereaving horrors are like lees,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which being once ſtirr'd, will ſinke, but by degrees.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Now, when they ſomething had expell'd their fears,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Hee</hi> with theſe ſpeeches board anew their ears,</l>
               <l>I am your brother <hi>Joſeph</hi> whom you ſold;</l>
               <l>Is yet my Father 'mongſt th'alive inroll'd?</l>
               <l>Come neer, and ſee, I have no falſe reſerves,</l>
               <l>Come, on this viſage ſpend your viſive nerves,</l>
               <l>I am the ſame as when you took my coat,</l>
               <l>Though chang'd in hiew, and of a rougher throat,</l>
               <l>Though heav'n have chang'd my Fortune, years my ſtature,</l>
               <l>Nor time hath chang'd my love, nor clime my nature.</l>
               <l>Fear not, the fact though groſs, ſhall not be blaz'd,</l>
               <l>'Tis from the book of my remembrance rac'd,</l>
               <l>Then judge your ſelves not raſhly, bleſs the deed,</l>
               <l>For I was promis'd to preſerve your ſeed,</l>
               <l>Two years are paſt, wherein remorſleſs dearth,</l>
               <l>Hath knit the bowels of the teeming earth,</l>
               <l>And yet theſe five years <hi>Nile</hi> in vain ſhall flowe,</l>
               <l>The Husband-man in vain ſhall plough and ſow;</l>
               <l>Like a true <hi>Alchimiſt</hi> hath providence,</l>
               <l>Drawn Honey from the Poyſon of offence;</l>
               <l>You ſold, God ſent me hither, heav'n be bleſt,</l>
               <l>That turn'd your very ſin unto the beſt;</l>
               <l>Haſt then, with winged ſwiftneſs, and infuſe</l>
               <l>Freſh ſpirits in our Father with this news,</l>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:57741:30"/>
               <l>Say thus, ſaith <hi>Joſeph,</hi> whom thou thoughtſt to be</l>
               <l>Seal'd in the boſome of eternity;</l>
               <l>Thus ſaith thy Son, who, by the common vogue,</l>
               <l>Was thought one of grim deaths large catalogue;</l>
               <l>Thus ſaith our Brother, here I am ador'd</l>
               <l>As <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Father, and all <hi>Egypts</hi> Lord,</l>
               <l>Come down, thou with thy houſe, thy heards, and flocks,</l>
               <l>Time limps away, methinks, with leaden ſocks</l>
               <l>Untill thou come, accept of my advice,</l>
               <l>Thine ſhall be <hi>Goſhen Egypts</hi> Paradiſe;</l>
               <l>Let no delay this thy deſcent prorogue,</l>
               <l>Leſt Famine in a fatall <hi>Epilogue</hi>
               </l>
               <l>End thee, and thine; come, that with my Protection</l>
               <l>I in ſome ſort may anſwer thy affection.</l>
               <l>The Sun five times ſhall paſs through all his Inns,</l>
               <l>Till dearth ſhall fully expiate our ſins;</l>
               <l>Mean while deſcend, and of my ſtore partake;</l>
               <l>Since heav'n by me prepar'd it for thy ſake.</l>
               <l>Haſt for your own ſakes, that I may refreſh.</l>
               <l>And cloath your naked bones with tender fleſh;</l>
               <l>My words and actions have not divers centers,</l>
               <l>Both end in one, but if upon the tenters</l>
               <l>This ſtretch your faith, beſide the foretold ſigns</l>
               <l>Obſerve this viſage and its wonted lines;</l>
               <l>Sweet <hi>Benjamin,</hi> bleſt were th' <hi>Astrologers,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>If as I know theſe eyes, they knew the Starrs;</l>
               <l>If ſo, though all events be cloſely ſeal'd,</l>
               <l>No doubt the future ſhould be all reveal'd.</l>
               <l>His Lordſhips ſpeeches were no ſooner ended,</l>
               <l>But he and <hi>Benjamin</hi> together blended</l>
               <l>Themſelves in cloſe embraces, both did lie</l>
               <l>Entwined like the <hi>Zodiacks Gemini;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As if they meant, leſt we again ſhould part,</l>
               <l>Come, by the ſtrings let's knit each others heart;</l>
               <l>Their eyes now pay'd their long-retained debt,</l>
               <l>Each on anothers neck entwined wept;</l>
               <l>That done, the reſt with ſweet inviting phraſes</l>
               <l>He even wearied in his cloſe embraces;</l>
               <l>Then kiſt them all, and <hi>Chorus</hi>-like enquir'd</l>
               <l>Again, is not my Father yet expir'd?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:57741:30"/>
               <l>God will be ſu'd to, who no other task</l>
               <l>Impoſeth on our wants, but this, to ask;</l>
               <l>And though he ſeem long in majeſtick pauſe,</l>
               <l>Not onely not to hear, but ſlight our cauſe,</l>
               <l>'Tis but to edge devotion, to inhance</l>
               <l>His Grace upon our Souls before he grants;</l>
               <l>All diſtance then is chang'd to an imbrace,</l>
               <l>Wrath falleth as a Vizzard from his face,</l>
               <l>He not defers, nor his affection ſmothers,</l>
               <l>Nor doth diſdain at all to call us Brothers;</l>
               <l>As one that dreams he's falling from a ſteep</l>
               <l>And tow'ring precipice into the deep,</l>
               <l>Awaking finds himſelf free from ſuch harms,</l>
               <l>And taking ſafe repoſe in friendly arms:</l>
               <l>Such were the Brethrens fears, and ſad extremes,</l>
               <l>Which now did ſeem but fancies and vain dreams,</l>
               <l>When <hi>Joſeph</hi> in their Paſſions <hi>Extaſie</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Reviv'd their ſenſes from their <hi>Lethargie;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With ſundry Paſſions were at once their minds</l>
               <l>Like a Ship toſt 'twixt two oppoſing winds;</l>
               <l>Now would they joy, then grief, by ſhame being backt,</l>
               <l>Their new reſolved greetings would diſtract;</l>
               <l>The tears from divers ſprings ſeem'd to proceed,</l>
               <l>Which they not ſo much ſeem'd to weep, as bleed;</l>
               <l>Within their brain two floods at once aroſe,</l>
               <l>Of joy, and grief, as when two Seas oppoſe;</l>
               <l>Some wept, ſome weeping ſmil'd, like <hi>Aprils</hi> weather,</l>
               <l>Which rains, then ſhines, then rains and ſhines together.</l>
               <l>Now were they all reſolved to regreet</l>
               <l>Their Brothers courteſie, but as a fleet</l>
               <l>Which comming neer the harbour, back is thruſt</l>
               <l>Into the Ocean by ſome angry guſt,</l>
               <l>Shame would retard intention, ſome would ſmother</l>
               <l>In ſilent whiſpering the name of Brother;</l>
               <l>Glad <hi>Reuben</hi> though he gave to God the glory,</l>
               <l>Yet bleſt perſwaſion, and his oratory,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Judah</hi> though he ſold him, yet was bold</l>
               <l>To ſay he joy'd, though griev'd he thus was ſold.</l>
               <l>Now they confeſt his Dreams no vain <hi>Phantaſms,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But heav'nly, and inſpir'd <hi>Enthuſiaſms,</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="56" facs="tcp:57741:31"/>
               <l>Their Sheaves and Stars had bow'd, the ſawcy Boy</l>
               <l>Was now <hi>their</hi> Lord, and <hi>Egypts</hi> chief <hi>Vice-roy;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Glad <hi>Benjamin</hi> admiring the reſults</l>
               <l>Of their immanity, thus now exults,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>A Brother loſt, and found, is worth like mirth,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As if you joyed at a Brothers birth;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Come then let's triumph, for who could expect</l>
               <l>From this ſo bad a cauſe ſo good effect?</l>
               <l>To hear the Lord ſpeak; how he was re-ſold,</l>
               <l>How often faſhion'd in afflictions mold,</l>
               <l>His Chaſtity, which with a full mouth'd blaſt</l>
               <l>Shall fill Fames trump as long as time ſhall laſt,</l>
               <l>How he ran Chance as blind as ever painted,</l>
               <l>Yet he by adoration thus was Sainted</l>
               <l>In mens opinions, would make a dint,</l>
               <l>And deep impreſſion in hearts of flint;</l>
               <l>For joy ſome ſwounded, and each circumſtance</l>
               <l>Of each relation ſtruck them in a trance,</l>
               <l>Each paſſage made each minutes time the mother</l>
               <l>Of ſome new joy ſo one joy crown'd another;</l>
               <l>Had th'whole world ſeen each act, heard each rehearſall,</l>
               <l>No doubt the joy had here been Univerſall.</l>
               <l>T'expreſs the triumph fully would extort</l>
               <l>Deſcriptions treaſury, undoe report.</l>
               <l>Now tell-tale Fame hath with a nimble wing</l>
               <l>Proclam'd theſe tidings to the Court, and King,</l>
               <l>Who thus to <hi>Joſeph,</hi> placed next his Throne,</l>
               <l>We to thy Fathers care, thy Mothers grone,</l>
               <l>All owe our lives, nay more, for to him ſeeng</l>
               <l>Thou being ow'ſt, we owe him <hi>all</hi> well being;</l>
               <l>Now ſince he liveth, and the fatall Star</l>
               <l>That blaſts our Kingdomes plenty, ſpreads ſo far</l>
               <l>Her fatall influence as <hi>Canaans</hi> clime,</l>
               <l>Send for thy Father, on our Souls this crime</l>
               <l>Shall not write <hi>guilt,</hi> that <hi>He</hi> amidſt our ſtore</l>
               <l>Should faint, <hi>whom</hi> for thee, all are bound t'adore;</l>
               <l>To <hi>Him</hi> alone for thee all <hi>Egypts</hi> bound</l>
               <l>So deep, more than conceit hath line to ſound;</l>
               <l>Thy duty ſhall joyn iſſue with my will,</l>
               <l>Since his one life exceeds the num'rous Bill</l>
               <pb n="57" facs="tcp:57741:31"/>
               <l>So far, that daily doth attend our gates,</l>
               <l>As doth one <hi>Phoenix</hi> life whole clouds of Gnats;</l>
               <l>Thus by thy Brethren ſay, wee, youth, and dotage,</l>
               <l>Both lofty Palace, and the lowly cotage,</l>
               <l>Owe thee, the Father of a Son ſo bleſt,</l>
               <l>More than by <hi>Hieroglyhick</hi> can b'expreſt;</l>
               <l>Thus ſaith the King, let not thy thoughts be gravell'd</l>
               <l>In doubts, thy <hi>Joſeph</hi> who my Dreams unravell'd,</l>
               <l>Which all our <hi>Sophies</hi> did in vain examine,</l>
               <l>Shall nouriſh, and protect thee in this famine.</l>
               <l>Which though it have ſet limits to my wiſh,</l>
               <l>And ſcarcity doth ſeaſon every diſh,</l>
               <l>Delay not thy deſcent: for thou deſerveſts</l>
               <l>The greateſt meaſure of our ſev'n years Harveſts.</l>
               <l>This to thy Brethren ſay, go take the beſt</l>
               <l>That <hi>Egypt</hi> yeelds, and lead each man his beaſt,</l>
               <l>Since that remorſleſſe dearth to death proſcribes</l>
               <l>Your aged Father and his hopefull tribes,</l>
               <l>Think <hi>Egypts</hi> King for <hi>Joſeph's</hi> ſake deplores</l>
               <l>Your empty Wine-preſſes and threſhing-floores;</l>
               <l>Go, bring your Father down, if <hi>Egypts</hi> Map.</l>
               <l>Have land whoſe poares breath a more vigo'rous ſap</l>
               <l>Than <hi>this,</hi> that is more fertile and more pleaſant,</l>
               <l>Come down, none ſhall reſiſt thee, <hi>Peer</hi> nor <hi>Peaſant;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This ſay, and for thy Fathers eaſe take Waggons,</l>
               <l>And for thy Brethren, ſpare no ſprightly Flaggons</l>
               <l>To ratifie their welcome, ſince with them</l>
               <l>Thou art a Branch ſprung from the ſelf ſame ſtem.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Glad <hi>Joſeph</hi> was that <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> thus inclin'd</l>
               <l>To what before he had himſelf deſign'd;</l>
               <l>Envy could not upbraid his want of love,</l>
               <l>So much he did the means, and time improve,</l>
               <l>Scarce <hi>Morpheus</hi> could at all betray his ſenſe,</l>
               <l>But care would counter-charm <hi>His</hi> influence,</l>
               <l>When bright <hi>Hyperion</hi> mounted <hi>Phlegons</hi> back,</l>
               <l>He gave command to fill each Brothers Sack,</l>
               <l>To all he gave proviſion, leſt the length</l>
               <l>Of the large journey, ſhould exceed their ſtrength;</l>
               <l>To each (remitting their unnat'rall quarrell)</l>
               <l>He bounteouſty gave changes of apparell;</l>
               <pb n="58" facs="tcp:57741:32"/>
               <l>To <hi>Benjamin,</hi> beſides five change of rayment,</l>
               <l>Three hundred ſilverlings in courteous payment;</l>
               <l>To <hi>Jacob</hi> thus, a choice <hi>Viaticum,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And to reward his Mirrhe, Spice, Balm, and Gumm,</l>
               <l>Ten Aſſes load of thoſe beſt things, in which</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Egypt</hi> is held moſt happy, and moſt rich,</l>
               <l>And ten ſhe Aſſes load of Corn; <hi>cloſe thriſt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Seems baſe, where princely duty walls a gift.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Their Aſſes ready, and their juſtling Waggons,</l>
               <l>Leſt that our <hi>Joſeph's</hi> (ſhould like <hi>Cadmus</hi> Dragons</l>
               <l>Fierce teeth-ſprung Brethren) when they fail'd in words,</l>
               <l>Diſpute the matter with their angry ſwords,</l>
               <l>While each one to acquit himſelf attempted,</l>
               <l>Who from that former rage was moſt exempted,</l>
               <l>At leaſt, they might expect to be ſurpriz'd,</l>
               <l>The lot of quarr'ling ſtrangers not advis'd,</l>
               <l>As a ſmall Fleet, who, in a forreign Sea,</l>
               <l>While each ſhip would maintain a private plea,</l>
               <l>And rudely mutiny amongſt themſelves,</l>
               <l>Is ſunk, ſurpriz'd, or daſht againſt ſome ſhelves;</l>
               <l>For fear of which events you may conjecture,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Ioſeph</hi> thus to his brethren reads this lecture;</l>
               <l>You may remember, but I wiſh that it</l>
               <l>You could ſo ſoon forget, as I remit,</l>
               <l>When you conſpired my deſtruction,</l>
               <l>As if your hearts were gravell'd into ſtone,</l>
               <l>Or rib'd with ſteel, congeal'd t'an Iron maſs,</l>
               <l>Yet though your Bowells thus were cramt with Braſs,</l>
               <l>Mine now are ſoft with pitty, may you find.</l>
               <l>As here of body, alway peace of mind;</l>
               <l>Confeſſion cancells all, and I accept</l>
               <l>Acknowledgement, as if you pai'd the debt;</l>
               <l>Your pardon is with many favours ſeal'd,</l>
               <l>Which time ſhall ne'r ſee cancel'd, age repeal'd;</l>
               <l>For which grant this one favour, 'tis but one,</l>
               <l>That you forget the wrong that you have done,</l>
               <l>I, in oblivion have lai'd it deep,</l>
               <l>Then dig't not up again, but let it ſleep;</l>
               <l>Both for your Fathers, mine, your ſafeties ſake,</l>
               <l>Drink, to it all a draught of <hi>Laethes</hi> Lake;</l>
               <pb n="59" facs="tcp:57741:32"/>
               <l>Take my example, 'twas I had the wrong,</l>
               <l>'Tis I that for your reconcilement long;</l>
               <l>Since I forgive it, in diſſentious ſort</l>
               <l>Do not one on another it retort?</l>
               <l>Diſſent not in the way, leſt that you teach</l>
               <l>Strangers to take advantage on the breach;</l>
               <l>Adviſe with Policie, if not with Love;</l>
               <l>Nay, with the Serpent, if not with the Dove;</l>
               <l>Serpents will not ſting Serpents, nor will cruſh</l>
               <l>The Cockatrices egg, then Brethren bluſh,</l>
               <l>That Reaſon's law to that of ſenſe ſubſcribes,</l>
               <l>Should Brethren quarr'll with Brethren, Tribes with Tribes?</l>
               <l>With ſuch advice as <hi>This,</hi> you may ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>Our carefull <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did his farewell cloſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Ev'n thus our Saviour yer his laſt he breath'd,</l>
               <l>Peace, his laſt <hi>Legacy,</hi> to <hi>his</hi> bequeath'd;</l>
               <l>Who, if he now ſhould come, would look to find</l>
               <l>Us, as he left us, of a peacefull mind;</l>
               <l>And if both Poles did now to ruine reel,</l>
               <l>Did th'world its pangs of diſſolution feel,</l>
               <l>Would <hi>he</hi> not find, adherents did increaſe</l>
               <l>More to the Prince of diſcord than of peace?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>While that old <hi>Iacob</hi> fervently did burn</l>
               <l>In expectation of his Son's return,</l>
               <l>Gheſſe them come home, who to their Father thus,</l>
               <l>The Sum of their proceedings did diſcuſs;</l>
               <l>Dear Sir, you cauſeleſly accus'd Fates knife</l>
               <l>To have bereft thy <hi>Ioſeph</hi> of his life;</l>
               <l>Unleſs that <hi>ſhe</hi> again have knit his cord,</l>
               <l>For <hi>hee</hi> yet liveth and's great <hi>Egypts</hi> Lord.</l>
               <l>My Sons, quoth he, my Meditation chewes,</l>
               <l>And dubiouſly doth ruminate your newes,</l>
               <l>O be adviſed, when my <hi>Ioſeph</hi> di'd</l>
               <l>My tears ſtow'd high, ev'n at their higheſt tide</l>
               <l>But if you mock my grief, I drown in tears,</l>
               <l>My heart of <hi>Ioſeph</hi> an impreſſion bears</l>
               <l>Too deep to be forgot, inhaunce not grief,</l>
               <l>Leſt you incur a Curſe, not win belief.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dear Sir, quoth they, what's by theſe Waggons meant</l>
               <l>There's twenty Aſſes load that he hath ſent</l>
               <pb n="60" facs="tcp:57741:33"/>
               <l>As dutious Pledges? thoſe our change of cloaths,</l>
               <l>But if theſe fail, believe us on our oaths.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>So now, quoth he, theſe evidences draw</l>
               <l>My Faith as ſtrong, as Vouchers do in Law;</l>
               <l>Speak thick till th'vapours of your breath condenſe</l>
               <l>Ev'n to the ſmoth'ring of my hearing ſenſe;</l>
               <l>I've ſurfeited with ſorrow, but this joy</l>
               <l>Is ſo tranſcendent, it can never cloy,</l>
               <l>My ſoul would hence, and leave her truth behind,</l>
               <l>How ſhe diſdaineth thus to be confind!</l>
               <l>My ſenſes ſeem too weak to hinder her,</l>
               <l>But ſhe would hence my winged harbinger;</l>
               <l>O for ſome Eagles pinions, or ſome Dragons</l>
               <l>With wide-ſtretcht wings to waft along our Waggons;</l>
               <l>Their motions are too dull, O would their wheeles</l>
               <l>Were ſwift as <hi>Titans,</hi> or the ſlippery Keeles</l>
               <l>Which with a Sphear-tike ſwiftneſs cut their way</l>
               <l>Through the wide Boſome of the yeſty Sea;</l>
               <l>I'll down and ſee my Son, and yeeld my breath</l>
               <l>In <hi>Joſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ph's</hi> boſome, and then welcome death.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Conceive him on his journey, with his train,</l>
               <l>When in the Viſions of the night, his brain</l>
               <l>Receiv'd the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> love</l>
               <l>Confirmed to an <hi>act</hi> from heav'n above;</l>
               <l>And ſeal'd with promiſes that God would bleſs</l>
               <l>This his removall with a good ſucceſs;</l>
               <l>And with aſſurance that he had decreed</l>
               <l>The ſafe returning of his num'rous ſeed,</l>
               <l>Gueſſe <hi>Judah</hi> likewiſe ſent for to direct</l>
               <l>His Fathers face to <hi>Goſhen,</hi> then reflect</l>
               <l>Your thoughts on <hi>Joſeph,</hi> who you now may gather</l>
               <l>In gallant equipage did meet his Father,</l>
               <l>Imagine with what triumph at the laſt</l>
               <l>Earth-rending ſound, and tomb-dividing blaſt,</l>
               <l>The widdow'd Soul will welcome the return</l>
               <l>Of her dear Body from the ſleepy urn;</l>
               <l>With ſuch like joy, your fancy may admit,</l>
               <l>Were <hi>Joſeph</hi> and his Father ſweetly knit</l>
               <l>In twin'd embraces, as if they each other</l>
               <l>Would cramp in chained arms, or meant to ſmother</l>
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:57741:33"/>
               <l>Each other in their kiſſes; haſt thou ever,</l>
               <l>Beheld a Gardner while he did diſcover</l>
               <l>Two ſprigs aſunder, then to joyn by craft</l>
               <l>Two divers parts in one entired graft;</l>
               <l>Ev'n thus was <hi>Jacob</hi> twined with his Son,</l>
               <l>As if they meant to grow again in one;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Iacob</hi> could onely with glad tears diſpute;</l>
               <l>For as great ſorrow's dumb, great joy is mute;</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo did <hi>Joſeph,</hi> at his Brethrens ſight</l>
               <l>His eyes but drizled, now they rain'd down-right;</l>
               <l>For tears are badges both of joy and ſorrow,</l>
               <l>Both Paſſions do alike the viſage furrow;</l>
               <l>Dear God, quoth <hi>I acob,</hi> then in num'rous chace</l>
               <l>Tears purſue tears upon his reeking face</l>
               <l>Bleſt heav'n that alwayes thus doſt me reſtore,</l>
               <l>Unleſs 'twere heav'n I could wiſh no more;</l>
               <l>Sweet Son, I know theſe eyes, this roſie cheek,</l>
               <l>That thus in dutious tears doth ſweetly reek,</l>
               <l>Since yet thou liv'ſt, Fate finiſh out my glome,</l>
               <l>And let my Soul on wings of joy fly home,</l>
               <l>But yet, my darling Son, great heav'n forgive,</l>
               <l>If I for thee do yet deſire to live;</l>
               <l>My tears ſhall tell the reſt, my lungs are weak,</l>
               <l>If not, I know not what I more ſhall ſpeak.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sir, quoth his Son (then tears in a full ſtream</l>
               <l>Choakt the proceedings of his dutious theam)</l>
               <l>Dear Sir, my ſwelling Breſt will burſt a ſunder,</l>
               <l>Like wind-ſwoll'n Clouds rent by the heavens thunder,</l>
               <l>My mouth a veſſell of a narrow bore,</l>
               <l>That muſt by ſlow degrees vent forth its ſtore,</l>
               <l>Though pay I cannot what your love deſerves,</l>
               <l>Yet to requite I'll ſtretch my utmoſt nerves,</l>
               <l>Since Seas repay, through crannies of the earth,</l>
               <l>Streams to the Springs from whence they had their birth,</l>
               <l>Then why ſhould Chilkren if advanc'd by Fate,</l>
               <l>Neglect their Parens in a meaner ſtate?</l>
               <l>But yet I boaſt not, that my power is ſuch,</l>
               <l>But joy, I'ave means t'expreſs my love ſo much;</l>
               <l>Though heav'n have freed me from the ſlaviſh yoak</l>
               <l>Of heavy bondage, that he hath not broke</l>
               <pb n="62" facs="tcp:57741:34"/>
               <l>Of filiall duty, <hi>this</hi> that thus doth deck</l>
               <l>With gawdy Ornament my gorgeous neck,</l>
               <l>I count leſs honour, than that dutious bond</l>
               <l>In which I ſerve thee; do not then deſpond;</l>
               <l>I Father am to <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> but will be</l>
               <l>A true, obſervant, dutious Son to thee;</l>
               <l>No bleer-ey'd ſorc'rers, nor <hi>Egyptian Weirds</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Shall hurt your perſons, wrong your Flocks or Herds,</l>
               <l>Thy crown of ſilver hairs I'll ever hold</l>
               <l>In greater honour, than his Crown of gold;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Honours null not relation,</hi> th'Oceans flood</l>
               <l>Alters not <hi>Nilus,</hi> nor can honour, blood,</l>
               <l>It tickles oft the temper with conceits,</l>
               <l>But as for me, honour on duty waits;</l>
               <l>I'<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>l goe before, and as your true Attorney</l>
               <l>Poſſeſs the King of your intents and journey;</l>
               <l>My Father, and his houſhold, flocks and droves,</l>
               <l>Have late left <hi>Paleſtinu's</hi> Sun-parcht groves,</l>
               <l>And down are come, whoſe cognizance of old,</l>
               <l>Both was, and is, a ſheephook and a fold,</l>
               <l>Which ſhould his Grace demand, ſpeak, I beſeech,</l>
               <l>According to the tenour of my ſpeech,</l>
               <l>And ſince th' <hi>Egyptians</hi> ever entertain</l>
               <l>A Shepheard, both with fury and diſdain,</l>
               <l>You may in <hi>Goſhen</hi> ſafely live, and trade,</l>
               <l>Where for your Flocks are Paſtures, Wells and Shade.</l>
               <l>And thus you may, if thus you wiſely deal,</l>
               <l>Inſtate your ſelves in <hi>Egypts</hi> Common-weal.</l>
               <l>When Love with Policy had thus conſpir'd,</l>
               <l>Imagine <hi>Ioſeph</hi> to his charge retir'd,</l>
               <l>Where he without a dilatory pauſe,</l>
               <l>Thus to his Sovereign, pleads his Fathers Cauſe;</l>
               <l>Dread Sir, what am I? a dead dogg, or flea?</l>
               <l>That thou ſhouldſt grant my ſute, or hear my plea?</l>
               <l>Who firſt thy favours didſt to me impart,</l>
               <l>And then lookſt on me worthy of deſert,</l>
               <l>To all which wouldſt thou adde this one requeſt,</l>
               <l>I'd count it greater far than all the reſt;</l>
               <l>My Father, and my Brethren late are come,</l>
               <l>And have left <hi>Canaan</hi> their native home,</l>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:57741:34"/>
               <l>Their ſtomachs bark for food, their bodies lean,</l>
               <l>Their looks are meager, and their teeth are clean,</l>
               <l>And Dearth more fierce than either Wolf or Fox,</l>
               <l>Hath from the Paſtures ſcarr'd their Heards and Flocks,</l>
               <l>Which with them they have brought, and all to prove</l>
               <l>The promis'd bounty of his princely love,</l>
               <l>That while Dearth falls unto her loweſteb,</l>
               <l>Their threads of life may to a peacefull web</l>
               <l>Of ſafety here be ſpun, whoſe hearts do pant</l>
               <l>In expectation of thy Princely grant.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>This ended, quoth the King, My darling Prince,</l>
               <l>I rather will inlarge, than baſely mince</l>
               <l>My promiſe to evaſions, I applaud</l>
               <l>Thy filiall love, nor power ſhall, nor fraud,</l>
               <l>Oppoſe, or circumvent you, no, my gem,</l>
               <l>I love the Branch, nor will neglect the ſtem;</l>
               <l>Since I ſent for him, he and his affairs</l>
               <l>Held room in equall with my choiceſt ears.</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Joſeph</hi> triumphing at theſe bleſt events,</l>
               <l>Five of his Brethren to his Grace preſents,</l>
               <l>To whom, quoth <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> by what labours ſweat</l>
               <l>Have you your ſuſtenance, are cloath'd, and eat?</l>
               <l>Do you the Sullow hold, or tug the Oars?</l>
               <l>What trade expells your vigour through your poars?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dread Sir, quoth they, we are but ſimple worms,</l>
               <l>Or ſuch like creatures of deſpiſed forms;</l>
               <l>Yet not to grate thy ears with vain digreſſion,</l>
               <l>Ours, and our Fathers trade, is by ſucceſſion</l>
               <l>To feed our Flocks, and ſo by carefull thrift</l>
               <l>Our providence enlargeth heavens gift;</l>
               <l>We feed them, they feed us, and leſt we freeze</l>
               <l>In Winter time, they cloath us with their fleece;</l>
               <l>When <hi>Phoebus</hi> firſt diſplayes his golden locks,</l>
               <l>We ſend abroad our Heards, diſmiſs our flocks,</l>
               <l>And while he chears the world, with carefull hook</l>
               <l>We them protect, defend, and overlook;</l>
               <l>And when the Sun again withdrawes his gold</l>
               <l>From th'Weſtern hills, we pin them in our fold;</l>
               <l>We are by famine from our homes divorc'd</l>
               <l>No idle vagrants, but are ſadly forc'd;</l>
               <pb n="64" facs="tcp:57741:35" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <l>We <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> in vain for Springs, our Wells are ſunk</l>
               <l>Down to the Center, and our Earth is ſhrunk</l>
               <l>And bak'd to ſtony clods, whoſe chaps in vain</l>
               <l>Gape for the ſhowers of refreſhing rain;</l>
               <l>Now we intreat thee in this time of Dearth,</l>
               <l>That art the onely Father of the earth,</l>
               <l>Let us in <hi>Goſhen</hi> live, where both are Rocks</l>
               <l>Fi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for our Goats, and Paſture for our flocks;</l>
               <l>We'll in the Land not plant our ſelves, nor build,</l>
               <l>But ſojourn in our Tents as ſtrangers ſhould,</l>
               <l>We'll all b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uled by thy Country lawes,</l>
               <l>And with our labours feed our hungry maws;</l>
               <l>At <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>his, quoth <hi>Pharoah,</hi> Sirs, do not deſpond,</l>
               <l>To ſuch it were no weakneſs to be fond;</l>
               <l>Your Brother makes you nigh as if each vein</l>
               <l>Swell'd with <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>igh blood, and of a nobler grain;</l>
               <l>Nature none equalls unto me in blood,</l>
               <l>Who ſhall partake more freely of our food,</l>
               <l>Then ſhall your Father, and your ſelves, I grant</l>
               <l>You may in <hi>Egypt</hi> freely build and plant;</l>
               <l>This ſaid, thus unto <hi>Joſeph</hi> he inſiſts,</l>
               <l>Dear <hi>Joſeph,</hi> I, my Peers, and princely Prieſts,</l>
               <l>Thy Fathers comming do congratulate,</l>
               <l>And likewiſe with thee, all condole his Fate,</l>
               <l>Yet though the Sun ſhoot forth his ſcorching beams,</l>
               <l>The air diſtill groſs dewes, and rotten ſtreams,</l>
               <l>Our Fields forbear to ſpring, our Trees to bud,</l>
               <l>And <hi>Nile</hi> deſiſt to yeeld his fruitfull mud;</l>
               <l>As if the Skies, had with the earth combind,</l>
               <l>To act the ruine of all humane kind;</l>
               <l>My <hi>Genius</hi> tell me, and I more than hope</l>
               <l>Thy Fathers, and each Brother <hi>Horoſcope,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>With kinder aſpect, happier things foretold,</l>
               <l>And that 'tis in Fates Notaries inroll'd,</l>
               <l>That <hi>Egypt</hi> is deſign'd (without diſpute)</l>
               <l>Their ſafe <hi>Aſyle,</hi> from Famines fierce purſute:</l>
               <l>All <hi>Egypt</hi> is before thee, if our Land</l>
               <l>Have any part untouch'd by Famines band</l>
               <l>Of ſcourging plagues, as <hi>Goſhen</hi> moſt is known,</l>
               <l>Let them poſſeſs that Country as their own,</l>
               <pb n="65" facs="tcp:57741:35"/>
               <l>They ſhall not be as Meteors for a time</l>
               <l>Exhal'd, but as fix'd Stars in <hi>Egypts</hi> clime:</l>
               <l>And if thou knowſt one fit to feed my Herd,</l>
               <l>Let him unto that Office be prefer'd.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, old <hi>Jacob</hi> by his carefull Sonne</l>
               <l>Was brought, and placed neer to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Throne;</l>
               <l>Where, having breathed on the King, and Peers,</l>
               <l>A bleſſing both of Peace, and many years,</l>
               <l>Grave, Sir, quoth <hi>Pharoah,</hi> we our thanks retort,</l>
               <l>And welcome thy deſcent unto our Court;</l>
               <l>Thy dutious Son was for his Father zealous,</l>
               <l>I and my <hi>Peers,</hi> were of thy ſafety jealous,</l>
               <l>Leſt Famine having draind our Fields, and Cells,</l>
               <l>Should leave you, like ſo many barks and ſhells,</l>
               <l>Sans coar, or kernell, ceaſe thou to requeſt,</l>
               <l>Live boldly on thy <hi>Joſeph's</hi> Intereſt.</l>
               <l>Who ſees the Sun, but reaſon wills for ſhame</l>
               <l>To praiſe the Author of that glorious flame?</l>
               <l>And who ſurvives his neighbour in thoſe dayes</l>
               <l>Who for the Son will not the Father praiſe?</l>
               <l>Thou haſt a Son whom all the world muſt prize,</l>
               <l>Leſs worth hath been ador'd with Sacrifice;</l>
               <l>An Angell ſent from heav'n, could not have done</l>
               <l>More than preſerv'd us all, ſo hath thy Son;</l>
               <l>'T was he, that when all Charmers were nonpluſt,</l>
               <l>Inchanters all were dumb, my Dreams diſcuſt,</l>
               <l>All Sorcery as huſht, now with their Spells</l>
               <l>Let them recruit their Garners, and their Cells;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Astrologie's</hi> undone, now let them dine</l>
               <l>On joynts of <hi>Taurus,</hi> or ſome empty ſigne;</l>
               <l>I'll make no nice enquiries, I have had</l>
               <l>A full rehearſall of thy life and trade.</l>
               <l>Thus thou wouldſt ſpeak, but I anticipate</l>
               <l>Thy ſad complainings, which would thus debate;</l>
               <l>That as <hi>Deucalions</hi> flood drown'd all the Earth,</l>
               <l>Some fear leſt it diſpeopled be by dearth;</l>
               <l>That your Earths chaps yawn like ſo many graves</l>
               <l>To ſwallow you, unleſs that plenty ſaves,</l>
               <l>That Famine's grown a Monſter of huge ſtature,</l>
               <l>Which not with few content, exacts on Nature;</l>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:57741:36"/>
               <l>Since plenty, as if Bankrupt of her ſtore,</l>
               <l>Keeps private houſe in <hi>Egypt,</hi> you implore</l>
               <l>Thy <hi>Joſeph</hi> being her Steward, ſhe would daign</l>
               <l>T'accept thee, and thy ſons, amongſt her train;</l>
               <l>I'll not impoſe upon thy lungs a task</l>
               <l>Of large, long-winded anſwers, but this ask</l>
               <l>Since Nature in thee fails, thy eyes decline,</l>
               <l>And in thy two-leav'd Spheres withdrawes their ſhine;</l>
               <l>And each decaying part doth ſeem to crave</l>
               <l>With bended ham of ev'ry land a grave;</l>
               <l>How long was't ſince thy Souls inſpired flame</l>
               <l>Poſſeſſion took of this declining frame?</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Dread Sir, quoth <hi>Jacob,</hi> rudeneſs, are, and age</l>
               <l>Unfit to act upon a Kingly ſtage,</l>
               <l>A hundred, and full thirty years I've ſeen,</l>
               <l>Both few, and evill, all my dayes have been;</l>
               <l>Nor have I yet attained to the age</l>
               <l>Of my fore-Fathers in their Pilgrimage;</l>
               <l>Though I am antient, I may truly ſay</l>
               <l>Sorrow, as well as age, hath made me gray,</l>
               <l>'Tis grief poſtdates my time, which 'twere but vain</l>
               <l>To think that joy can antidate again:</l>
               <l>An ounce of grief emacerates the fleſh</l>
               <l>More than a pound of joy can it refreſh,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Sol</hi> ſooner may regrade his morning track,</l>
               <l>Than joy can change this gray to youthfull black;</l>
               <l>If I've a Son, whom all, of all degrees,</l>
               <l>From thoſe that fry, ev'n unto thoſe that freeze,</l>
               <l>Under their Zones, are bound to praiſe, and love,</l>
               <l>Impute it not as his, but Gods above;</l>
               <l>Let not the Husbandman give to the clod</l>
               <l>That glory, which is onely due to God;</l>
               <l>Yet if his merit be ſo much, and more</l>
               <l>Than he can be made Bankrupt of, w'implore</l>
               <l>That you would lay it, (if our charge ſurmount</l>
               <l>Your expectation) on my Sons account.</l>
               <l>This ſaid, again on them he bleſſings breath'd,</l>
               <l>And them, departing, to his God bequeath'd;</l>
               <l>And glad he brought his wiſhes to this cloſe</l>
               <l>Reſigns himſelf as <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſhould diſpoſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <pb n="67" facs="tcp:57741:36"/>
               <l>Gheſs him in <hi>Goſhen</hi> next, where he immerds</l>
               <l>The fruitfull Paſtures, with his Flocks and Heards;</l>
               <l>I'th' Land of <hi>Ramiſſes</hi> he liv'd, a ſoyl</l>
               <l>Which Famine could not of its vigour ſpoyl;</l>
               <l>And though it laught not, now, with kinds of grains,</l>
               <l>It ſmil'd with Paſtures to delight our Swains.</l>
               <l>To him by <hi>Joſeph</hi> all reſpect was ſhown;</l>
               <l>No Manumiſſive <hi>Corbon</hi> yet was known</l>
               <l>To <hi>Superſedeas</hi> a Son, for he</l>
               <l>Still gave, yet ne'r eſteem'd himſelf as free;</l>
               <l>No, though he cheriſh'd had his age, as long</l>
               <l>As <hi>He</hi> by him was nouriſh'd being young;</l>
               <l>For filiall dutie's Gods command, no <hi>Bull</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Can it repeal, no Vote can change, or null,</l>
               <l>No wit, or art reverſe it, no mans joint</l>
               <l>Carv'd it, 'twas ſculptur'd by <hi>his</hi> fingers point</l>
               <l>That publiſh'd it by thunder, and <hi>His</hi> bolt</l>
               <l>Or worſe, ſhall vengeance take on their revolt</l>
               <l>That dare oppoſe it, for they who explode</l>
               <l>Duty to Parents, next will theirs to God.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Old <hi>Jacobs</hi> Cells were ſtor'd with Wine, and Corn,</l>
               <l>As full and free, as was that plenteous Horn</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Jove</hi> gave his Nurſe, ev'n ſuch was <hi>Joſeph's</hi> love</l>
               <l>Unto his Father, great as that of <hi>Iove;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor time, nor charge could dull it, even ſo</l>
               <l>Wells if you draw them, will the freer flow.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Nor was our <hi>Joſeph's</hi> duty onely ſuch,</l>
               <l>But to his Brethren was his love as much;</l>
               <l>Though for their former rage he once ſeem'd ſtrange,</l>
               <l>Yet now they found in him a bounteous change,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>As pardon is the daughter of Contrition,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>So love's the common iſſue of remiſſion;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>He, who was like the Sun, that could diſpenſe</l>
               <l>Upon the mean'ſt his bounteous influence,</l>
               <l>Could not neglect the <hi>Starres,</hi> could not deny</l>
               <l>Unto his Brethrens want his gracious eye;</l>
               <l>Not like to ſome, whoſe proud advanced height,</l>
               <l>Looks on all other men as out of ſight,</l>
               <l>As fixt in higher Sphears, out of the view,</l>
               <l>And the <hi>Horizon</hi> of the common crew,</l>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:57741:37"/>
               <l>As if conceit of honour with th'affection,</l>
               <l>Had likewiſe chang'd the temper and complexion;</l>
               <l>But <hi>Joſeph</hi> thought it honour to deſcend</l>
               <l>His Brethrens Father, and his Fathers friend.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now more and more the Dearth began to rage,</l>
               <l>Advancing on in horrid equipage;</l>
               <l>New maladies outbrav'd the <hi>Phyſicks</hi> skill,</l>
               <l>And deſp'rate murther acted now its will,</l>
               <l>Faintneſs had ſome confined to their Beds,</l>
               <l>As if Dearth meant to ravell out their threds,</l>
               <l>Or if ſhe ſcorn'd the common way, by knife,</l>
               <l>And meant t'untwind their fatall glomes of life;</l>
               <l>The Barns were empty, where was nought, unleſs</l>
               <l>The mournfull Owle, to wail their emptineſs;</l>
               <l>The gawdy gallants ſpirit now grew dull,</l>
               <l>And wiſh'd a Garner for his Wardrobe full;</l>
               <l>His <hi>Robes</hi> no better than the Beggers <hi>raggs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>The poor mans <hi>Scrip</hi> good as the rich mans <hi>baggs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Though Gold be cordiall, it but to the ſight,</l>
               <l>But a ſad meale to hungry appetite;</l>
               <l>The clown that thought that metall was divine,</l>
               <l>Had rather find a <hi>Garner</hi> than a <hi>Mine;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Were <hi>Nole</hi> a <hi>Tagus,</hi> and each fand i'th' ſtream,</l>
               <l>Such ſtones whereof <hi>Philoſophie</hi> doth dream;</l>
               <l>Yet <hi>Midas</hi> now, would gladly change his wiſh</l>
               <l>For roots, or Acorns, or ſo mean diſh;</l>
               <l>The Harveſts paſs, the Clown no longer reaps,</l>
               <l>But now his Husbandry lay all in heaps;</l>
               <l>O'r-grown with Burrs, rough Thiſtles, Docks, and Sedges,</l>
               <l>The Culter ruſted, and the fruitfull Hedges</l>
               <l>Now with diſorder'd boughes grew perewigg'd,</l>
               <l>None plow'd, prun'd, planted, ſow'd, manur'd, or digg'd;</l>
               <l>Dearth ſo purvei'd for Death, now were the rodes</l>
               <l>Wherein they juſtled with their plenteous loads,</l>
               <l>So much o'r-grown, through ſcarcitie of men,</l>
               <l>Each fearfull Beaſt there boldly made his den;</l>
               <l>Each houſe as empty ſtood, the owner's dead,</l>
               <l>As were their Bodies, now their Souls were fled;</l>
               <l>Each look ſo meager, none could know, almoſt.</l>
               <l>Where 'twere the man that walk'd, or elſe his Ghoſt,</l>
               <pb n="69" facs="tcp:57741:37"/>
               <l>Who, now with weakneſs, bow'd their feeble hams</l>
               <l>Like late-earnd Lambkins, yer they ſuck'd their dams;</l>
               <l>The Oxe i'th' Commons motionleſs did lie,</l>
               <l>The Gum down-roping from his pale dead eye,</l>
               <l>The Cow lob'd down her head, the raw-bon'd Aſs</l>
               <l>His mouth was foul with half-chew'd roots of graſs,</l>
               <l>Each Beaſt half ſtarv'd, drooping the ſide, and hip,</l>
               <l>Not moving for the Scourge, goad, ſpur, or whip;</l>
               <l>Unto the Cities there was no reſort</l>
               <l>Except of Crows, who tore in knaviſh ſport</l>
               <l>Their dead, and ſtill, impatient of delay,</l>
               <l>Rookt on the houſe tops, waiting for their prey;</l>
               <l>Their ſtreets o'rgrown with rubbiſh, ſeem'd t'expreſs</l>
               <l>Unto the eye a civill wilderneſs;</l>
               <l>So pining Dearth had ſhriv'led each ones skin,</l>
               <l>With looks diſtorted they did ſtrangely grin,</l>
               <l>Which when they view'd in glaſſes, and in brooks,</l>
               <l>Amazedly they ſtartled at their looks;</l>
               <l>In fine, a task that lames both tongue, and pen,</l>
               <l>All nothing, but the ſhales, or husks of men;</l>
               <l>This while, had <hi>Egypt</hi> for all kind of grains</l>
               <l>Exchang'd their Coin, their Jewels, and their Chains,</l>
               <l>All which our loyall <hi>Joſeph</hi> never wreſts</l>
               <l>To his own uſe, but adds to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> Cheſts,</l>
               <l>This ſtore exhauſted, you may gheſs for bread,</l>
               <l>Thus the <hi>Egyptians</hi> to <hi>Joſeph</hi> plead;</l>
               <l>Dread Sir, great <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> darling, <hi>Egypts</hi> Saint,</l>
               <l>Vouchſafe a patient ear to our complaint;</l>
               <l>We have for Corn exchang'd our coin and gold,</l>
               <l>And yet Dearth rageth as your Grace foretold;</l>
               <l>Our Barns are empty, not through our default,</l>
               <l>Nor hath an en'my ſow'd our Fields with Salt;</l>
               <l>None enviouſly have choakt our Fields with ſtones;</l>
               <l>None of theſe things are authors of our mones;</l>
               <l>Great <hi>Nile's</hi> offended, and no wonted ſhout</l>
               <l>Awakes the <hi>Echo,</hi> ſince no flood ran out</l>
               <l>Through his fat banks, cut by our num'rous troops,</l>
               <l>No, <hi>Nile</hi> within his ſhallow chanell ſtoops;</l>
               <l>Our Money faileth, and who will not hold</l>
               <l>A grain of Corn well worth an ounce of gold?</l>
               <pb n="70" facs="tcp:57741:38"/>
               <l>Our hopes are faild, and when the main-ſpring Hope</l>
               <l>Is out of tune, the leſſer wheels will ſtop</l>
               <l>Of joy and pleaſure; yet we'll not deſiſt,</l>
               <l>Since in thee bounty hath with goodneſs kiſt.</l>
               <l>Think on thy honour, let it not be ſaid</l>
               <l>That we now periſh, whom you firſt didſt aid;</l>
               <l>Redeem us from the jawes of Death, which boon</l>
               <l>Will make thy fame ſhine bright as <hi>Titans</hi> noon.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sirs, quoth the Lord, my troubled heart doth languiſh</l>
               <l>In true imagination of your anguiſh;</l>
               <l>Yet though I you condole, I hope each knowes</l>
               <l>That I diſpenſe as <hi>Pharaoh</hi> doth diſpoſe;</l>
               <l>Yet will he grant (ſuch is his mild remorſe)</l>
               <l>Corn in exchange for Heards, and teams of Horſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Glad was all <hi>Egypt,</hi> nor at all deferr'd</l>
               <l>T'accept his love, each brings his team and heard;</l>
               <l>On which exchange they liv'd this year, yet pind</l>
               <l>In ſad conceit of two years yet behind,</l>
               <l>More then with food refreſh'd; ſo ranging Deers</l>
               <l>Fear more emacerates, than plenty cheers.</l>
               <l>The year being ended, which as in a ring</l>
               <l>It ſelf within it ſelf again doth bring,</l>
               <l>Sad <hi>Egypt</hi> having all their cattle ſpent,</l>
               <l>Which Induſtry had got, or Fortune lent,</l>
               <l>Gheſs them in a full preſs, with bended ham,</l>
               <l>And proſtrate faces, unto <hi>Ioſeph</hi> came;</l>
               <l>Great Sir, quoth they, now this is the third time</l>
               <l>We have appeald to thee, and yet no prime.</l>
               <l>Is <hi>Nile</hi> after ſo many years effluxions,</l>
               <l>Th'earth weary grown after ſo oft productions?</l>
               <l>And ſo expects like an exhauſted ſoil</l>
               <l>A reſt and reſpite from the wonted toil;</l>
               <l>Our Share tuſts, and our tools that digg'd the earth</l>
               <l>Hang like ſome <hi>Trophies</hi> dedicate to dearth;</l>
               <l>Each body here's her <hi>Obelisk,</hi> that bears</l>
               <l>Her triumph Grav'd in meager Characters;</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> firſt, our Cauſe to thee refer'd;</l>
               <l>There's none but hath exchang'd his Teem and Herd,</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Wee not a Beaſt detain, there's none, great Prince,</l>
               <l>That can thy ſervants of ſuch fraud convince,</l>
               <pb n="71" facs="tcp:57741:38"/>
               <l>Now if our perſons may, and each ones land</l>
               <l>Ioyn'd with thy love, in equall ballance ſtand</l>
               <l>With one years diet more, we have to boaſt,</l>
               <l>Nor will as yet eſteem our ſelves as loſt;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſhall a double title have</l>
               <l>In each one, of ſubject, and a ſlave;</l>
               <l>View but theſe looks well, thou wilt not demur,</l>
               <l>Nor will thy pity need another ſpur,</l>
               <l>Thou art our noſtrills breath, why ſhould we dy,</l>
               <l>The breath of all our noſtrills being by?</l>
               <l>And ſince now's the laſt year, by fate decreed</l>
               <l>That Dearth ſhall rage, we further beg ſome ſeed</l>
               <l>To ſow the land, that it may be reduc'd,</l>
               <l>Which in its ancient <hi>Chaos</hi> lies confus'd.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Sirs, quoth our Lord, my heart with you condoles</l>
               <l>The bitter anguiſh of your troubled Souls,</l>
               <l>Yet 'twere a ſin in me beyond excuſe,</l>
               <l>Should I not all diſpence to <hi>Pharaohs</hi> uſe,</l>
               <l>Yet as I pittie what you have diſclos'd,</l>
               <l>So will I grant you what you have propos'd;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gheſs <hi>Ioſeph</hi> now for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> wiſely changes</l>
               <l>Bread for their Fields, their Mannors and their Granges,</l>
               <l>And with the Citizens for <hi>Pharaoh</hi> Barters,</l>
               <l>For Corn, their Houſes, Liberties, and Charters,</l>
               <l>And that their lands and rights might all be known</l>
               <l>By ſome clear evidence as <hi>Pharaohs</hi> own,</l>
               <l>Th'<hi>Egyptians</hi> were to Cities far remov'd;</l>
               <l>To the lands end, ſo <hi>Pharaohs</hi> right was prov'd,</l>
               <l>Yet the Prieſts lands, and <hi>I ſis</hi> Princely <hi>Flamines,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Became not <hi>Pharaohs</hi> nor the greedy Famins;</l>
               <l>As if 'twere Sacrilegious extortion,</l>
               <l>Ev'n in this Panic ſale to buy <hi>their</hi> portion;</l>
               <l>Nor were they famiſhed, for <hi>Pharaohs</hi> ſtores</l>
               <l>They made as bold with, as their threſhing floors;</l>
               <l>And which, thoſe Prieſts who, then, ſerv'd <hi>I ſis</hi> Cow,</l>
               <l>Or they that ſerve the Lamb of heaven, now,</l>
               <l>Are worth moſt honours? reader, fear, and pray,</l>
               <l>Leſt <hi>Pagans</hi> judge us at the latter day.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Gheſs <hi>Egypt</hi> now, were in a full convention</l>
               <l>By <hi>Joſeph</hi> ſummond then to ſoft attention,</l>
               <pb n="72" facs="tcp:57741:39"/>
               <l>To whom, quoth he, Sirs there is none but knowes,</l>
               <l>And will acknowledge ſtill, with thankfull vowes,</l>
               <l>That y'are preſerved, not by common Power,</l>
               <l>Since <hi>Fate,</hi> and <hi>Fortune</hi> on you all did lower,</l>
               <l>If <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> bounty did not intervene,</l>
               <l>Your Play were marr'd now in the latter Scene;</l>
               <l>And you, like long-toſs'd Veſſells, ſhould fall ſhort,</l>
               <l>And drown within the kenning of the Port;</l>
               <l>Now ſo will <hi>Pharaoh</hi> as you do importune,</l>
               <l>In true commiſeration of your fortune,</l>
               <l>Not out of Avariee for to ſupplant,</l>
               <l>But out of pitty to ſupply your want;</l>
               <l>Be't then in <hi>Egypts</hi> Notaries inroll'd,</l>
               <l>That y'have your lands, and ſelves to <hi>Pharaoh</hi> ſold,</l>
               <l>Lo, here is ſeed, go, ſow the land in peace,</l>
               <l>Which with its former vigour ſhall increaſe;</l>
               <l>Whereof a fifth part you ſhall grant the King,</l>
               <l>You now being ſafe under his Graces wing,</l>
               <l>You for your houſhold ſhall the reſt reſerve,</l>
               <l>To nouriſh them, <hi>Bread's natures chiefeſt nerve.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>This he Enacted, and a Statute ſeal'd,</l>
               <l>Which to this day's not cancell'd, nor repeal'd;</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>At this quoth <hi>Egypt,</hi> moſt renowned Prince,</l>
               <l>Whoſe trueſt <hi>Hieroglyphick</hi> were a <hi>Lynce,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>For as with <hi>him</hi> compar'd, each creature's blind,</l>
               <l>Each ſpirits dark to thy inlightned mind;</l>
               <l>Nature (the worlds great Soul) muſt needs confeſs</l>
               <l>Thee alone her preſerver, th'world muſt bleſs</l>
               <l>Thee the ſole cauſe, thy pitty and remorſe,</l>
               <l>That Dearth on both, now acts not a divorce;</l>
               <l>To thee we owe, we here converſe with men,</l>
               <l>And not with Ghoſts, in deaths unſavoury den;</l>
               <l>Thee, that our Wives by her impartiall Bawd</l>
               <l>Not raviſh'd are for death; we praiſe, we laud,</l>
               <l>Thee, that our children, like ſo many elves</l>
               <l>Shrink not to nought, but yet look like themſelves,</l>
               <l>Admit us ſafe, under thy Graces wing,</l>
               <l>Renowned Prince, ſo will we ſerve the King.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Grant now that debt that <hi>Adam</hi> did ingage</l>
               <l>All men in, Death hath claim'd of <hi>Jacobs</hi> age;</l>
               <pb n="73" facs="tcp:57741:39"/>
               <l>Who ſwearing <hi>Joſeph</hi> to tranſport his bones</l>
               <l>Hath breath'd his laſt in bleſſings on his Sons;</l>
               <l>Grant <hi>Ioſeph</hi> next, by generall ſuffrage</l>
               <l>Attended on in mourning equipage,</l>
               <l>His Fathers corps (to <hi>Canaan</hi> brought) interr'd</l>
               <l>In <hi>Machpelah,</hi> ſo of his oath was cleer'd.</l>
               <l>When <hi>Iacob</hi> thus had deaths arreſt obeyd,</l>
               <l>Conſcience within the Brethren 'gan t'upbraid</l>
               <l>Their old offence anew, thus guilt would plead;</l>
               <l>Their Brothers hate but ſlept, though it ſeem'd dead,</l>
               <l>Occaſion now might wake it, th'end might prove,</l>
               <l>That with their Father, di'd their Brothers love;</l>
               <l>That wounds are dang'rous when they inward bleed,</l>
               <l>And if their Brother all this while ſhould feed</l>
               <l>Upon revenge, ſince full rage now had vent,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>It's poys'nous rancour ſhould on them be ſpent.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>
                  <hi>Fear by guilt raiſed ſeldome is remiſs,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till in concluſion hope and pardon kiſs;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor were our Brethren negligent, but ſtrove</l>
               <l>To gain firm int'reſt in their Brothers love;</l>
               <l>Yet ſo conceit had of their weak demerits</l>
               <l>Diſſolv'd their courage, and outbrav'd their ſpirits,</l>
               <l>That they came not, but ſent, nor durſt they frame</l>
               <l>The meſſage in theirs, but their Fathers name,</l>
               <l>Know'ng if their ſute in <hi>Iacobs</hi> name were coucht,</l>
               <l>'T would like a Charm, not ceaſe till it had touch'd</l>
               <l>Their Brothers midriffs with remorſe, 'twould wreſt</l>
               <l>A ſoft remiſſion from his melting Breſt;</l>
               <l>Great Sir (this was the burthen of their ſute,</l>
               <l>And thus they humbly taught to proſtitute)</l>
               <l>Thus ſaid our Father, yer in <hi>Ephrons</hi> Urn</l>
               <l>He pawn'd his body for his Souls return,</l>
               <l>Thus in my name you ſhall to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſpeak,</l>
               <l>Remember not thy Brethrens ſin, nor wreak</l>
               <l>Thy juſt revenge upon their hate, which ſin,</l>
               <l>Than all their ſinns in groſs hath greater been;</l>
               <l>Remit what God hath pardond, and in this</l>
               <l>On their ſoft Souls thy pardon ſeal with <hi>His;</hi>
               </l>
               <pb n="74" facs="tcp:57741:40"/>
               <l>Thus did our Father bid, whoſe Soul above</l>
               <l>Hovers with bleſſings yet to crown thy love;</l>
               <l>Now this offence remit we thee intreat,</l>
               <l>Whoſe hearts with true devotion truly beat</l>
               <l>Of <hi>Jacobs</hi> God, t'whom from our hearts ariſe</l>
               <l>Zealous affection in Sacrifice.</l>
               <l>For Gods, for <hi>Iacobs</hi> ſake, our fault remit,</l>
               <l>Though we for neither would at all acquit</l>
               <l>Thy innocence, and if it yet appears</l>
               <l>Thy rage doth flame, we'll quench it with our tears.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Mild <hi>Joſeph</hi> pittying their anxious fears</l>
               <l>Could not but ſecond grief again with tears,</l>
               <l>Now griev'd he they ſuſpected him, and wept</l>
               <l>Then joy'd their conſcience not ſecurely ſlept.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now, as one having foil'd a fell diſeaſe</l>
               <l>Wherein he long hath labour'd, doth not ceaſe</l>
               <l>Untill that <hi>Phyſick</hi> ſhall the reliques purge,</l>
               <l>Which after might in wonted <hi>Symptoms</hi> urge,</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo the Brethren though they now might judge</l>
               <l>Their Brother reconcil'd, and that no grudge</l>
               <l>Did ſwell his peacefull Breſt, but that with tears,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>He entertained had their anxious fears;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Yet Conſcience never leaves her nice inqueſts,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Till in the Boſome ſhee of pardon reſts.</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor were the Ten remiſs till they found out</l>
               <l>By true experience they had nought to doubt;</l>
               <l>Wherefore all in a perſonall ſubmiſſion</l>
               <l>Thus beg their Pardon, and thus couch contrition;</l>
               <l>Neither preſum'd they on an equall greet,</l>
               <l>But thus fell proſtrate at their Brothers feet.</l>
               <l>Dread Sir, in <hi>Jacobs</hi> name, and for his ſake,</l>
               <l>We come to ſecond what our meſſage ſpake;</l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Jacob</hi> ſaid, yer he enjoy'd on high</l>
               <l>The bleſſings purchas'd by his lamed thigh;</l>
               <l>This in my name to <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſpeak, pray blot</l>
               <l>Thy Brethrens ſin (if it be not forgot)</l>
               <l>From thy remembrance, ſince they are convinc'd,</l>
               <l>And their Souls in repentant tears are rinc'd;</l>
               <pb n="75" facs="tcp:57741:40"/>
               <l>Trample not grief, guilt is a greater ſcourge</l>
               <l>That can revenge inflict, or Juſtice urge;</l>
               <l>'Tis true, the fault was great, and to be brief,</l>
               <l>Such as me thinks yet ſtartles my belief;</l>
               <l>Yet think not on revenge, their fault forget,</l>
               <l>And let not rage uſurp mild mercies ſeat;</l>
               <l>This did our Father bid, before his death;</l>
               <l>Yer Angells ſuck'd his Soul out with his breath;</l>
               <l>And now we hope, our fault did not ſo harden</l>
               <l>Thy heart, but tears may melt it to my pardon.</l>
               <l>Huge winds, they ſay, are ſtill'd by little rain,</l>
               <l>Then let not all our tears thus fall in vain,</l>
               <l>Thou at firſt ſight, we hope, was't reconcil'd,</l>
               <l>For ever ſince thy carriage hath been mild;</l>
               <l>And if yet mercy in thy Breſt bear ſway,</l>
               <l>Our hopes are anchor'd in a happy Bay.</l>
               <l>If not — but then their paſſion grew ſo high,</l>
               <l>That with th' <hi>Apoſiopeſis</hi> of a ſigh</l>
               <l>They there muſt ſtop; to whom quoth <hi>Joſeph</hi> thus,</l>
               <l>I know already what you would diſcuſs;</l>
               <l>'Tis true, your fact was groſs, and ſince y'are come,</l>
               <l>If you want tears, I here will lend you ſome</l>
               <l>For to lament it, God did you prevent,</l>
               <l>And unto good did wreſt your bad intent,</l>
               <l>Who hath ſo many ſav'd alive by one</l>
               <l>Unworthy perſon as you ſee is done;</l>
               <l>I long for no revenge, but that you ſentence</l>
               <l>Your ſin to death by an unfeign'd repentance;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Tears are the blood I thirst for,</hi> ſince to God</l>
               <l>Belongs revenge, I'll not uſurp his rod;</l>
               <l>Yet ſince you fear I will revenge your deed,</l>
               <l>That falſe ſuggeſtion doth from guilt proceed;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>For though there be no cauſe, yet buſie guilt</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Still holds her hand upon her Daggers hilt,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Envy doth burn like fire,</hi> and then no doubt</l>
               <l>But once in ſeventeen years it would break out;</l>
               <l>But yet, thus may your buſie guilt inſiſt,</l>
               <l>My cords of friendſhip, you may doubt, were twiſt</l>
               <pb n="76" facs="tcp:57741:41"/>
               <l>Upon my Fathers heart-ſtrings, and guilt durſt</l>
               <l>Infer, perchance, both were together burſt,</l>
               <l>Fear not my Brethren, this the end ſhall prove</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>That guilt's a traitour which miſconſtrues love;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Doubt no cloſe malice, fear no poys'nous rancour,</l>
               <l>But in this Boſome let your hopes caſt anchor,</l>
               <l>I'll nouriſh you, reſpect you little ones,</l>
               <l>And when I die the like will charge my Sons;</l>
               <l>With ſuch advice as this you may ſuppoſe</l>
               <l>Mild <hi>Ioſeph</hi> did his ſatisfaction cloſe;</l>
               <l>Ev'n ſo as theſe, Gods Saints do never ceaſe,</l>
               <l>Till through repentance they have purchas'd peace,</l>
               <l>I in Gods mercy ioy, that he did die</l>
               <l>A ſacrifice for me yer I was I,</l>
               <l>Yet can I not but grieve, and grieving mourn,</l>
               <l>That I him crucifi'd yer I was born,</l>
               <l>Nay greater cauſe of grief, for, I'm the <hi>Iew,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>And him each minute crucifie anew,</l>
               <l>My ſighes ſhould wing me to ſome Hermites Cave,</l>
               <l>Where with my nayles I'd hourly dig my grave,</l>
               <l>And there would live a ſorrowfull Recluſe,</l>
               <l>Tears ſhould be <hi>Helicon,</hi> and grief my Muſe,</l>
               <l>And as an <hi>Anch'ret</hi> would my ſelf immure,</l>
               <l>Yet live in tears a gawdy <hi>Epicure.</hi>
               </l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>When <hi>Ioſeph</hi> fully pardon'd had this crime,</l>
               <l>Admit a certain Intervall of time,</l>
               <l>When Fortune <hi>(ſerving, whom ſhe can't ſeduce)</hi>
               </l>
               <l>As proud of his acceptance, grew profuſe</l>
               <l>T'wards <hi>Ioſeph</hi> in her favours, which he took</l>
               <l>Still with a thankfull, not ambitious look;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Vertue commandeth Fortune, and doth clip</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Her wings, or holds her like an anchor'd ſhip;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Nor doubted he, leſt that with giddy changes,</l>
               <l>She ſhould vacillate in her wonted ranges,</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>God who</hi> Alph' <hi>and</hi> Omega <hi>is, is love</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Which ſtill doth</hi> Alpha <hi>and</hi> Omega <hi>prove;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Thus <hi>Ioſeph</hi> long in honour liv'd, the ſtrength</l>
               <l>Of whoſe old age extended to that length,</l>
               <pb n="77" facs="tcp:57741:41"/>
               <l>That his Poſterity to three degrees</l>
               <l>Deſcent he ſaw, and on his aged knees</l>
               <l>Were <hi>Machirs</hi> children brought, <hi>Manaſſeh's</hi> Son;</l>
               <l>So might he boaſt as <hi>Iacob</hi> once had done,</l>
               <l>Who comming one o'r <hi>Iordan,</hi> was increaſt,</l>
               <l>When he came back, a Nation at the leaſt.</l>
            </lg>
            <lg>
               <l>Now as the glorious Sun, who proudly oft</l>
               <l>Hath rid in triumph through the azurd loft,</l>
               <l>Anon meets an <hi>Eclips,</hi> which, in a brook,</l>
               <l>If view'd, affronts him with a gloomy look,</l>
               <l>So death (which makes a falling-Star of each,</l>
               <l>Although he mount unto the higheſt reach,</l>
               <l>And altitude of honour in his Sphere)</l>
               <l>Began to threaten <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with ſuch fear;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Rude death eſteems not honour, and Fate dooms</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>With equall ſentence Monarchs and their Grooms;</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Shuffles the Beggers ſcabs, and Ladies paint</hi>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Into a clod, nor Villain knowes nor Saint,</hi>
               </l>
               <l>So <hi>Ioſeph</hi> with the mean'ſt of <hi>Adams</hi> race</l>
               <l>Muſt feel th'arreſt of Deaths imperious Mace;</l>
               <l>When Fates black-bed-roul of diſeaſes 'gan</l>
               <l>T'aſſault the ſuburbs of his inward man;</l>
               <l>He (conſcious of his weakneſs) 'gan to doubt</l>
               <l>His Souls frail manſion could not long hold out;</l>
               <l>Wherefore his Brethren he, as one convenes,</l>
               <l>To whom, Sirs, I perceive what heaven means,</l>
               <l>For death (Gods Bayliff) with his Ebbon Scepter</l>
               <l>Stands ready to arreſt me as his debtor;</l>
               <l>Nought but my life acquits me, and each day</l>
               <l>Preſents my ſenſes with ſome new decay;</l>
               <l>Now Brethren, ſince you know my youthfull Dreams</l>
               <l>(Th'event can witneſs) were no idle theams,</l>
               <l>I'll ſpeak a truth too now, but it propounds</l>
               <l>Its burthen to your thoughts on ſurer grounds;</l>
               <l>'Tis truth, as if 'twere by the heavens hoaſts</l>
               <l>Proclaim'd, and witneſs't by our Fathers Ghoſts;</l>
               <l>That God will ſure, in his appoined time,</l>
               <l>To <hi>Can'an</hi> bring you back, your Native clime,</l>
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:57741:42"/>
               <l>Which <hi>Abr'ham, Jſaack,</hi> and to <hi>Jacob</hi> both,</l>
               <l>He gave by promiſe, and confirm'd by oath,</l>
               <l>Then do not my expiring ſpirit grieve,</l>
               <l>Nor forfeit <hi>Can'an</hi> by your unbelief;</l>
               <l>Believ't, as if each of you (as an heir</l>
               <l>Unto Gods promiſe) now breath'd <hi>Can'ans</hi> air;</l>
               <l>Record it on your Souls, in after years</l>
               <l>Let theſe my words ſtill echo in your ears;</l>
               <l>And when you ſee th'event doth not fall ſhort</l>
               <l>Of expectation, ſwear for to tranſport</l>
               <l>My bones with you to <hi>Can'an,</hi> for I luſt</l>
               <l>To be diſſolved with my Fathers duſt;</l>
               <l>So <hi>Joſeph</hi> yeelded to the Fates, ſo old,</l>
               <l>That he an hundred and ten years had told;</l>
               <l>Did all the Muſes Springs unto my brain</l>
               <l>Pay Tribute, as all Rivers to the Main;</l>
               <l>I could not weep him as he was, nor fits</l>
               <l>My creeping ſtile with <hi>Egypts</hi> tow'ring wits;</l>
               <l>Yet thus conceive they mourn'd, th' <hi>Aſtrologers</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Began to curſe the baſe-revolting Stars;</l>
               <l>Could one command the <hi>Sun,</hi> he'd make him burn</l>
               <l>As an obſequious Tapor on his Urn;</l>
               <l>The <hi>Moon</hi> a ſecond, then unto his Hearſe</l>
               <l>The yeſty Sea ſhould pay its brackiſh tears;</l>
               <l>A third the <hi>Orbs,</hi> then he would make them meet</l>
               <l>On earth in honour for his Winding ſheet;</l>
               <l>A fourth the <hi>Air,</hi> then ſhould ſome Meteors ſhine</l>
               <l>Like to a Fun'rall lamp ſtand o'r <hi>his</hi> ſhrine;</l>
               <l>A fift the <hi>Earth,</hi> then ſhould her teeming womb</l>
               <l>Spread a continued <hi>May</hi> about his Tomb;</l>
               <l>A ſixth command the <hi>Fire,</hi> then he would bid</l>
               <l>A ne'r to-be-extinguiſh'd <hi>Pyramid</hi>
               </l>
               <l>Blaze on his Hearſe; A ſeventh would ſet forth</l>
               <l>Fit <hi>Hieroglyphicks</hi> to deſcribe his worth;</l>
               <l>
                  <hi>Pharaoh</hi> deveſted of his Kingly State</l>
               <l>In mourning wailes <hi>Zaphnath-Paaneahs</hi> fate,</l>
               <l>The princely Prieſts lament, and <hi>Iſis</hi> Cow</l>
               <l>Within her Temple did in mourning low.</l>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:57741:42"/>
               <l>Th'embalming Doctor not at all forbears,</l>
               <l>But with his Odours doth commix his tears;</l>
               <l>One, in commemoration of his alms</l>
               <l>With <hi>them</hi> his name as with ſweet odour balms;</l>
               <l>Grief witty grew in ſome, each day his years</l>
               <l>Some vie with ſighes, and ſome, his months with tears;</l>
               <l>'Twere infinite to quote their Fun'rall Odes,</l>
               <l>Endleſs for to deſcribe their mourning Modes;</l>
               <l>Fit Mourners were they all, whom you might ſee,</l>
               <l>Nature had deck'd in mourning <hi>Cap-a-pe:</hi>
               </l>
               <l>But this large task had dull'd my tyred Muſe,</l>
               <l>My fingers are benum'd, my Pen's obtuſe,</l>
               <l>Leave him in <hi>Egypt,</hi> where on this Divorce</l>
               <l>Worms ſweetly fed on his embalmed Courſe.</l>
            </lg>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
